<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xml:lang="EN" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?origin publisher?><?properties no_embargo?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Theor Appl Genet</journal-id><journal-title>TAG. Theoretical and Applied Genetics. Theoretische Und Angewandte Genetik</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0040-5752</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-2242</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2705721</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1039</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-009-1039-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mapping of loci from <italic>Solanum lycopersicoides</italic> conferring resistance or susceptibility to <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> in tomato</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Daozhan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>Wendy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gokirmak</surname><given-names>Tufan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chetelat</surname><given-names>Roger T.</given-names></name><address><phone>+1-530-7526726</phone><fax>+1-530-7529659</fax><email>trchetelat@ucdavis.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stotz</surname><given-names>Henrik U.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Horticulture, Oregon State University, Corvallis, OR 97331 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>School of Medicine, University of Maryland, Baltimore, MD 21201 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Plant Molecular and Cellular Biology Program, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611 USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Plant Sciences, University of California, Davis, CA 95616 USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>RIKEN Plant Science Center, Yokohama, Kanagawa 230-0045 Japan </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p>Communicated by I. Paran.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2009</year></pub-date><volume>119</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2009</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2009</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract xml:lang="EN"><p>Cultivated tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum,</italic> syn. <italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>) is susceptible to the necrotrophic ascomycete and causal agent of gray mold, <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>. Resistance to this fungal pathogen is elevated in wild relatives of tomato, including <italic>Solanum lycopersicoides</italic>. An introgression line population (IL) containing chromosomal segments of <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> within the background of tomato cv. VF36 was used to screen the genome for foliar resistance and susceptibility to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. Based on this screen, putative quantitative trait loci (QTL) were identified, five for resistance and two for susceptibility. Four resistance QTL decreased infection frequency while the fifth reduced lesion diameter. One susceptibility QTL increased infection frequency whereas the other increased lesion diameter. Overlapping chromosomal segments provided strong evidence for partial resistance on chromosomes 1 and 9 and for elevated susceptibility on chromosome 11. Segregation analysis confirmed the major resistance QTL on the long arm of chromosome 1 and susceptibility on chromosome 11. Linkage of partial resistance to chromosome 9 could not be confirmed. The usefulness of these data for resistance breeding and for map-based cloning of foliar resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> is discussed.</p></abstract><custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag 2009</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> (teleomorph: <italic>Botryotina fuckeldiana</italic> (de Bary) Whetzel) is a necrotrophic ascomycete that attacks more than 200 host species (Elad et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2004</xref>). This fungus infects various fruit, flower, and vegetable crops in the field and/or after harvest. The cultivated tomato, <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> (formerly <italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>), is an agronomically important host, but variation for resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> among cultivars is small. Sources for resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> have therefore been sought among wild relatives of tomato. <italic>Solanum lycopersicoides</italic> exhibits high resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> (Rick <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1987</xref>; Rick and Chetelat <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">1995</xref>, Chetelat et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1997</xref>). Importantly, accession LA2951, which was used to develop a population of introgression lines (ILs) (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>), proved to express strong foliar resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> (Guimaraes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2004</xref>).</p><p>Other resistance traits are important for tomato production. Specifically for greenhouse production, stem resistance is a critical trait because pruning provides sites for fungal penetration. Hence, <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic> (formerly <italic>L. hirsutum</italic>) and <italic>Solanum neorickii</italic> (formerly <italic>L. parviflorum</italic>) have been used to identify quantitative trait loci (QTL) for stem resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2008</xref>). QTL mapping has also been done in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (Denby et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2004</xref>; Rowe and Kliebenstein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2008</xref>) and, although the genes that are responsible for quantitative resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> remain at large, camalexin has been shown to contribute to defense against this fungus (Kliebenstein et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2005</xref>; Rowe and Kliebenstein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2008</xref>). Approximately half of the resistance QTL recently identified were associated with camalexin accumulation (Rowe and Kliebenstein <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2008</xref>). <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> studies provide valuable background information that may aid in the identification of candidate genes that control resistance QTL in crop species such as tomato. The relationship to induced phytoalexin biosynthesis is particular intriguing in light of rishitin&#x02019;s role in UV protection of fruits against <italic>B. cinerea</italic> (Charles et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2008</xref>).</p><p>The objectives of the present study were to locate resistance factors from <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> using a nearly complete set of ILs. Based on a genome-wide screen for foliar resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>, three chromosomal regions were selected for further characterization in segregating progeny. The results presented herein establish the ILs as a potentially useful resource for <italic>B. cinerea</italic> resistance breeding in tomato.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Biological material</title><p>Introgression lines (ILs) of an original backcross <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> cv. &#x02018;VF36&#x02019;&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>Solanum lycopersicoides</italic> &#x02018;LA2951&#x02019; were used for linkage mapping of resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. The development and description of this population of ILs have been reported (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>). Seeds of the IL&#x02019;s and parental lines as well as in vitro-propagated clones of the F<sub>1</sub> hybrid were provided by the Tomato Genetics Resource Center (TGRC), University of California, Davis. <italic>B. cinerea</italic> strain B05.10 was a gift of Jan van Kan (Wageningen University, The Netherlands).</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Growth conditions</title><p>Seeds were treated with bleach (Guimaraes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2004</xref>) and sown in soil (Sunshine Mix SB40, Sungrow). Plants were grown in a greenhouse with supplemental lighting. Day-time and night-time temperatures were set at 21 and 16&#x000b0;C, respectively. Slow release fertilizer (Osmocote 15-9-12) was added to the soil after 1&#x000a0;month of growth. Seedlings were grown for a minimum of 6&#x02013;8&#x000a0;weeks prior to leaf removal for inoculation trials. A completely randomized design was used to grow seedlings in 5&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;5 flats consisting of 0.5&#x000a0;l pots. Multiple flats were used per experiment. Consecutive numbers were given to the seedlings that were planted. It was, therefore possible to conduct &#x0201c;blind&#x0201d; assays because identification of genotypes was avoided.</p><p><italic>B. cinerea</italic> was grown on potato dextrose agar from conidia stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C. The fungus was grown in darkness for 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days and then exposed to fluorescent light (34&#x000a0;&#x003bc;mol&#x000a0;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x000a0;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) to promote sporulation. Conidia were harvested according to published protocols (Benito et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">1998</xref>; Guimaraes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2004</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Foliar inoculation</title><p>For the genome wide screen, a minimum of five and ten individuals per homozygous and heterozygous IL were screened for resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>, respectively. The youngest, fully expanded leaves (typically the fourth leaf from the apex) were detached from the plant and inserted into moist florist foam to maintain turgidity. Prior to inoculation, conidia (10<sup>6</sup>&#x000a0;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) were incubated in Gamborg&#x02019;s medium containing 10&#x000a0;mM sucrose and 10&#x000a0;mM potassium phosphate, pH 6 for 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;h at room temperature. A total of ten droplets (10<sup>3</sup>&#x000a0;conidia&#x000a0;inoculum<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) were applied per leaf. Inoculated leaves were maintained in clear plastic boxes at room temperature under saturating humidity and a 12&#x000a0;h light/12&#x000a0;h dark regime at 34&#x000a0;&#x003bc;mol&#x000a0;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x000a0;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Each box contained both <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> &#x02018;VF36&#x02019; and <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> &#x02018;LA2951&#x02019; as controls. Lesions were evaluated 2&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days after inoculation based on two parameters. First, the frequency of lesion expansion was based on the ability of the fungus to spread beyond the initial necrotic region that is confined to a diameter of 2&#x000a0;mm. This assessment provides an indicator of healthy versus diseased leaf tissues. Second, lesion diameters were measured using a caliper.</p><p>For the marker cosegregation analysis a minimum of 50 segregating progeny of the IL&#x02019;s were inoculated using the same inoculation procedure, but with two modifications. A total of ten droplets (5&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;conidia&#x000a0;inoculum<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) were applied to each leaf, and the frequency and diameter of lesions expanding more than 3&#x000a0;mm were recorded.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The SAS (Cary, NC, USA) program package was used to analyze all of the data. Data analysis of the frequency of expanding lesions was based on a binomial distribution using a generalized linear model (GENMOD). Average numbers of infections per leaf over 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days period (3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;days for the cosegregation test) were used as response variables per ten inoculations. IL was used as a covariate and the model was based on a logistic regression. The DSCALE option was used to limit overdispersion of the model.</p><p>The fixed effect model of an analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to determine differences in lesion diameter among ILs. Levene&#x02019;s Test was used to assess the homogeneity of variances and only if the data passed this test, contrasts and least squares means (LSMEANS) were used to identify significant differences among means. Each date of evaluation was tested separately.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>DNA Extraction</title><p>For Southern blot and CAPS marker analysis, DNA extraction was performed according to the protocol of Miklas et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1993</xref>) with minor modifications. DNA samples were quantified using a UV fluorimeter (Hoefer).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Marker analysis</title><p>Southern blots were prepared by digesting DNA from the ILs, VF36, LA2951, and F<sub>1</sub> with <italic>Eco</italic>RI followed by electrophoresis on 1% agarose gels. PCR primers derived from cloned and sequenced tomato RFLP&#x02019;s (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) were used to amplify fragments from the VF36 parent. Amplification conditions were optimized using a gradient thermocycler (BioRad) to determine appropriate annealing temperatures (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The PCR profile consisted of a 3&#x000a0;min denaturing at 94&#x000b0;C followed by 35 cycles of 30&#x000a0;s at 94&#x000b0;C, 45&#x000a0;s annealing, and 2&#x000a0;min at 72&#x000b0;C, a final extension step at 72&#x000b0;C for 7&#x000a0;min, and then held at 4&#x000b0;C. Fragments were gel purified and labeled with the AlkPhos labeling kit (Amersham Biosciences). Hybridization and signal detection were performed using the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p><p>CAPS markers were generated by PCR amplification of the parents and F1 using the same RFLP primers, followed by restriction digests of aliquots of the amplification products with enzymes, such as BamHI, BsrDI, DraIII, HaeIII, HindIII, NotI, and XhoI. After visualization on agarose gels, the restriction enzymes that allowed identification of the parental and F1 genotypes were used for subsequent genotyping of the IL progeny (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Screening of the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> genome for foliar resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic></title><p><italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> ILs were screened for resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> over a period of more than 2&#x000a0;years (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Seven trials were conducted to evaluate all of the ILs, which together represent more than 96% of the map units in the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> genome (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>). A total of 58 ILs were tested, 49 of those belonging to a &#x02018;primary set&#x02019; of ILs (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>). This allowed for complete coverage of the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> genome with the exception of a region encompassing the marker TG65 on chromosome 4 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and two additional small segments on chromosomes 2 and 3 (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>). Given that <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> restricts the formation of expanding lesions (Guimaraes et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2004</xref>), all of the seven trials included data on frequencies of lesion expansion (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In addition, diameters of expanding lesions were recorded during the last four trials (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Identification of <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> introgression lines with altered resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Screen</th><th align="left">Season Year</th><th align="left">LA</th><th align="left">IL<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">RIF<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left"><sup>b, c</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">Winter 03</td><td char="." align="char">4268</td><td align="left">9A</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">0.53</td><td char="." align="char">6.81</td><td char="." align="char">0.0091</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">Summer 03</td><td char="." align="char">4233</td><td align="left">1B</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td char="." align="char">0.65</td><td char="." align="char">13.2</td><td char="." align="char">0.0003</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">Summer 03</td><td char="." align="char">4237</td><td align="left">2</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td char="." align="char">0.6</td><td char="." align="char">15.94</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">Summer 03</td><td char="." align="char">4269</td><td align="left">9B</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td char="." align="char">0.73</td><td char="." align="char">9.31</td><td char="." align="char">0.0023</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">Summer 03</td><td char="." align="char">4242</td><td align="left">3</td><td char="." align="char">10</td><td char="." align="char">0.35</td><td char="." align="char">9.35</td><td char="." align="char">0.0022</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">Summer 03</td><td char="." align="char">4279</td><td align="left">11C</td><td char="." align="char">10</td><td char="." align="char">1.62</td><td char="." align="char">8.75</td><td char="." align="char">0.0031</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">Summer 04</td><td char="." align="char">4264</td><td align="left">8A</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td char="." align="char">1.27</td><td char="." align="char">4.78</td><td char="." align="char">0.0299</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">Summer 04</td><td char="." align="char">3866</td><td align="left">1A</td><td char="." align="char">7</td><td char="." align="char">2.19</td><td char="." align="char">7.45</td><td char="." align="char">0.0063</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">Summer 04</td><td char="." align="char">4234</td><td align="left">1C</td><td char="." align="char">11</td><td char="." align="char">0.53</td><td char="." align="char">5.91</td><td char="." align="char">0.0151</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">Summer 04</td><td char="." align="char">4277</td><td align="left">11A</td><td char="." align="char">17</td><td char="." align="char">1.52</td><td char="." align="char">8.17</td><td char="." align="char">0.0043</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">Summer 05</td><td char="." align="char">4233</td><td align="left">1B</td><td char="." align="char">25</td><td char="." align="char">0.77</td><td char="." align="char">6.72</td><td char="." align="char">0.0095</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">Summer 05</td><td char="." align="char">4234</td><td align="left">1C</td><td char="." align="char">20</td><td char="." align="char">0.77</td><td char="." align="char">5.84</td><td char="." align="char">0.0156</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">Summer 05</td><td char="." align="char">4268</td><td align="left">9A</td><td char="." align="char">10</td><td char="." align="char">0.5</td><td char="." align="char">21.2</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Statistically significant differences in frequency of infection are based on GENMOD</p><p><sup>a</sup>Introgression lines are designated by chromosome number and a letter based on chromosomal location from top to bottom</p><p><sup>b</sup>Relative Infection frequency in comparison to <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. VF36</p><p><sup>c</sup><italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup>-tests are based on contrasts between individual introgression lines and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. VF36</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Screen of the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> genome for resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. Introgression lines of the <bold>a</bold> primary and <bold>b</bold> secondary set were screened. Columns indicate chromosomes with markers (not to scale), rows indicate introgression lines. <italic>Lines in bold</italic> were tested at least twice. <italic>Italicized lines in bold</italic> were only scored as hyper-resistant once out of two trials (IL-2) or twice out of three trials (IL-9B). <italic>Solid</italic> and <italic>hatched boxes</italic> indicate homozygous and heterozygous segments, respectively. Reduction in frequency of infection and rate of lesion expansion are color-coded <italic>red</italic> and <italic>yellow</italic>, respectively. Elevation in frequency of infection and rate of lesion expansion are color-coded <italic>blue</italic> and <italic>purple</italic>, respectively. The consensus shown beneath all introgression lines shows the location of resistance and susceptibility QTL. In each of these indicated consensus regions differences in phenotypes outnumbered similarities to <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. VF36</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2009_1039_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Identification of <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> introgression lines with altered resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Screen</th><th align="left">Season year</th><th align="left">LA</th><th align="left">IL<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">LER<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic> value<sup>c</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic> value</th><th align="left">Transformation<sup>d</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">Winter 04</td><td char="." align="char">4246</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">0.57</td><td char="." align="char">4.94</td><td char="." align="char">0.0275</td><td align="left">Log</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">Winter 04</td><td char="." align="char">4278</td><td char="." align="char">11B</td><td char="." align="char">10</td><td char="." align="char">1.45</td><td char="." align="char">5.33</td><td char="." align="char">0.0221</td><td align="left">Log</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">Winter 04</td><td char="." align="char">4281</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td char="." align="char">11</td><td char="." align="char">1.57</td><td char="." align="char">4.52</td><td char="." align="char">0.0349</td><td align="left">Log</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">Summer 04</td><td char="." align="char">4249</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">1.33</td><td char="." align="char">4.39</td><td char="." align="char">0.0405</td><td align="left">Inv</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">Summer 05</td><td char="." align="char">3889</td><td char="." align="char">8B</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td char="." align="char">1.32</td><td char="." align="char">4.06</td><td char="." align="char">0.0467</td><td align="left">Log</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Statistically significant differences in rates of lesion expansion are based on ANOVA</p><p><sup>a</sup>Introgression lines are designated by chromosome number and a letter based on chromosomal location from top to bottom</p><p><sup>b</sup>Lesion expansion rates as compared to <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. VF36</p><p><sup>c</sup>Contrasts were used to determine statistical differences between means of introgression lines and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. VF36</p><p><sup>d</sup>Logarithmic and inverse transformations were used to fulfill the homogeneity criterion of variances</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>CAPS markers used for genotyping introgression lines (ILs)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Marker<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left">Chromosome/IL</th><th align="left">Primer sequences (5&#x02032;-3&#x02032;)<sup>1</sup></th><th align="left">Size<sup>b</sup> (bp)</th><th align="left">Anneal. temp. (&#x000b0;C)</th><th align="left">Enzyme</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">TG17</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">1B</td><td align="left">cggctgtgtacgtatctgga</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">2,200</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Hind</italic>III</td></tr><tr><td align="left">aaaatcaattgaaccggctgt</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">TG18</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">9A</td><td align="left">ctcaagctccagctgtttcc</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">1,700</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">58</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Bam</italic>HI</td></tr><tr><td align="left">gctccttctgcaatgggtaa</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">TG46</td><td align="left" rowspan="2">11C</td><td align="left">atcccaacctctgagcacac</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">1,400</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">62</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Hae</italic>III</td></tr><tr><td align="left">gttcctggaaccgatattgc</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Marker and primer sequences were obtained from Solanaceae Genomics Network database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sgn.cornell.edu">http://www.sgn.cornell.edu</ext-link>)</p><p><sup>b</sup>PCR product size before digestion with restriction enzyme</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Six <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> ILs were significantly more resistant to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> than <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> &#x02018;VF36&#x02019; when frequency of infection was used as a variable. Three of these lines were verified in two independent trials. These lines are referred to as IL-1B and IL-1C because they contain introgressed segments from chromosome 1, and as IL-9A with an introgressed segment of chromosome 9. Another line, IL-9B, was more resistant to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> than &#x02018;VF36&#x02019; when 16 individuals were tested during the second trial (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), but this line was not significantly different from the tomato parent when eight or five individuals were tested in 2003 and 2005, respectively. IL-9A and IL-9B share a polymorphism for the marker TG9 and, therefore, contain a region of overlap (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>). Nevertheless, the phenotype of IL-9A was more robust and the magnitude of the phenotypic effect was larger in this line than in IL-9B. This suggests either that a susceptibility locus is located on the chromosomal segment that was introgressed into IL-9B or that more than one resistance locus is present on the region that was introgressed into IL-9A. The former explanation appears more likely because line IL-9C (LS10-6A) contains part of the chromosomal region of IL-9B and has a phenotype that is similar to tomato &#x02018;VF36&#x02019; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Moreover, IL-3, which shares a region containing TG18 with IL-9A, is resistant to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. These data suggest that a quantitative trait locus (QTL) is located near the &#x02018;top&#x02019; of chromosome 9. IL-2 was evaluated as resistant to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> when 16 individuals were analyzed during the summer but not when seven individuals were analyzed during the winter of 2003. It is possible that there is a seasonal influence or resistance at this locus. We have observed that resistance of <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> can weaken during winter months under conditions in Oregon, but we have not analyzed this phenomenon further. Collectively, these data suggest that QTL controlling frequency of infection by <italic>B. cinerea</italic> are located on chromosomes 1, 2, and 9, and possibly on chromosome 3.</p><p>Four <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> ILs were significantly more susceptible to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> than <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> &#x02018;VF36&#x02019; when frequency of infection was evaluated. IL-11A and IL-11C both contain introgressed segments located on chromosome 11 and share segments with IL-11B, an IL which is more susceptible to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> than the tomato parent based on lesion expansion (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). A higher frequency of expanding lesions was also observed for lines IL-1A and IL-8A.</p><p>Besides IL-11B, three other lines, IL-5, IL-8B, and IL-12, were more susceptible than tomato &#x02018;VF36&#x02019; when lesion expansion was evaluated (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Based on the consensus of all lines evaluated, a susceptibility QTL may be present on chromosome 5 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), but this inference is solely based on the phenotype of IL-5 because no other line contained the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> polymorphism for CD64 (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>).</p><p>IL-4 was scored as more resistant to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> than &#x02018;VF36&#x02019; based on lesion expansion data. The consensus data of all the lines suggests a resistance QTL is linked to CT50 on chromosome 4. In hindsight, it would have been advisable to include LA4250 (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>) for comparison with IL-4 to verify this prediction. However, line LA4250 contains additional introgressed segments from chromosomes 5, 8, and 9. LA4250 was not included in the original screen because the introgressed region was covered by IL-4.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Segregation analysis of a foliar <italic>B. cinerea</italic> resistance QTL on chromosome 1</title><p>Based on genome-wide analysis of resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>, a QTL altering infection frequency was identified on chromosome 1 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Fewer expanding lesions were observed when accession IL-1B was challenged with <italic>B. cinerea</italic> compared to tomato cv. &#x02018;VF36&#x02019;. In order to determine whether this difference in frequency of infection was linked to marker TG17 on chromosome 1, a segregation analysis was performed in the progeny of heterozygous IL-1B. TG17 is located at the bottom of an approximately 43&#x000a0;cM-long segment that has been introgressed into IL-1B (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>). Segments introgressed from <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> recombine at only a very low rate with corresponding tomato chromosomes (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2006</xref>). Recombination rates are generally only 0&#x02013;10% of expected frequencies (i.e. 90&#x02013;100% suppressed). In the absence of significant recombination, single markers are sufficient to genotype each IL in segregating populations.</p><p>Segregation of TG17 was not significantly different from the Mendelian 1:2:1 expectation. Individuals carrying the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> allele were significantly more resistant to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> both in terms of infection frequency and in terms of lesion diameter (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Resistance of the heterozygous progeny to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> appeared intermediate relative to homozygous segregants. Nevertheless, heterozygotes were significantly more resistant than homozygotes carrying the <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> allele (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Conversely, resistance of heterozygotes to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> was not significantly different from homozygotes carrying the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> allele. With respect to lesion diameter, no significant differences in resistance were observed between heterozygous and homozygous progenies, indicating that genetic control of this trait may be different from infection frequency.<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Segregation analysis of introgression line F<sub>2</sub> progeny</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">IL</th><th align="left">Genotype<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left">Infection freq.<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic> value<sup>c</sup></th><th align="left">% var.<sup>d</sup></th><th align="left">Lesion diameter (mm)<sup>e</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic> value</th><th align="left">% var.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">1B</td><td align="left">+/+</td><td char="(" align="char">6.9 (17)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="3">21.4</td><td char="(" align="char">6.2 (17)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="3">11.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">+/S</td><td char="(" align="char">4.9 (30)</td><td char="." align="char">0.0226</td><td char="(" align="char">5.3 (26)</td><td char="." align="char">0.1003</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S/S</td><td char="(" align="char">2.8 (8)</td><td char="." align="char">0.0009</td><td char="(" align="char">4.4 (6)</td><td char="." align="char">0.0318</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">9A</td><td align="left">+/+</td><td char="(" align="char">4.9 (27)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="3">4.0</td><td char="(" align="char">6.6 (24)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="3">6.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">+/S</td><td char="(" align="char">5.5 (17)</td><td char="." align="char">0.1952</td><td char="(" align="char">6.8 (17)</td><td char="." align="char">0.6163</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S/S</td><td char="(" align="char">3.8 (10)</td><td char="." align="char">0.3458</td><td char="(" align="char">5.9 (8)</td><td char="." align="char">0.2039</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">11C</td><td align="left">+/+</td><td char="(" align="char">4.7 (21)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">3.8</td><td char="(" align="char">5.2 (17)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">6.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">+/S</td><td char="(" align="char">5.8 (28)</td><td char="." align="char">0.1977</td><td char="(" align="char">6.4 (27)</td><td char="." align="char">0.0580</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>+/+&#x000a0;is homozygous for cv. VF36 allele, S/S is homozygous for <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> allele, and +/S is heterozygous</p><p><sup>b</sup>Infection frequency is the mean number of expanding lesions per leaf (10 inoculation droplets per leaf); values in parentheses are the numbers of F<sub>2</sub> progeny of each genotype included in the statistical analysis</p><p><sup>c</sup><italic>P</italic> values compare the +/S or S/S genotypes against the +/+ genotype</p><p><sup>d</sup>Percentage of phenotypic variation explained by each QTL in each F2 population</p><p><sup>e</sup>Lesion diameter is the mean diameter in mm of leaf lesions; values in parentheses are the numbers of F<sub>2</sub> progeny of each genotype included in the statistical analysis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Accession IL-1B apparently harbors a major QTL linked to marker TG17. Infection frequency of homozygotes for the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> allele was reduced by 55% relative to the difference between tomato cv. VF36 and <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> LA2951 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). This approximation compared favorably with estimates that were obtained during the genome-wide screen for <italic>B. cinerea</italic> resistance (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In the latter case, infection frequency was reduced by 45 and 23% during 2003 and 2005 seasons. More importantly, segregation analysis demonstrates that the QTL on chromosome 1 explains approximately 21% of the phenotypic variation (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). By comparison, the effect on lesion size was smaller (11% of the phenotypic variation) and not observed during the genome-wide screen, perhaps a result of the smaller sample size or lower expression of the trait during the 2005 season.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Segregation for resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> on chromosome 1. <bold>a</bold> Numbers of expanding lesions and <bold>b</bold> lesion diameters were scored among progeny of heterozygous IL-1B and compared to the parents LA2951 and VF36. Alleles of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. &#x02018;VF36&#x02019; and <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> line LA2951 are abbreviated + and S, respectively. Heterozygous +/S and homozygous +/+ and S/S individuals were identified using the CAPS marker TG17<italic>/Hind</italic>III. Means, standard errors, and sample sizes are indicated. Significant differences to +/+ genotypes are indicated at <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 (*) and <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001 (***)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2009_1039_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> is not linked to TG18 in IL-9A</title><p>Genome wide analysis of resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> indicated a QTL decreasing infection frequency on chromosome 9. To determine linkage between marker TG18 and this trait, homozygous IL-9A and cv. VF36 were crossed, then self-pollinated to generate a segregating population. TG18 is located 14&#x000a0;cM from the top of chromosome 9. The segment that has been introduced into IL-9A is approximately 18&#x000a0;cM in size (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>).</p><p>Segregation of TG18 in the F<sub>2</sub> progeny of IL-9A differed significantly from the 1:2:1 expectation. Marker segregation was skewed in favor of the allele from cultivated tomato. Infection frequency (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a) and lesion diameter (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b) did not significantly differ among the three genotypes that were defined by TG18 segregation. Nevertheless, all the three IL-9A genotypes were significantly more resistant to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> than cv. VF36. Both infection frequency and lesion diameter were reduced (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The magnitude of reduction in an infection frequency was similar to the 50 and 53% reduction observed during the genome-wide screen (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The progeny was not genotyped based on phenotype, but on molecular marker data. In the absence of discernible phenotypic segregation, the most parsimonious explanation is that this partial resistance locus is not linked to the segment on chromosome 9 but located elsewhere in the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> genome even though markers used by Canady et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>) did not detect the presence of other introgressed segments in IL-9A.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Segregation analysis for resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> on chromosome 9. <bold>a</bold> Numbers of expanding lesions and <bold>b</bold> log&#x000a0;N-transformed lesion diameters were scored among progeny of heterozygous IL-9A and compared to the parents LA2951 and VF36. +/+ is homozygous for the VF36 allele, S/S is homozygous for the LA2951 allele, and +/S is heterozygous based on CAPS marker TG18/<italic>Bam</italic>HI. Means, standard errors, and sample sizes are indicated</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2009_1039_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Analysis of a putative susceptibility locus linked to TG46 on chromosome 11</title><p>Genome wide analysis of the interactions between <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic>-derived ILs and <italic>B. cinerea</italic> indicated a susceptibility locus on chromosome 11. Marker TG46 was used to analyze segregation for susceptibility to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> in progeny of heterozygous line IL-11C. TG46 is located approximately in the middle of a ca. 50&#x000a0;cM segment introgressed into IL-11C. Surprisingly, seedlings homozygous for the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> allele were not recovered between germinating and surviving individuals. Segregation of TG46 was not significantly different from an expectation of 1:2:0. Although we do not know whether embryo lethality occurs in this genotype because we did not attempt embryo rescue, homozygosity at this locus still causes a selective disadvantage.</p><p>The remaining genotypes were analyzed for susceptibility to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Frequency of infection was not significantly different between genotypes that were heterozygous or homozygous for the <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> allele. Lesion diameters were elevated in the heterozygous genotype compared to individuals homozygous for the <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> allele and cv. VF36, but this difference was not statistically significant. It might be argued that a one-tailed test could be used based on the expectation of the genome-wide screen. In this case, the heterozygous genotype would be scored as susceptible. When compared to cv. VF36, susceptibility was clearly elevated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), probably a reflection of the larger number of cultivar seedlings tested. Lesion size was 25% larger in the case of IL-11C when compared in the heterozygous state to cv. VF36. Collectively, these data let us conclude that susceptibility locus exists on chromosome 11.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Segregation for susceptibility to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> on chromosome 11. Genotypes homozygous for the LA2951 allele were not recovered. <bold>a</bold> Numbers of expanding lesions and <bold>b</bold> lesion diameters were scored among the remaining progeny of heterozygous IL-11C and compared to the parents LA2951 and VF36. +/+ is homozygous for the VF36 alelle, and +/S is heterozygous based on the CAPS marker TG46<italic>/Hae</italic>III. Means, standard errors, and sample sizes are indicated. Significant difference to VF36 is indicated at <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01 (**)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2009_1039_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Analysis of foliar susceptibility to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> among 58 ILs derived from <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> has resulted in identification of four putative resistance QTL for infection frequency and one putative resistance QTL for lesion diameter. In addition, putative susceptibility QTL for infection frequency or lesion diameter was identified. Several of these loci are referred to <italic>Fbc</italic> for foliar <italic>B. cinerea</italic> resistance or susceptibility in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Synopsis of resistance and susceptibility loci mapped to chromosomes 1&#x02013;5 and to chromosome 11. The genetic map has previously been published (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>). <italic>Solid vertical bars</italic> delimit locations of putative foliar <italic>B. cinerea</italic> (<italic>Fbc</italic>) resistance QTL on chromosomes 1 through 4 or susceptibility QTL on chromosomes 5 and 11. Approximate locations of previously reported qualitative resistance genes (<italic>R</italic> genes) or resistance QTL (<italic>dashed vertical lines</italic> or <italic>underlined</italic>) are also shown. Resistance loci on chromosomes 3 and 4 have previously been designated (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2008</xref>); QTL3 and 4 were renamed to <italic>Snbc3</italic> and <italic>4</italic> in reference to <italic>Solanum neorickii</italic>. Following references assign remaining resistance loci: <italic>Cf9</italic> (Parniske et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1997</xref>), <italic>Rbcq1</italic> and <italic>2</italic> (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>), <italic>Cm1-1</italic> (Sandbrink et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1995</xref>), <italic>rx-2</italic> (Yu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1995</xref>), <italic>Tm-1</italic> (Young and Tanksley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1989</xref>), <italic>Bs4</italic> (Ballvora et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2001</xref>), <italic>Pto</italic> and <italic>Prf</italic> (Salmeron et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">1996</xref>), <italic>lb5b</italic> and <italic>lb11b</italic> (Brouwer and St Clair <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2004</xref>), <italic>Sm</italic> (Behare et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1991</xref>), and <italic>I2</italic> (Ori et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1994</xref>)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2009_1039_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Colocation of foliar <italic>B. cinerea</italic> resistance and susceptibility QTL with known resistance loci</title><p>Several of the putative foliar <italic>B. cinerea</italic> resistance QTL identified herein are linked to previously recognized QTL for stem resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. The closest association was observed between <italic>Fbc3</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) and <italic>Snbc3</italic>, the latter from <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2008</xref>). Although we did not find other regions of overlap, <italic>Fbc2</italic> and <italic>Fbc4</italic> are closely linked to <italic>Rbcq2</italic> and <italic>Rbcq4b</italic>, respectively (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>). Homologous QTL for stem resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> were previously identified (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2008</xref>), suggesting that a limited number of QTL specify resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> in different <italic>Solanum</italic> species. Collectively, data on stem resistance (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2008</xref>; Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>) and on foliar resistance from <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> presented here indicate genomic specialization for <italic>B. cinerea</italic> resistance on chromosomes 1, 2, 3, 4, and 9 of <italic>Solanum</italic>. Nevertheless, comparative analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) also demonstrates that stem and foliar resistance are controlled by separate QTL. The map locations of resistance genes and QTL controlling interactions with other pathogens are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, but due to the large sizes of introgressed <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> fragments, any inferences about potential coincidences would be speculative.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Confirmed QTL for foliar resistance or susceptibility to <italic>B. cinerea</italic></title><p>Three putative QTL were characterized further because overlapping segments of ILs strongly suggested the presence of loci that have a quantitative influence on interactions with <italic>B. cinerea</italic> in leaves. <italic>Fbc1</italic>, a major QTL for foliar resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>, was identified in this fashion. This QTL was initially identified based on its reduction of infection frequency (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). <italic>Fbc1</italic> explains approximately 21% of the phenotypic variation in susceptibility to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>, which is larger than the magnitudes of previously reported stem resistance QTL (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2008</xref>). Analysis of a segregating IL-1B population also revealed a significant difference in lesion diameter between homozygous progenies, but this effect was much smaller than the infection frequency (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The relatively small effect on lesion size probably explains why this trait was not detected in the previous genome-wide screen (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Based on the large effect on infection frequency, <italic>Fbc1</italic> would make a good candidate for fine-scale mapping and eventual cloning of the resistance gene. Although suppression of recombination in ILs represents a genetic barrier (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>), <italic>S. pennellii</italic> has successfully been used as a bridge species to overcome this barrier and increase the rate of recombination between <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> and cultivated tomato (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2006</xref>).</p><p>A second resistance QTL was examined in detail based on the observation that IL-9A and IL-9B, with overlapping fragments of chromosome 9, were more resistant to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. Surprisingly, segregation of resistance was not observed using marker TG18 in progeny of heterozygous IL-9A, although all of the progeny were more resistant than tomato cv. VF36 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). This suggests that the resistance locus either exists somewhere else in the genome or that linkage between TG18 and the QTL has been broken. With respect to the former possibility, it is interesting to note that markers used for mapping ILs were separated by 18.4&#x000a0;cM on average with a range of 2.5&#x02013;64&#x000a0;cM (Canady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>). Although Canady et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>) reported introgression of a single segment on chromosome 9 in IL-9A, it can therefore not be excluded that an unlinked small piece was introduced from the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> genome. This could explain our inability to detect segregation for partial resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> using TG18.</p><p>Genome wide screening for <italic>B. cinerea</italic> susceptibility indicated that the chromosomal region of <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> in IL-11C increases infection frequency (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). However, segregation analysis showed that <italic>Lbc11</italic> significantly increased lesion diameter. Lesion size was not evaluated during the primary screen. An effect on lesion diameter may, therefore, have been missed during this earlier assessment. The population size of the segregating progeny was larger than the number of individuals used for the primary screen. Quantitative differences in lesion diameter are therefore assumed to be reliable. Variability between disease incidence and lesion growth was also observed for QTL9 from <italic>S. neorickii</italic> (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2008</xref>). Although the authors argued that in their case QTL9 was expected to reduce disease incidence, the cause for different experimental observations in separate screens was not resolved. The size of the phenotypic effect appeared to be relatively small in the case of QTL9 (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2008</xref>). Similarly, <italic>Fbc11</italic> appeared to be a relatively minor QTL, at least in comparison to <italic>Fbc1</italic>. Thus, in the case of minor QTL, large samples appear to be needed to reliable assign resistance or susceptibility traits. However, in the case of <italic>Fbc11</italic> no surviving homozygotes for the <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> were recovered, possibly indicating a major defect-related to plant development and defense.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our studies confirm that <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> is a potent source of foliar resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. Several partially resistant ILs were identified in this study. These ILs could be used in combination with marker-assisted selection to develop improved tomato cultivars.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Rejane Guimar&#x000e3;es for advice in resistance screening. The California Tomato Commission provided financial support.</p><p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballvora</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackerveken</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schornack</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossier</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahaye</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonas</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic mapping and functional analysis of the tomato <italic>Bs4</italic> locus governing recognition of the <italic>Xanthomonas campestris</italic> pv. <italic>vesicatoria</italic> AvrBs4 protein</article-title><source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><year>2001</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI.2001.14.5.629</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ballvora A, Pierre M, van den Ackerveken G, Schornack S, Rossier O, Ganal M, Lahaye T, Bonas U (2001) Genetic mapping and functional analysis of the tomato Bs4 locus governing recognition of the Xanthomonas campestris pv. vesicatoria AvrBs4 protein. Mol Plant Microbe Interact 14:629&#x02013;638 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11332727</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behare</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Laterrot</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarfatti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Restriction-fragment-length-polymorphism mapping of the <italic>Stemphylium</italic> resistance gene in tomato</article-title><source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><year>1991</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>492</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Behare J, Laterrot H, Sarfatti M, Zamir D (1991) Restriction-fragment-length-polymorphism mapping of the Stemphylium resistance gene in tomato. Mol Plant Microbe Interact 4:489&#x02013;492 </citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benito</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Have</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van&#x02019;t Klooster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal and plant gene expression during synchronized infection of tomato leaves by <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic></article-title><source>Eur J Plant Pathol</source><year>1998</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008698116106</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Benito E, ten Have A, van&#x02019;t Klooster J, van Kan J (1998) Fungal and plant gene expression during synchronized infection of tomato leaves by Botrytis cinerea. Eur J Plant Pathol 104:207&#x02013;220 </citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brouwer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>St Clair</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine mapping of three quantitative trait loci for late blight resistance in tomato using near isogenic lines (NILs) and sub-NILs</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-003-1469-8</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Brouwer DJ, St Clair DA (2004) Fine mapping of three quantitative trait loci for late blight resistance in tomato using near isogenic lines (NILs) and sub-NILs. Theor Appl Genet 108:628&#x02013;638 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14586504</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canady</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meglic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chetelat</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A library of <italic>Solanum lycopersicoides</italic> introgression lines in cultivated tomato</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2005</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g05-032</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Canady MA, Meglic V, Chetelat RT (2005) A library of Solanum lycopersicoides introgression lines in cultivated tomato. Genome 48:685&#x02013;697 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16094436</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canady</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chetelat</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Homeologous recombination in <italic>Solanum lycopersicoides</italic> introgression lines of cultivated tomato</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>1775</fpage><lpage>1788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.106.065144</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Canady MA, Ji Y, Chetelat RT (2006) Homeologous recombination in Solanum lycopersicoides introgression lines of cultivated tomato. Genetics 174:1775&#x02013;1788 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17057228</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Makhlouf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arul</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological basis of UV-C-induced resistance to <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> in tomato fruit&#x02014;I. Role of pre- and post-challenge accumulation of the phytoalexin-rishitin</article-title><source>Postharvest Biol Technol</source><year>2008</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2007.05.013</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Charles MT, Mercier J, Makhlouf J, Arul J (2008) Physiological basis of UV-C-induced resistance to Botrytis cinerea in tomato fruit&#x02014;I. Role of pre- and post-challenge accumulation of the phytoalexin-rishitin. Postharvest Biol Technol 47:10&#x02013;20 </citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chetelat</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cisneros</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamoa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A male-fertile <italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>Solanum lycopersicoides</italic> hybrid enables direct backcrossing to tomato at the diploid level</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>1997</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1002958030799</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Chetelat RT, Cisneros P, Stamoa L, Rick CM (1997) A male-fertile Lycopersicon esculentum&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;Solanum lycopersicoides hybrid enables direct backcrossing to tomato at the diploid level. Euphytica 95:99&#x02013;108 </citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denby</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kliebenstein</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> susceptibility loci in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2004</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0960-7412.2004.02059.x</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Denby KJ, Kumar P, Kliebenstein DJ (2004) Identification of Botrytis cinerea susceptibility loci in Arabidopsis thaliana. Plant J 38:473&#x02013;486 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15086796</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elad</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tudzynski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Delen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic>Botrytis</italic>: biology, pathology, and control</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kluwer</publisher-name></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Elad Y, Williamson B, Tudzynski P, Delen N (2004) Botrytis: biology, pathology, and control. Kluwer, Dordrecht </citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finkers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Berloo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Have</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heusden</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>JAL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three QTLs for <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> resistance in tomato</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-006-0458-0</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Finkers R, van den Berg P, van Berloo R, ten Have A, van Heusden AW, van Kan JAL, Lindhout P (2007) Three QTLs for Botrytis cinerea resistance in tomato. Theor Appl Genet 114:585&#x02013;593 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17136515</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finkers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Berloo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer-Dekens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Have</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heusden</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative resistance to <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> from <italic>Solanum neorickii</italic></article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2008</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-007-9460-0</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Finkers R, Bai YL, van den Berg P, van Berloo R, Meijer-Dekens F, ten Have A, van Kan J, Lindhout P, van Heusden AW (2008) Quantitative resistance to Botrytis cinerea from Solanum neorickii. Euphytica 159:83&#x02013;92 </citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guimaraes</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chetelat</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Stotz</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance to <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> in <italic>Solanum lycopersicoides</italic> is dominant in hybrids with tomato, and involves induced hyphal death</article-title><source>Eur J Plant Pathol</source><year>2004</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:EJPP.0000010133.62052.e4</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Guimaraes RL, Chetelat RT, Stotz HU (2004) Resistance to Botrytis cinerea in Solanum lycopersicoides is dominant in hybrids with tomato, and involves induced hyphal death. Eur J Plant Pathol 110:13&#x02013;23 </citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kliebenstein</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Denby</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Secondary metabolites influence <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>/<italic>Botrytis</italic> interactions: variation in host production and pathogen sensitivity</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02508.x</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kliebenstein DJ, Rowe HC, Denby KJ (2005) Secondary metabolites influence Arabidopsis/Botrytis interactions: variation in host production and pathogen sensitivity. Plant J 44:25&#x02013;36 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16167893</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miklas</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Delorme</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of QTL conditioning resistance to white mold in snap bean</article-title><source>J Am Soc Hortic Sci</source><year>1993</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>570</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Miklas PN, Delorme R, Riley R (1993) Identification of QTL conditioning resistance to white mold in snap bean. J Am Soc Hortic Sci 128:564&#x02013;570 </citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ori</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Paran</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Aviv</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fluhr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genomic search for the gene conferring resistance to <italic>Fusarium</italic> wilt in tomato</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>1994</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00022520</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ori N, Paran I, Aviv D, Eshed Y, Tanksley S, Zamir D, Fluhr R (1994) A genomic search for the gene conferring resistance to Fusarium wilt in tomato. Euphytica 79:201&#x02013;204 </citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parniske</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel disease resistance specificities result from sequence exchange between tandemly repeated genes at the <italic>Cf-4/9</italic> locus of tomato</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1997</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>821</fpage><lpage>832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80470-5</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Parniske M, Hammond-Kosack KE, Goldstein C, Thomas CM, Jones DA (1997) Novel disease resistance specificities result from sequence exchange between tandemly repeated genes at the Cf-4/9 locus of tomato. Cell 91:821&#x02013;832 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9413991</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Nevins</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic resources in <italic>Lycopersicon</italic></article-title><source>Plant biology</source><year>1987</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Alan R. Liss</publisher-name><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rick C (1987) Genetic resources in Lycopersicon. In: Nevins DJ, Jones RA (eds) Plant biology. Alan R. Liss, New York, pp 17&#x02013;26 </citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chetelat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utilization of related wild species for tomato improvement</article-title><source>Acta Hort</source><year>1995</year><volume>412</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rick C, Chetelat R (1995) Utilization of related wild species for tomato improvement. Acta Hort 412:21&#x02013;38 </citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kliebenstein</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complex genetics control natural variation in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> resistance to <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2008</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>2237</fpage><lpage>2250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.108.091439</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rowe HC, Kliebenstein DJ (2008) Complex genetics control natural variation in Arabidopsis thaliana resistance to Botrytis cinerea. Genetics 180:2237&#x02013;2250 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18845849</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salmeron</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oldroyd</surname><given-names>GED</given-names></name><name><surname>Rommens</surname><given-names>CMT</given-names></name><name><surname>Scofield</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavelle</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahlbeck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Staskawicz</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tomato <italic>Prf</italic> is a member of the leucine-rich repeat class of plant disease resistance genes and lies embedded within the <italic>Pto</italic> kinase gene cluster</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1996</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80083-5</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Salmeron JM, Oldroyd GED, Rommens CMT, Scofield SR, Kim H-S, Lavelle DT, Dahlbeck D, Staskawicz BJ (1996) Tomato Prf is a member of the leucine-rich repeat class of plant disease resistance genes and lies embedded within the Pto kinase gene cluster. Cell 86:123&#x02013;133 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8689679</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandbrink</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooijen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Purimahua</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrielink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Verkerk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Localization of genes for bacterial canker resistance in <italic>Lycopersicon peruvianum</italic> using RFLPs</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1995</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>444</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00221988</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sandbrink JM, van Ooijen JW, Purimahua CC, Vrielink M, Verkerk R, Zabel P, Lindhout P (1995) Localization of genes for bacterial canker resistance in Lycopersicon peruvianum using RFLPs. Theor Appl Genet 90:444&#x02013;450 </citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RFLP analysis of the size of chromosomal segments retained around the <italic>Tm-2</italic> locus of tomato during backcross breeding</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1989</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00305828</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Young ND, Tanksley SD (1989) RFLP analysis of the size of chromosomal segments retained around the Tm-2 locus of tomato during backcross breeding. Theor Appl Genet 77:353&#x02013;359 </citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Stall</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallejos</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic localization of tomato genes that control a hypersensitive reaction to <italic>Xanthomonas campestris</italic> pv. <italic>vesicatoria</italic> (Doidge) dye</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1995</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>682</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Yu ZH, Wang JF, Stall RE, Vallejos CE (1995) Genomic localization of tomato genes that control a hypersensitive reaction to Xanthomonas campestris pv. vesicatoria (Doidge) dye. Genetics 141:675&#x02013;682 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8647402</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>