<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">DNA Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">DNA Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">dnares</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">dnares</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>DNA Research: An International Journal for Rapid Publication of Reports on Genes and Genomes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1340-2838</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1756-1663</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3859326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dst033</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dst033</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Full Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genome-Wide Association Studies Using Single Nucleotide Polymorphism Markers Developed by Re-Sequencing of the Genomes of Cultivated Tomato</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>Kenta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fukuoka</surname><given-names>Hiroyuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matsunaga</surname><given-names>Hiroshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Yuhko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Issei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>Hideki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Isobe</surname><given-names>Sachiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>Satoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><institution>Kazusa DNA Research Institute</institution>, <addr-line>2-6-7 Kazusa-Kamatari, Kisarazu, Chiba 292-0818</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><institution>NARO Institute of Vegetable and Tea Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>360 Kusawa, Ano, Tsu, Mie 514-2392</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label><institution>Life Science Research Center</institution>, <institution>Mie University</institution>, <addr-line>1577 Kurimamachiya, Tsu, Mie 514-8507</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel. +81 438-52-3935. Fax. +81 438-52-3934. E-mail: <email>shirasaw@kazusa.or.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>603</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Kazusa DNA Research Institute.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="dst033.pdf"/><abstract><p>With the aim of understanding relationship between genetic and phenotypic variations in cultivated tomato, single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) markers covering the whole genome of cultivated tomato were developed and genome-wide association studies (GWAS) were performed. The whole genomes of six tomato lines were sequenced with the ABI-5500xl SOLiD sequencer. Sequence reads covering &#x0223c;13.7&#x000d7; of the genome for each line were obtained, and mapped onto tomato reference genomes (SL2.40) to detect &#x0223c;1.5 million SNP candidates. Of the identified SNPs, 1.5% were considered to confer gene functions. In the subsequent Illumina GoldenGate assay for 1536 SNPs, 1293 SNPs were successfully genotyped, and 1248 showed polymorphisms among 663 tomato accessions. The whole-genome linkage disequilibrium (LD) analysis detected highly biased LD decays between euchromatic (58 kb) and heterochromatic regions (13.8 Mb). Subsequent GWAS identified SNPs that were significantly associated with agronomical traits, with SNP loci located near genes that were previously reported as candidates for these traits. This study demonstrates that attractive loci can be identified by performing GWAS with a large number of SNPs obtained from re-sequencing analysis.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>genome-wide association studies</kwd><kwd>linkage disequilibrium</kwd><kwd>whole-genome re-sequencing</kwd><kwd>single nucleotide polymorphism</kwd><kwd>tomato</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>), which is considered to be an important crop, originated from South and Central America, and spread to the rest of the world with accompanying morphological diversification.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C1">1</xref></sup> The Solanaceae family, to which tomato belongs, includes other important crop species, such as potato (<italic>S. tuberosum</italic>), eggplant (<italic>S. melongena</italic>), tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>), and pepper (<italic>Capsicum annuum</italic>). Comparative genomics within these various genera and species have greatly accelerated understanding of their genome evolution and the genetic mechanisms that confer phenotypic diversity to these species.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C2">2</xref></sup> Furthermore, several interspecific genetic linkage maps have been constructed between cultivated tomato and its wild relatives (<italic>S. chmielewskii</italic>, <italic>S. habrochaites</italic>, <italic>S. pennellii</italic>, and <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C3">3</xref></sup> These maps allow identification of the genes responsible for interspecific phenotypic variations, including disease resistance, fruit size and shape, and plant architecture.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C3">3</xref></sup> However, few genetic studies have reported intraspecific variations due to its narrow genetic diversity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C4">4</xref></sup></p><p>In the field of human and animal genomic and genetic studies, the availability of whole-genome sequence data has resulted in more rapid advances in re-sequencing analysis and genome-wide association studies (GWAS) than in classical genetics and quantitative trait locus (QTL) mapping.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C6">6</xref></sup> In plants such as rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>) and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, the initial plant species for which whole-genome sequences were available provided representative targets for such analysis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C10">10</xref></sup></p><p>Tomato has also been used as a model plant in classical and molecular genetics,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C11">11</xref></sup> due to autogamous diploidy (2<italic>n</italic> = 2<italic>x</italic> = 24) and a relatively compact genome (&#x0223c;950 Mb). Recently, the whole-genome sequence of tomato was published.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C12">12</xref></sup> Furthermore, Hirakawa <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C13">13</xref></sup> inferred the functions of 200 SNPs among the transcribed sequences of cultivated tomato lines by determining their positions in predicted genes on the tomato genome. These results are expected to accelerate the understanding of genetic mechanisms that confer phenotypic variations among tomato cultivars.</p><p>Massive parallel sequencing and genotyping methods have contributed to progress in genetics and genomics. Next-generation sequencers (NGSs), such as HiSeq2500 (Illumina), the GS FLX+ system (Roche), 5500xl SOLiD (Life Technologies), and Ion Proton (Life Technologies), have been employed for <italic>de novo</italic> assembly of genome sequences and re-sequencing analyses of genomes of several organisms.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C15">15</xref></sup> In such re-sequencing analysis, sequence reads from the whole genome are mapped onto the reference genome to identify nucleotide variations, including single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and insertions/deletions (indels).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C14">14</xref></sup> A large amount of nucleotide sequence data (up to Mb- or Gb-scale), redundantly covering the whole-genome sequence, can be obtained simultaneously by NGS technologies. This allows a huge number of the nucleotide variations to be identified cheaply and within a relatively short period of time. The identified SNPs can be used, for example, for polymorphic analysis of germplasm collections, which, in turn, allows genetic analyses such as QTL mapping, GWAS, and genomic selection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C16">16</xref></sup> Large-scale SNP genotyping is often performed with commercially available array-based platforms, such as Infinium (Illumina), GoldenGate (Illumina), and Axiom Genotyping Solution (Affymetrix).</p><p>Tomato accessions, so-called genetic resources, are stocked in several gene banks, including the Tomato Genetic Resource Center (TGRC), USA (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://tgrc.ucdavis.edu">http://tgrc.ucdavis.edu</uri>); the National Institute of Agrobiological Sciences (NIAS) Genebank, Japan (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gene.affrc.go.jp">http://www.gene.affrc.go.jp</uri>); and the NARO Institute of Vegetable and Tea Science (NIVTS), Japan (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.naro.affrc.go.jp/vegetea">http://www.naro.affrc.go.jp/vegetea</uri>). In the NIAS and NIVTS Genebanks, over 1500 tomato lines have been deposited from &#x0003e;50 countries. The morphological traits of each line are recorded when the plants are reproduced, whereas DNA-based genetic variation has not yet been evaluated. By combining massive parallel sequencing and high-throughput genotyping technologies, it is now possible to probe genome-wide genetic diversity in the large number of tomato accessions currently available. In addition, associations between genetic and phenotypic variations can be identified in the genetic resources by using morphological traits recorded in the NIVTS and NIAS Genebanks. These studies would provide useful knowledge for molecular genetic analysis and breeding. In this study, we re-sequenced six tomato lines to discover novel SNPs that could be used to estimate the ratio of the SNPs contributing to the phenotypic variation. The identified candidate SNPs were used for GWAS to predict the loci responsible for agronomically important traits, e.g. fruit size and shape and plant architecture.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><label>2.</label><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><label>2.1.</label><title>Plant materials and DNA isolation</title><p>Six inbred lines, &#x02018;Ailsa Craig&#x02019; (AIC), &#x02018;Furikoma&#x02019; (FRK), &#x02018;M82&#x02019; (M82), &#x02018;Tomato Chuukanbonhon Nou 11&#x02019; (PL11), &#x02018;Ponderosa&#x02019; (PON), and &#x02018;Regina&#x02019; (REG), which were selected as representative lines from the clusters in the phylogenetic tree obtained in our previous study,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C13">13</xref></sup> were used for whole-genome re-sequencing (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>). AIC and PON are greenhouse types, and FRK and M82 are processing types suited for field cultivation. PL11 is a breeding material developed at the NIVTS for a short-internode trait,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C17">17</xref></sup> and REG is a dwarf tomato with cherry-type fruits obtained from Sakata Seeds Co., Japan. All materials except for REG are available from the NIVTS, Japan.</p><p>The number of genotyped tomato accessions with SNPs was 663, of which 641, 9, 6, 5, 1, and 1 were derived from the NIVTS, Japan; five private companies (De Ruiter Seeds Co., The Netherlands; Sakata Seeds Co., Japan; Suntory Holdings Ltd., Japan; Takii Seeds Co., Japan; and Vilmorin Seeds Co., France); the TGRC at the University of California, USA; the National BioResource Project (NBRP) at the University of Tsukuba, Japan; Cornell University, USA; and the Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique (INRA), France, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>). Total genomic DNA was isolated from leaves of a single plant from each line using a DNeasy plant mini kit (Qiagen).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><label>2.2.</label><title>Whole-genome re-sequencing and identification of SNP candidates</title><p>Total genomic DNA from the six lines, such as AIC, FRK, M82, PL11, PON, and REG, was used for whole-genome shotgun sequencing according to the standard protocol (Life Technologies). The nucleotide sequences were determined using the 5500xl SOLiD sequencer (Life Technologies) in the paired-end mode (35 + 75 bases). The data obtained were mapped onto the reference genome sequence of &#x02018;Heinz 1706&#x02019; (H1706) ver. SL2.40<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C12">12</xref></sup> for SNP discovery using the LifeScope Genomic Analysis software (Life Technologies) with default parameters. When heterozygous SNPs were discovered in any one of six lines, they were manually excluded from the list of SNP candidates.</p><p>The SNP candidates were classified into seven groups according to ITAG2.3 predictions of the gene positions on the tomato genome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C12">12</xref></sup> as follows: intergenic SNPs, SNPs at the donor and acceptor splice sites bordering two bases of introns, intron SNPs, SNPs at untranslated regions (UTRs), synonymous SNPs, missense SNPs, and nonsense SNPs. The functional categories of tomato genes predicted in the ITAG2.3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C12">12</xref></sup> were assigned by BLASTP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C18">18</xref></sup> searches against the eukaryotic orthologous groups (KOG) database (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/COG">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/COG</uri>), with E-value cut-off of 1E&#x02212;4.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C19">19</xref></sup></p><p>SNP2CAPS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C20">20</xref></sup> and dCAPS Finder 2.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C21">21</xref></sup> were used for developing cleaved amplified polymorphic sequence (CAPS) and derived CAPS (dCAPS) markers, respectively. Oligonucleotides for the markers were designed using the PRIMER3 software.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C22">22</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><label>2.3.</label><title>SNP genotyping</title><p>A total of 1536 SNPs were selected for Illumina GoldenGate SNP genotyping of the 663 tomato accessions. The Illumina GoldenGate assay and subsequent SNP calling were performed as described by Shirasawa <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C23">23</xref></sup> Polymorphic analysis of CAPS and dCAPS markers including <italic>FAS</italic>, <italic>SP</italic>, and <italic>OVATE</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C24">24</xref></sup> was performed as described by Shirasawa <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C23">23</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><label>2.4.</label><title>Data analysis</title><sec id="s2d1"><label>2.4.1.</label><title>Clustering of the genetic resources</title><p>The genetic distances and Jaccard's similarity coefficients of all combinations of any two accessions were calculated from the genotypic data using the GGT2 software<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C25">25</xref></sup> as described by Shirasawa <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C26">26</xref></sup> A dendrogram of the genetic resources was established using the neighbor-joining method in the MEGA5 software.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C27">27</xref></sup></p><p>Principal component analysis (PCA) was also performed to determine the relationship between samples using the TASSEL software,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C28">28</xref></sup> in which SNPs with minor allele frequencies (MAFs) of &#x0003c;0.05 were removed and the number of components was limited to three.</p><p>The STRUCTURE software,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C29">29</xref></sup> in which SNPs with MAFs of &#x0003e;0.00 were included, was used to assess the genetic relationships of the investigated lines. The degree of admixture in each line was estimated under the conditions of a 100 000 burn-in period and 100 000 Markov Chain Monte Carlo replications. The ideal number of clusters (K) was estimated from the output of 20 independent calculations as described by Evanno <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C30">30</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s2d2"><label>2.4.2.</label><title>Linkage disequilibrium and haplotyping analysis</title><p>Linkage disequilibriums (LDs) of all SNP pairs on each chromosome were detected using the Haploview software<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C31">31</xref></sup> with the following parameters: MAF, &#x02265;0.05; Hardy&#x02013;Weinberg <italic>P</italic>-value cut-off, 0; and percentage of genotyped lines, &#x02265;0.75. Haplotypes and tag SNPs were predicted based on the estimated LD blocks according to the definition of Gabriel <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C32">32</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s2d3"><label>2.4.3.</label><title>Genome-wide association studies</title><p>Associations between genotypes and phenotypes were analysed using the mixed linear model (MLM) using the TASSEL program<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C28">28</xref></sup> with the following parameters: MAF of &#x02265;0.05. In the association analysis, we considered the kinship matrix based on the SNP data in the model of MLM, while population structure was excluded from the model since it could not be detected in the tomato accessions with the STRUCTURE analysis. The thresholds for the association were set to a &#x02013;log<italic>P</italic> of &#x0003e;5.06 and 4.36 at a significant level of 1 and 5%, respectively, after Bonferroni multiple test correction.</p><p>On NIAS Genebank databases (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.gene.affrc.go.jp">http://www.gene.affrc.go.jp</uri>), 71 phenotypic traits are registered for 9&#x02013;479 accessions (the numbers of investigated lines differ depending on the traits) as actual measured numeric data, qualitative data, and ranked data. They were investigated in the field and/or under greenhouse conditions over a number of years (1983&#x02013;2011) at multiple locations (seven sites in Japan and Taiwan). The phenotypic data for each accession redundantly recorded in multi-years and locations were averaged, so that the data could be regarded as continuous numerical data for the MLM. Of these, 23 traits that scored in &#x0003e;100 lines genotyped in this study were tested for the GWAS.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><label>3.</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><label>3.1.</label><title>Whole-genome shotgun re-sequencing of cultivated tomato</title><p>Whole-genome shotgun re-sequencing was performed for the six inbred tomato lines, such as AIC, FRK, M82, PL11, PON, and REG. DNA samples tagged with line-specific index sequences were subjected to sequencing analysis using the 5500xl SOLiD sequencer (Life Technologies) in the paired-end mode (75 + 35 bases) (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DST033TB1">1</xref>). A total of 708.3 million read pairs corresponding to 77.9 Gb DNA were obtained (13.7&#x000d7; mean depth for each line). In the subsequent <italic>in silico</italic> analysis with the LifeScope Genomic Analysis software (Life Technologies), 53.9% of the obtained sequences covered 93.4% of the reference genome sequence of H1706 ver. SL2.40<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C12">12</xref></sup> at 9.2&#x000d7; coverage on average for each line (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DST033TB1">1</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>). The other 46.1% reads were omitted from the mapping results due to the low quality of the reads and repetitive sequences in the tomato genome.<table-wrap id="DST033TB1" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;1.</label><caption><p>Statistics of the re-sequenced genomes in the six tomato lines</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Line name</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of read pairs (reads)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total sequence length (bp)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Re-sequencing depth<sup>a</sup> (times)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of genome coverage<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coverage depth (times)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 913 343</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 540 467 730</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FRK</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 995 911</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 119 550 210</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107 226 071</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 794 867 810</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PL11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121 752 304</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 392 753 440</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PON</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 404 895</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 384 538 450</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">188 026 505</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 682 915 550</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">118 053 172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 985 848 865</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup>Re-sequencing depth = total sequence length/tomato genome size (950 Mb).</p></fn><fn><p><sup>b</sup>Mapped percentage on the reference genome sequences (SL2.40, 760 Mb) at &#x02265;1 coverage.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><label>3.2.</label><title>Identification of SNP candidates and their positions on the tomato genome</title><p>Within the mapped sequence reads, a total of 2 011 984 SNP candidates were discovered between H1706 (SL2.40ch01 to SL2.40ch12) and the re-sequenced lines. Heterozygous and triallelic SNPs were often observed among the identified SNP candidates. They were considered false positives and were excluded from further analysis. As a result, a total of 1 473 798 SNPs, consisting of 836 676 transition and 637 122 transversion mutations, were identified as confident biallelic SNP candidates (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DST033F1">1</xref>, <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kazusa.or.jp/tomato">http://www.kazusa.or.jp/tomato</uri>), for which accuracy was validated using the GoldenGate assay described below. Among these, 170 173 SNPs were confirmed by their convertibility to CAPS markers (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kazusa.or.jp/tomato">http://www.kazusa.or.jp/tomato</uri>), which are considered a useful tool for conventional DNA polymorphic analysis.
<fig id="DST033F1" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1.</label><caption><p>Density maps for SNPs detected in six tomato lines with respect to the reference tomato genome, SL2.40. The colours in each block represent a continuum of SNP densities: low-to-high SNP densities are represented by green to red. Left-side elliptic bars indicate the tomato chromosomes. Horizontal lines in each chromosome bar show mapped positions of SNPs used for the GoldenGate assay (black for intergenic SNPs, red for SNPs at splice sites and intron SNPs, blue for SNPs at UTRs and synonymous SNPs, and green for missense SNPs and nonsense SNPs). Heterochromatic regions are indicated by vertical lines on the right of the chromosomes. Names of genes identified by map-based cloning in previous studies are shown on the right of the chromosomes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dst03301"/></fig></p><p>Different numbers of SNPs with respect to H1706 were observed in each line, e.g. 85 534 in PON, 85 670 in AIC, 120 329 in FRK, 245 730 in PL11, 710 904 in M82, and 1 102 982 in REG (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S3</ext-link>). SNP density with respect to H1706 was calculated to be, on average, one SNP per 516 bp (0.19%), and ranged from 1 SNP/689 bp (0.15%) in REG to 1 SNP/8884 bp (0.01%) in AIC, assuming a 760 Mb genome size for SL2.40 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S3</ext-link>). The SNPs were unevenly distributed across the genomes, i.e. a remarkably large number of SNPs were observed on Chromosome 11 (Chr11) in PL11; Chr04, Chr05, and Chr11 in M82; and Chr04, Chr05, and Chr12 in REG. At the chromosomal segment level, the numbers of SNPs ranged from 1 (88&#x02013;89 Mb position of Chr01 in M82) to 10 847 (34&#x02013;35 Mb position of Chr05 in REG) using a 1-Mb window scale (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DST033F1">1</xref>).</p><p>The identified SNP candidates were classified into seven groups according to their positions in predicted genes on the tomato genome sequence (see Section 2 for details). Of the 1 473 798 SNP candidates, 998, 279, 110, and 1 were redundantly mapped onto two, three, four, and five gene models, respectively, while the other 1 472 410 SNPs were positioned on a single gene model. As a result, a total of 1 475 688 SNP sites in gene models were targeted for classification. Among them, 1 316 332 (89.2%) were in intergenic spaces, corresponding to DNA sequences located between genes, including UTRs. The other 159 356 SNPs (10.8%) were in genic regions, of which 110 315 (7.5%) and 49 041 (3.3%) were in introns and exons, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DST033TB2">2</xref>). The number of SNPs potentially affecting gene function was 22 805 (1.5%), including 156 SNPs at splice sites in introns, 558 resulting in nonsense codons, and 22 091 of missense codons.
<table-wrap id="DST033TB2" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;2.</label><caption><p>The number of SNPs categorized into seven classes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Line</th><th align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Total</th><th align="left" rowspan="5" colspan="1">Intergenic</th><th align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Intragenic<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Intron<hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Exon<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Splice site</th><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Intron</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">UTR</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">CDS<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Synonymous</th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Non-synonymous<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missense</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonsense</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 721</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 707</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9477</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">628</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1769</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FRK</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 379</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">104 542</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">645</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1799</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3175</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">710 986</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">672 467</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 951</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1529</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6708</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">236</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PL11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">245 805</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">213 427</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 083</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1438</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3646</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PON</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 595</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70 205</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9847</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">661</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1751</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">REG</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 104 787</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">984 271</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 074</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 157</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 647</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">413</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 lines</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 475 688</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 316 332</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 159</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8982</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 410</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 091</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">558</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>The functions of genes having or not having the SNPs were investigated. First, a total of the 34 348 tomato genes predicted in the ITAG2.3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C12">12</xref></sup> were classified into the three groups: 508 genes having nonsense SNPs (Group 1); 9436 genes having nonsynoymous SNPs including nonsense, missense SNPs, and SNPs at splice junctions (Group 2); and 24 404 genes not classified in the Group 2 (Group 3). BLASTP was then used to compare the protein sequences with those in the KOG database.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C19">19</xref></sup> The 15 974 predicted genes were classified into KOG categories. The distributions of the categories were similar between the Groups 2 and 3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link>). In the Group 3, on the other hand, the proportions of the Categories C (energy production and conversion) and T (signal transduction mechanisms) were relatively prominent, while those of the Categories M (cell wall/membrane/envelope biogenesis), O (post-translational modification, protein turnover, and chaperones), U (intracellular trafficking, secretion, and vesicular transport), Y (nuclear structure), and Z (cytoskeleton) were conversely low (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><label>3.3.</label><title>SNP genotyping of tomato accessions by the Illumina GoldenGate assay</title><p>To select SNPs showing high polymorphism in the accessions, the 1 473 798 SNPs were filtered by the following criteria: (i) a LifeScope score of 0.000000; (ii) a 3:4 SNP segregation ratio in seven plant lines (H1706 and the six re-sequenced lines), or PL11-specific SNPs, or SNPs specific to two lines including PL11 [the later two criteria were set because the PL11 line is considered to be closely related to many modern F<sub>1</sub> hybrid cultivars (Fukuoka, personal communication)]; (iii) SNPs showing different segregation patterns among the seven lines within 3-cM windows covering whole genomes of a total length of 1500 cM;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C33">33</xref></sup> and (iv) an Illumina SNP score of &#x0003e;0.6, as determined on the Illumina website (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://icom.illumina.com">https://icom.illumina.com</uri>). Using these criteria, 1235 SNPs were selected (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DST033F1">1</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>). An additional 301 SNPs with MAFs of &#x0003e;0.3 and an Illumina SNP score of 1.0 were selected based on data reported in our previous studies.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C23">23</xref></sup></p><p>A total of 663 tomato accessions (listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>) were genotyped with the 1536 SNPs using the GoldenGate assay. As a result, 1293 SNPs were successfully genotyped in the 663 accessions, satisfying the criteria of the GenomeStudio Data Analysis software (Illumina). Of the 1293 SNPs, 1248 (96.5%) and 1147 (88.7%) showed segregations within the 663 accessions within the threshold of MAFs of &#x0003e;0 and &#x02265;0.05, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>). The MAF values of the 1248 SNPs were evenly distributed from 0.001 to 0.5, and no significant differences in the distribution of the MAF values of the seven SNP categories were observed (data not shown). The ratios of heterozygous alleles and null alleles were high in the seven F<sub>1</sub> hybrids and three wild species, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link>). The higher ratio in the three wild species could reflect polymorphisms at the probe annealing sites.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C23">23</xref></sup> In contrast, few heterozygous or null alleles were observed in the 23 inbred lines.</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><label>3.4.</label><title>Clustering analyses of the tomato accessions</title><p>The genetic distances between all combinations of any pairs in the 663 tomato accessions were calculated based on the genotypes of the 1248 SNPs. The genetic distances among the 663 accessions ranged from 0.00 to 0.72, with an average of 0.39. No obvious clusters were observed in the dendrogram of the genetic distances (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S3A</ext-link>). To evaluate this result, the genetic relationships between the accessions were determined by PCA, which showed that there were no clusters in the 663 lines (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S3B</ext-link>), because the individual proportions for PC1, 2, and 3 were 0.09, 0.06, and 0.05, respectively. Genetic relationship analysis using the STRUCTURE software indicated that there was no population structure in the accessions (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S3C</ext-link>). This is in contrast to the six clusters identified by the delta-K method reported by Evanno <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C30">30</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><label>3.5.</label><title>Linkage disequilibrium and haplotype identifications</title><p>Because no clear genetic structure was observed in the 663 accessions, LD across the tomato genome in these lines was investigated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DST033F2">2</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Figs S4 and S5</ext-link>). A total of 123 LD blocks, i.e. chromosome sections showing significant LD (based on the definition of Gabriel <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C32">32</xref></sup>) between each pair of located SNPs, were observed across chromosomes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>). The 123 LD blocks comprised a total of 458 SNPs. The average length of the LD blocks was 3.2 Mb, ranging from 256 bp in Chr10 between solcap_snp_sl_8260 and SL2.40ch10_59989140W to 58.3 Mb in Chr01 between SL2.40ch01_7886746R and SL2.40ch01_66149134Y (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>). The lengths of LD blocks containing heterochromatic regions (average, 13.8 Mb) were longer than that in euchromatic regions (average, 58 kb) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>).
<fig id="DST033F2" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2.</label><caption><p>LD measures; <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> values against physical distance (Mb) between all pairs of SNPs located on the same chromosome.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dst03302"/></fig></p><p>A total of 437 haplotypes were identified in the 123 LD blocks. An LD block had an average of 3.6 haplotypes consisting of an average of 3.7 SNPs (data now shown). Subsequently, 308 tag SNPs, the minimum SNP subset required for distinguishing haplotypes, were selected from the 458 SNPs located in the 123 LD blocks (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s3f"><label>3.6.</label><title>GWAS for agronomical traits in genetic resources</title><p>GWAS identified a total of nine SNP loci that were significantly associated with eight morphological traits recorded in the NIVTS and NIAS Genebanks (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DST033F3">3</xref>, Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DST033TB3">3</xref>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S6</ext-link>). The eight traits were phenotyped by actual measured numeric data, qualitative data, and ranked data, and comprised inflorescence branching (nine ranks), plant habit determinate (indeterminante or determinate), plant height (cm), number of leaves between inflorescences (number of leaves), fruit size (10 ranks), locule number (five ranks), green shoulder on immature fruit (10 ranks), and the colour of the fruit epidermis (colorless or yellow), of which the numbers of scored lines were 476, 478, 457, 111, 479, 474, 452, and 137, respectively (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Fig. S7</ext-link>).
<table-wrap id="DST033TB3" position="float"><label>Table&#x000a0;3.</label><caption><p>Effects of associated SNPs on the traits</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="char" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trait</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Associating SNP</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Position</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-Log <italic>P</italic><sup>a</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additive effect<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dominant effect<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Candidate gene</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Inflorescence branching</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch02_41751976Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 751 976</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S</italic> and <italic>AN</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">solcap_snp_sl_39457</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 904 111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">No. of leaves between inflorescences</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch06_42601581W</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 601 581</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SP</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>SP</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SL2.40ch06</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>42</bold>
<bold>362</bold>
<bold>163</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7.4</bold>**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<bold>0.7</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.4</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Plant habit determinate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch06_42601581W</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 601 581</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SP</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>SP</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SL2.40ch06</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>42</bold>
<bold>362</bold>
<bold>163</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>28.8</bold>**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.3</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<bold>0.4</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Plant height</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch06_42601581W</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42 601 581</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;7.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>SP</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>SP</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SL2.40ch06</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>42</bold>
<bold>362</bold>
<bold>163</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>11.6</bold>**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<bold>13.5</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>25.6</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">solcap_snp_sl_16654</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 135 101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Fruit size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL1_00sc6004_2094360_solcap_snp_sl_44897</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 280 215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>FAS</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>FAS</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SL2.40ch11</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>52</bold>
<bold>252</bold>
<bold>771</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>8.4</bold>**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<bold>33.3</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>12.2</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Locule number</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch02_41172086R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 172 086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.9*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>LC</italic> and <italic>OVATE</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL1_00sc6004_2094360_solcap_snp_sl_44897</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 280 215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.6**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>FAS</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>FAS</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SL2.40ch11</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>52</bold>
<bold>252</bold>
<bold>771</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>10.1</bold>**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<bold>1.2</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Green shoulder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch01_89266983Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 266 983</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.3*</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch10_1539862R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 539 862</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>U</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>U</italic></bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SL2.40ch10</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2</bold>
<bold>292</bold>
<bold>260</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20.9</bold>**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<bold>1.5</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Colour of fruit epidermis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch01_71279371Y</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.40ch01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 279 371</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0**</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not detected</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Y</italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Genes associating with the traits in the replicated GWAS are shown by bold.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>a</sup>** and * indicate the significance level of 1 and 5%, respectively.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>b</sup>Effect of &#x02018;Heinz 1706&#x02019; allele.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="DST033F3" position="float"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3.</label><caption><p>SNPs associated with inflorescence branching identified by GWAS. Distribution of SNPs associated with inflorescence branching. SNPs that associated significantly (-log<italic>P</italic> of 4.36 at a significant level of 5%) are indicated by arrows.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="dst03303"/></fig></p><p>Among the eight traits, inflorescence branching was associated with two SNP loci, SL2.40ch02_41751976Y and solcap_snp_sl_39457 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DST033F3">3</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DST033TB3">3</xref>). The SNP SL2.40ch02_41751976Y not belonging to any LD block was located at a distance of 4.8 and 1.6 Mb from the previously identified <italic>S</italic> (Solyc02g077390) and <italic>AN</italic> (Solyc02g081670) genes involved in compound inflorescence,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C34">34</xref></sup> respectively. The other seven morphological traits were significantly associated with seven SNP loci (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DST033TB3">3</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S6</ext-link>). Of the seven SNPs not belonging to any LD block, five were located near previously identified genes responsible for the targeted traits. These were SL2.40ch06_42601581W located at 240 kb from <italic>SP</italic> (Solyc06g074350),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C35">35</xref></sup> which is associated with plant habit determinate, plant height, and the number of leaves between inflorescences; SL1_00sc6004_2094360_solcap_snp_sl_44897, located at 31 kb from <italic>FAS</italic> (Solyc11g071810),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C36">36</xref></sup> which is associated with fruit size; SL1_00sc6004_2094360_solcap_snp_sl_44897, located at 31 kb from <italic>FAS</italic> (Solyc11g071810);<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C36">36</xref></sup> SL2.40ch02_41172086R, located at 594 kb from <italic>LC</italic> (Solyc02g083940 and/or Solyc02g083950),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C37">37</xref></sup> and 1.8 Mb from <italic>OVATE</italic> (Solyc02g085500),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C38">38</xref></sup> which are associated with locule number; SL2.40ch10_1539862R, located at 753 kb from U (Solyc10g008160),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C39">39</xref></sup> which is associated with green shoulder on immature fruit; and SL2.40ch01_71279371Y, located at 24 kb from <italic>Y</italic> (Solyc01g079620),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C40">40</xref></sup> which is associated with colour of the fruit epidermis. To investigate association between the genes conferring the traits, polymorphic analysis of <italic>SP</italic>, <italic>FAS</italic>, <italic>LC</italic>, <italic>OVATE</italic>, and <italic>U</italic> was performed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S5</ext-link>). The replicated GWAS including the five loci showed that <italic>SP</italic>, <italic>U</italic>, and <italic>FAS</italic> were strongly associated with these traits (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DST033TB3">3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><label>4.</label><title>Discussion</title><p>The re-sequencing analysis presented here identified a large number of SNP candidates in the cultivated tomato, <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, in which DNA polymorphisms have been difficult to detect.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C23">23</xref></sup> This has been attributed to its narrow genetic diversity, which was caused by the genetic bottlenecks that occurred during its domestication, cultivation, and breeding.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C41">41</xref></sup> The intraspecies SNP density of 0.19% was approximately three times lower than that of 0.6% between <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C12">12</xref></sup> The distribution of the SNPs on the reference sequence of H1706 was not evenly spaced over the genome as reported by Asamizu <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C42">42</xref></sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DST033F1">1</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>). In the H1706 genome, large introgressions are observed in Chr04, 09, 11, and 12, which has implications for the introduction of disease resistance loci into H1706 from <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C12">12</xref></sup> The biased SNP density observed in this study also suggests the presence of introgressions of genome segments from wild relatives in tomato breeding processes for disease resistance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C12">12</xref></sup></p><p>SNPs are abundant sequence alterations that can affect gene function. Among the seven inbred tomato lines (including H1706), 558 nonsense, and 22 091 missense, and 17 410 synonymous SNPs were found in 508 (1.5%), 9285 (26.7%), and 7825 (22.5%) of 34 727 predicted genes, respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DST033TB2">2</xref>). Between <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>, 3.5, 36.3, and 37.0% of genes contain nonsense, missense, and synonymous mutations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C12">12</xref></sup> The ratio of interspecies nonsense mutations to intraspecies nonsense mutations is 2.3, while the ratios of missense mutations and synonymous variations were 1.4 and 1.6, respectively. This result suggests that the alleles of wild relatives possessing SNPs that critically disrupt gene function, i.e. nonsense SNP, have been negatively selected from the gene pool of wild relatives for the purpose of breeding.</p><p>The tomato accessions used in this study included broad genetic diversities (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Figs S2 and S3</ext-link>). Genome-wide LD analysis based on these accessions revealed that the extension of the LD was dependent on the nature of the chromatin (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S4</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>). Similar observations have been reported for interspecific F<sub>2</sub> mapping populations in tomato, which indicated that chromosome recombination in heterochromatin is strongly suppressed compared with that in euchromatin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C43">43</xref></sup> LD analysis of whole genomes have been previously performed not only for tomato, but also for rice, soybean, and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C44">44</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C46">46</xref></sup> However, LDs specific to chromatin have not been investigated. It is expected that chromosome recombination over the genome is not appreciably different between the accessions and biparental mapping populations.</p><p>GWAS revealed SNPs that were associated with agronomically important traits (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="DST033F3">3</xref>, Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DST033TB3">3</xref>, and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S6</ext-link>), and three genes (<italic>FAS</italic>, <italic>SP</italic>, and <italic>U</italic>) were found to confer trait variations (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DST033TB3">3</xref>). Although such genes have been previously identified by a map-based cloning strategy, with interspecific populations conferring phenotypic variations between cultivated tomato and its wild relatives, the present results indicated that these genes are responsible for phenotypic variations within cultivated tomato. The identified SNPs could be potent selection markers for marker-assisted selection in breeding. However, no significant SNP association was detected for most of the traits registered in the NIVTS and NIAS Genebanks. Two possibilities can be advanced to explain the lack of a significant association. First, the density of the SNPs was insufficient for GWAS. In this study, while 1248 SNPs were employed in GWAS, LD extension in the gene-rich euchromatin region (58 kb) was too short to be covered by the SNP density employed (1 SNP/213 kb in euchromatin; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>). This analysis suggests that &#x0003e;3228 and &#x0003e;41 SNPs in eu- and heterochromatin regions, respectively, would be required to obtain high-resolution results from GWAS. Additionally, most of the traits were scored on 1&#x02013;5 or 1&#x02013;10 scales, rather than by performing actual measurements. Since the scale standards may vary between individual investigators, the accuracy is unlikely to be sufficient for GWAS. One of the reasons for the success in identifying the SNP associations with the eight morphological traits might be that the SNPs possessed large effects on phenotypic variations.</p><p>In this study, we demonstrated that genetic resource accessions can be used for GWAS, i.e. there is no need to establish a specific mapping population via labour-intensive methods for performing crosses and advancing generations. In addition, a core collection would be more effective for GWAS, as it would avoid the labour and cost associated with high-density whole-genome genotyping and replicated phenotyping. In barley, GWAS was used to detect SNP associations with agronomical traits in a worldwide collection.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C47">47</xref></sup> The establishment of core collections for tomato, whose contents could be changed depending on the purpose,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DST033C48">48</xref></sup> would enable the identification of valuable loci for molecular genetics and breeding.</p><p>In conclusion, the usefulness of GWAS was demonstrated by analysing a large SNP data set obtained from the re-sequencing data. This study represents an important step forward in genomics, genetics, and for the breeding of cultivated tomato.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><label>5.</label><title>Availability</title><p>Nucleotide sequence data reported are available in the DDBJ Sequence Read Archive (BioProject PRJDB1397) under the accession numbers DRA001017 (AIC), DRA001018 (FRK), DRA001019 (M82), DRA001020 (PL11), DRA001021 (PON), and DRA001022 (REG). Details of the SNPs and genotypes of the investigated genetic resources are available at the Kazusa Tomato Genomics DataBase (KaTomicsDB: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.kazusa.or.jp/tomato">http://www.kazusa.or.jp/tomato</uri>).</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Supplementary data</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/dnares/dst033/-/DC1">Supplementary data are available at www.dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org.</ext-link></p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the <funding-source>Kazusa DNA Research Institute Foundation</funding-source> and the <funding-source>Genomics for Agricultural Innovation Foundation</funding-source> (<award-id>SGE-1001</award-id>), <funding-source>Ministry of Agriculture, Forestry, and Fisheries of Japan</funding-source>.</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Data</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_20_6_593__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp.doc"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_fig1.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_fig2.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_fig3.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_fig4.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_fig5.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_fig6.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_fig7.jpg"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_table1.xls"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_table2.xls"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_table3.xls"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_table4.xls"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_dst033_dst033supp_table5.xls"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank S. Sasamoto, S. Nakayama, Y. Kishida, M. Kohara, and H. Tsuruoka (Kazusa DNA Research Institute) for their technical assistance, and Drs T. Ariizumi (NBRP), S.M. Tam (TGRC), S.D. Tanksley (Cornell University), and C. Rothan (INRA) for providing plant materials.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p>Edited by Dr Katsumi Isono</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="DST033C1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Labate</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandillo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tomato</article-title><source>Genome Mapping and Molecular Breeding in Plants</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>125</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromosomal evolution in the plant family Solanaceae</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>182</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20236516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA marker applications to molecular genetics and genomics in tomato</article-title><source>Breed. Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23641178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoffel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Deynze</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buell</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single nucleotide polymorphism discovery in cultivated tomato via sequencing by synthesis</article-title><source>Plant Genome</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>The 1000 Genomes Project Consortium</collab><article-title>An integrated map of genetic variation from 1092 human genomes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>491</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23128226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>The Bovine HapMap Consortium</collab><article-title>Genome-wide survey of SNP variation uncovers the genetic structure of cattle breeds</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>324</volume><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19390050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneeberger</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ossowski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole-genome sequencing of multiple <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> populations</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2011</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>956</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21874002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stegle</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Behr</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiple reference genomes and transcriptomes for <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2011</year><volume>477</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21874022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurata</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A map of rice genome variation reveals the origin of cultivated rice</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>490</volume><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23034647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Resequencing 50 accessions of cultivated and wild rice yields markers for identifying agronomically important genes</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22158310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernatzky</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toward a saturated linkage map in tomato based on isozymes and random cDNA sequences</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1986</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17246322</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>The Tomato Genome Consortium</collab><article-title>The tomato genome sequence provides insights into fleshy fruit evolution</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>485</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22660326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohyama</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide SNP genotyping to infer the effects on gene functions in tomato</article-title><source>DNA Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23482505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buell</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advances in plant genome sequencing</article-title><source>Plant J.</source><year>2012</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22449051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schatz</surname><given-names>M.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Witkowski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCombie</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current challenges in de novo plant genome sequencing and assembly</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>243</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22546054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varshney</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribaut</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckler</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuberosa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafalski</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Langridge</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can genomics boost productivity of orphan crops?</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1172</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23222781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsunaga</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tomato Chuukanbohon Nou 11&#x02019;, a tomato parental line with a short-internode trait</article-title><source>Bull. Natl. Inst. Veg. Tea Sci.</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>76</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatusov</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fedorova</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The COG database: an updated version includes eukaryotes</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>41</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12969510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kota</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosse</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Graner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SNP2CAPS: a SNP and INDEL analysis tool for CAPS marker development</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>e5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14704362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neff</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalishman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Web-based primer design for single nucleotide polymorphism analysis</article-title><source>Trends Genet.</source><year>2002</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12446140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rozen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skaletsky</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers</article-title><source>Methods Mol. Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10547847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isobe</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SNP discovery and linkage map construction in cultivated tomato</article-title><source>DNA Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21044984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>G.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;os</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distribution of <italic>SUN</italic>, <italic>OVATE</italic>, <italic>LC</italic>, and <italic>FAS</italic> in the tomato germplasm and the relationship to fruit shape diversity</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21441384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Berloo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GGT 2.0: versatile software for visualization and analysis of genetic data</article-title><source>J. Hered.</source><year>2008</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18222930</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of <italic>Capsicum</italic> EST-SSR markers for species identification and <italic>in silico</italic> mapping onto the tomato genome sequence</article-title><source>Mol. Breed.</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23316112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods</article-title><source>Mol. Biol. Evol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2731</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroon</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casstevens</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramdoss</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckler</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TASSEL: software for association mapping of complex traits in diverse samples</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>2633</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>J.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inference of population structure using multilocus genotype data</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2000</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>945</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10835412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evanno</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Regnaut</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: a simulation study</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2611</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15969739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fry</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maller</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haploview: analysis and visualization of LD and haplotype maps</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15297300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gabriel</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffner</surname><given-names>S.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The structure of haplotype blocks in the human genome</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>296</volume><fpage>2225</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12029063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asamizu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuoka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An interspecific linkage map of SSR and intronic polymorphism markers in tomato</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>2010</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20431859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lippman</surname><given-names>Z.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The making of a compound inflorescence in tomato and related nightshades</article-title><source>PLoS Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e288</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19018664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pnueli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmel-Goren</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hareven</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The <italic>SELF-PRUNING</italic> gene of tomato regulates vegetative to reproductive switching of sympodial meristems and is the ortholog of <italic>CEN</italic> and <italic>TFL1</italic></article-title><source>Development</source><year>1998</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>1979</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9570763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrero</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulatory change in YABBY-like transcription factor led to evolution of extreme fruit size during tomato domestication</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>800</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18469814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munos</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranc</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Botton</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increase in tomato locule number is controlled by two single-nucleotide polymorphisms located near WUSCHEL</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>2244</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21673133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Eck</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new class of regulatory genes underlying the cause of pear-shaped tomato fruit</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>13302</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>C.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Uniform ripening</italic> encodes a <italic>Golden 2-like</italic> transcription factor regulating tomato fruit chloroplast development</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2012</year><volume>336</volume><fpage>1711</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22745430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballester</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Molthoff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vos</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biochemical and molecular analysis of pink tomatoes: deregulated expression of the gene encoding transcription factor SlMYB12 leads to pink tomato fruit color</article-title><source>Plant Physiol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kesicki</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fobes</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and biosystematic studies on two new sibling species of <italic>Lycopersicon</italic> from interandean Peru</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>1976</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asamizu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping of Micro-Tom BAC-end sequences to the reference tomato genome reveals possible genome rearrangements and polymorphisms</article-title><source>Inter. J. Plant Genomics</source><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><fpage>437026</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Durstewitz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plieske</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of a large SNP genotyping array and generation of high-density genetic maps in tomato</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e40563</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22802968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Resequencing of 31 wild and cultivated soybean genomes identifies patterns of genetic diversity and selection</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2010</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1053</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21076406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranc</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Munos</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide association mapping in tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) is possible using genome admixture of <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> var. <italic>cerasiforme</italic></article-title><source>G3</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22908034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Deynze</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoffel</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-density SNP genotyping of tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> L.) reveals patterns of genetic variation due to breeding</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e45520</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23029069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pasam</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malosetti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide association studies for agronomical traits in a world wide spring barley collection</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22284310</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DST033C48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Odong</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Eeuwijk</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Hintum</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of core collections for effective utilisation of genetic resources review, discussion and interpretation</article-title><source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source><year>2013</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22983567</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>