<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3209458</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2229-11-140</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22014149</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-11-140</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Localization of QTLs for <italic>in vitro </italic>plant regeneration in tomato</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Trujillo-Moya</surname><given-names>Carlos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>cecaltrujillo@yahoo.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" id="A2"><name><surname>Gisbert</surname><given-names>Carmina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>cgisbert@btc.upv.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Vilanova</surname><given-names>Santiago</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>sanvina@btc.upv.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Nuez</surname><given-names>Fernando</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>fnuez@btc.upv.es</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Instituto de Conservaci&#x000f3;n y Mejora de la Agrodiversidad Valenciana (COMAV) Universitat Polit&#x000e8;cnica de Val&#x000e8;ncia, Camino de Vera, 14 46022 Valencia, Spain</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2011 Trujillo-Moya et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Trujillo-Moya et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/11/140"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Low regeneration ability limits biotechnological breeding approaches. The influence of genotype in the regeneration response is high in both tomato and other important crops. Despite the various studies that have been carried out on regeneration genetics, little is known about the key genes involved in this process. The aim of this study was to localize the genetic factors affecting regeneration in tomato.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We developed two mapping populations (F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1</sub>) derived from a previously selected tomato cultivar (cv. Anl27) with low regeneration ability and a high regeneration accession of the wild species <italic>Solanum pennellii </italic>(PE-47). The phenotypic assay indicated dominance for bud induction and additive effects for both the percentage of explants with shoots and the number of regenerated shoots per explant. Two linkage maps were developed and six QTLs were identified on five chromosomes (1, 3, 4, 7 and 8) in the BC<sub>1 </sub>population by means of the Interval Mapping and restricted Multiple QTL Mapping methods. These QTLs came from <italic>S. pennellii</italic>, with the exception of the minor QTL located on chromosome 8, which was provided by cv. Anl27. The main QTLs correspond to those detected on chromosomes 1 and 7. In the F<sub>2 </sub>population, a QTL on chromosome 7 was identified on a similar region as that detected in the BC<sub>1 </sub>population. Marker segregation distortion was observed in this population in those areas where the QTLs of BC<sub>1 </sub>were detected. Furthermore, we located two tomato candidate genes using a marker linked to the high regeneration gene: <italic>Rg-2 </italic>(a putative allele of <italic>Rg-1</italic>) and <italic>LESK1</italic>, which encodes a serine/threonine kinase and was proposed as a marker for regeneration competence. As a result, we located a putative allele of <italic>Rg-2 </italic>in the QTL detected on chromosome 3 that we named <italic>Rg-3</italic>. <italic>LESK1</italic>, which is also situated on chromosome 3, is outside <italic>Rg-3</italic>. In a preliminary exploration of the detected QTL peaks, we found several genes that may be related to regeneration.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this study we have identified new QTLs related to the complex process of regeneration from tissue culture. We have also located two candidate genes, discovering a putative allele of the high regeneration gene <italic>Rg-1 </italic>in the QTL on chromosome 3. The identified QTLs could represent a significant step toward the understanding of this process and the identification of other related candidate genes. It will also most likely facilitate the development of molecular markers for use in gene isolation.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic>In vitro </italic>regeneration of cultivated tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum </italic>L.) has been a constant subject of research because of the commercial value of the crop. Consequently, numerous studies on plant regeneration from a wide range of tissues and organs of wild and cultivated tomato germplasm have been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. These studies demonstrate that organogenesis, the common tomato regeneration pathway, is strongly influenced by genotype as well as by several physical and chemical factors. These reports also document the existence of recalcitrance (partial or total inability to respond to <italic>in vitro </italic>culture), which greatly limits biotechnological breeding. High regeneration is crucial to the success of techniques such as haploid regeneration, genetic transformation, propagation, somatic hybridization, mutation selection and germplasm storage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. For example, the low efficiency of tomato transformation has been associated with the low regeneration potential of the cultivars used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. In addition, in some cultivars, buds may be induced but do not develop into shoots [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. In order to increase regeneration ability in low regenerating tomato cultivars, several introgression programs have been documented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>The process of <italic>in vitro </italic>shoot organogenesis usually involves a hormonal response of somatic cells, the dedifferentiation of differentiated cells in order to acquire organogenic competence, cell division of the responding cell(s) and initiation and development of new shoots from the newly dividing cell(s), either directly or indirectly through a callus stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Thus, many genes may be involved at different steps of this complex process. For instance, the <italic>cdc2 </italic>gene expression, which encodes p34, a key cell cycle regulator, has been proposed as an indicator of the state of competence to divide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Genes that encode or regulate cytokinins and auxin may clearly influence regeneration. Both types of growth regulators act synergistically to promote cell division and antagonistically to promote shoot and root initiation from callus cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, a Histidine Kinase (AHK) gene that encodes a cytokinin receptor (CRE1/AHK4) has been identified [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] and linked, like other AHKs, to cell division and regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. With regard to the initiation of shoot formation, the most characterized gene reported is <italic>ESR1</italic>, which confers, when overexpressed, cytokinin-independent shoot formation in <italic>Arabidopsis </italic>root explants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. <italic>ESR1 </italic>encodes a transcription factor belonging to the ethylene-responsive factor (ERF) family and is classified in subgroup VIII-b. The <italic>ESR2 </italic>gene that encodes a protein that is very similar to <italic>ESR1 </italic>appears to have redundant functions that regulate shoot regeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. The expression patterns of other Arabidopsis ERF VIII-b subgroup genes may also be involved in early events of shoot regeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p><p>Genetic analysis of regeneration in tomato suggests that dominant alleles determine high regeneration capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. However, there is no consensus about the number of genes involved. For instance, Koorneef et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] obtained regeneration segregation ratios in accordance with either a monogenic, digenic or trigenic model depending on the tester tomato line, despite the fact that none of the lines themselves were able to regenerate shoots from root explants. In this study, a dominant allele of <italic>S. peruvianum </italic>L. (<italic>Rg-1</italic>), which determines efficient shoot regeneration in tomato root explants, was mapped near the middle of chromosome 3. In addition, a putative allele of <italic>Rg-1 </italic>from <italic>S</italic>. <italic>chilense </italic>(Dunal) Reiche (<italic>Rg-2</italic>) was reported by Takashina et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] and Satoh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Both alleles may act in combination with other alleles of either tomato or the wild relatives <italic>S. peruvianum </italic>or <italic>S. chilense </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. On the other hand, Torelli et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] identified a cDNA by mRNA-differential display that corresponded to the <italic>LESK1 </italic>gene and whose expression is specifically and transiently enhanced by the exposure to the hormonal treatment leading to caulogenesis (shoot induction). This gene encodes a putative serine-threonine kinase and has been reported as an <italic>in vitro </italic>caulogenesis marker in tomato [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>].</p><p>Despite ongoing research into the genetic control of <italic>in vitro </italic>culture traits in tomato and other crops, there is still not enough information regarding which key genes are responsible for low or high regeneration ability, nor even the number of genes involved. The study and characterization of the reported genes and others that might be identified could greatly improve our understanding of the molecular mechanism underlying the different phases of tomato <italic>in vitro </italic>organogenesis. In the present study, we developed two mapping populations (F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1</sub>) from <italic>S. lycopersicum </italic>(as the recurrent parent) and <italic>S. pennellii </italic>Correll (as the regenerating parent) and conducted a QTL-based analysis. We hereby report the identification of six QTLs on five chromosomes. These QTLs present high significant LOD scores and together represent a high percentage of phenotypic variance. We also report markers associated with QTL peaks. In addition, we located two candidate genes, <italic>Rg-2 </italic>and <italic>LESK1</italic>, and performed a preliminary search for genes situated at QTL peaks. Our findings will complement the current knowledge of the genetics of regeneration and facilitate the development of molecular markers for use in tomato breeding and gene isolation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Development of populations and evaluation of the regeneration ability</title><p>Two mapping populations, F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1</sub>, were obtained from a low regenerating cultivar of tomato (cv. Anl27) and the organogenic accession of <italic>S. pennellii </italic>(PE-47). The BC<sub>1 </sub>population was obtained using the tomato cultivar as the recurrent parent. In the first assay, the regeneration ability of the parents and the F<sub>1 </sub>plant used for obtaining the mapping populations was checked by culturing leaf explants on shoot induction medium. Regeneration occurred with little callus development and can be considered as direct. As expected, <italic>S. pennellii </italic>and F<sub>1 </sub>explants manifested a higher regeneration potential versus <italic>S. lycopersicum </italic>explants (<italic>P &#x0003c;</italic>0.001). The percentage of explants with buds (B) in <italic>S. pennellii </italic>was 100%, whereas only 10% was obtained in tomato cv. Anl27 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Data obtained in F<sub>1 </sub>for B do not significantly differ from those obtained for <italic>S. pennellii</italic>. The percentage of explants with shoots (R) and the number of regenerated plants per explant with shoots, considered to be the productivity rate (PR), was also higher in <italic>S. pennellii </italic>and F<sub>1 </sub>than in cv. Anl27. However, for these traits (R and PR), the F<sub>1 </sub>values differ significantly from those of <italic>S. pennellii </italic>(Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Phenotyping parental genotypes and mapping population</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th align="center" colspan="3">First Assay<break/>Phenotyping parental genotypes and F<sub>1</sub></th><th align="center" colspan="3">Second Assay<break/>Phenotyping mapping populations</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td/><td align="center"><bold>B<sup>a, c</sup></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>R<sup>a, c</sup></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>PR<sup>b, c</sup></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>B<sup>a, c</sup></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>R<sup>a, c</sup></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>PR<sup>b, c</sup></bold></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>S. pennellii</italic></td><td align="center">100 b</td><td align="center">96 c</td><td align="center">6.36 c</td><td align="center">100.00 c</td><td align="center">95.00 d</td><td align="center">6.74 c</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>S. lycopersicum</italic></td><td align="center">10 a</td><td align="center">6 a</td><td align="center">0.30 a</td><td align="center">7.50 a</td><td align="center">2.50 a</td><td align="center">0.12 a</td></tr><tr><td align="left">F1</td><td align="center">90 b</td><td align="center">78 b</td><td align="center">3.17 b</td><td align="center">87.50 c</td><td align="center">70.0 c</td><td align="center">3.08 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">76.91 bc</td><td align="center">63.92 c</td><td align="center">2.65 b</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">59.48 b</td><td align="center">36.65 b</td><td align="center">1.67 b</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Means of the traits: percentage of explants with buds (B), percentage of explants with shoots (R) and number of shoots per explant with shoots (PR) for the parent genotypes (<italic>S. pennellii </italic>and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>), F<sub>1</sub>, F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1</sub>.</p><p><sup>a </sup>B and R are the percentages of explants able to develop buds and shoots, respectively. <sup>b </sup>PR is the number of shoots per explant with shoots. <sup>c </sup>Mean values within a column separated by different letters are significantly different (<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.05) according to Duncan's multiple range test.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1 </sub>populations were evaluated for regeneration using explants from the parents and F<sub>1 </sub>plants as controls (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The phenotypes are shown in Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>. The distribution obtained for each individual trait as well as the means for controls in this assay are presented in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>. Mean values for B, R and PR in the F<sub>2 </sub>population are between F<sub>1 </sub>and tomato (P1), but skewed towards F<sub>1</sub>. For the PR trait, some F<sub>2 </sub>plants were in a range higher than the <italic>S. pennellii </italic>parent (P2). This can be considered transgressive segregation. BC<sub>1 </sub>yielded mean values for B, R and PR that were intermediate between F<sub>1 </sub>and cv. Anl27 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Population distributions for regeneration traits</bold>. a) The percentage of explants with buds (B), b) The percentage of explants with plants (R) and c) The percentage of plants per explant with shoots (PR). The F<sub>2 </sub>population (dark) is derived from selfing an F<sub>1</sub>, the result of a cross between the tomato cv. Anl27 (P1) and <italic>S. pennellii </italic>PE-47 (P2). The BC<sub>1 </sub>population (grey) is the result of crossing the tomato cv. Anl27 and the F<sub>1 </sub>plants. Maternal (P1), Paternal (P2), F<sub>1</sub>, F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1 </sub>mean values are indicated by arrows.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-11-140-1"/></fig><p>B and R show a high correlation (r = 0.88/0.79 p &#x0003c; 0, 001 for F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1 </sub>data, respectively), which suggests common or linked genes controlling these traits. The correlation between PR and both B and R was lower (r = 0.56/0.52 p &#x0003c; 0, 001; 0.66/0.66 p &#x0003c; 0, 001 for PR and B and R for F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1</sub>, respectively) indicating that different genes may influence the PR trait and/or variations between different biological samples are higher in PR.</p></sec><sec><title>Linkage maps</title><p>Genetic linkage maps were constructed from 106 F<sub>2 </sub>and 113 BC<sub>1 </sub>plants genotyped with SSR, COSI, COSII, CAPS and AFLP markers (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Of the 149 SSR and 97 other markers (86 COSII, 6 COSI, 5 CAPS) assayed, 78 SSR and 59 (51 COSII, 4 COSI, 4 CAPS) markers exhibited codominant polymorphisms. These markers were obtained from the Sol Genomics Network (SGN) webpage at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sgn.cornell.edu/">http://www.sgn.cornell.edu/</ext-link>with the exception of 60 SSRs that were designed following the procedure described in Materials and Methods (see Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>a) Tomato genetic linkage map of F<sub>2 </sub>population derived from <italic>S. lycopersicum </italic>(cv. Anl27) &#x000d7; <italic>S. pennellii </italic>(PE-47) and QTLs detected for regeneration traits by IM</bold>. b) Tomato genetic linkage map of BC<sub>1 </sub>population derived from <italic>S. lycopersicum </italic>(cv. Anl27) &#x000d7; F<sub>1 </sub>(cv. Anl27 &#x000d7; PE-47) and QTLs detected for regeneration traits by rMQM. The segregated data were classified into 12 linkage groups, which corresponded to the Tomato-EXPEN 2000 map; italics indicate markers with segregation significantly skewed (P &#x0003c; 0.05) in favour of parent alleles. The colors specify the direction of the segregation distortion (red: markers skewed toward the alleles of cultivated tomato; green: markers skewed toward the alleles of the wild parent). Green bars reflect QTLs from S. <italic>pennellii</italic>: <italic>SpRg-1, Rg-3, SpRg-4a, SpRg-4b </italic>and <italic>SpRg-7</italic>; the red bar reflects the <italic>SlRg-8 </italic>QTL from S. <italic>lycopersicum</italic>. Regeneration traits: B (Bud percentage), R (Regeneration percentage) and PR (Productivity rate). The black star labels the acid invertase gene (inv<italic><sup>penn</sup></italic>) mapped on chromosome 3 included in the <italic>Rg-3 </italic>QTL range.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-11-140-2"/></fig><p>For the F<sub>2 </sub>linkage map (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>), a total of 246 polymorphic loci were used, including 151 AFLP, 53 SSR, 35 COSII, 3 COSI and 4 CAPS markers. The markers were aligned in 12 linkage groups, with LOD scores &#x02265; 3.0. The average number of markers per linkage group was 20 and markers were well distributed over all the 12 linkage groups. The F<sub>2 </sub>map spans 963.85 cM with an average interval of 3.72 cM between adjacent markers. There were five intervals &#x0003e; 25 cM in chromosomes 2, 4, 5 and 11. A total of 268 polymorphic loci were used to assemble the genetic linkage map of BC<sub>1 </sub>(Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>), including 174 AFLP, 46 SSR, 43 COSII, 3 COSI and 2 CAPS markers. The markers were distributed over 12 linkage groups with LOD scores &#x02265; 3.0. The average number of markers per linkage group was 22. The total genetic distance covered by the markers was 1014.94 cM, with an average interval of 4.12 cM between adjacent markers. The markers were well distributed over all the 12 linkage groups with only two intervals &#x02265; 25 cM in chromosomes 5 and 10. Marker distribution in both maps indicates that they will be useful for tagging the traits studied.</p><p>The order and placement of SSR markers were in agreement with the <italic>S. lycopersicum </italic>x <italic>S. pennellii </italic>reference tomato-EXPEN 2000 map (SGN) with the exception of TAHINA-6-64 (<italic>in silico </italic>designed), which was expected to be positioned on chromosome 6 (position 64) but is positioned on chromosome 8 (position 8.85) in our F<sub>2 </sub>map.</p></sec><sec><title>Distorted segregation</title><p>42.45% of the mapped markers deviated significantly from the expected 1:2:1 segregation ratio for the F<sub>2 </sub>generation at P &#x0003c; 0.05 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>). Segregation distorted markers (SDMs) were mainly observed on chromosomes 1 (0.00-63.17 cM), 3 (33.24-38.85 cM), 4 (19.74-92.09 cM), 5 (12.60-72.26 cM), 6 (0.00-55.38 cM) and 10 (0.00-51.24 cM). SDMs were generally caused by a surplus of <italic>S. pennellii </italic>homozygotes, with the exception of that observed on chromosome 5.</p><p>In the BC<sub>1 </sub>population (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>), SDMs were fewer (30.3%) than in F<sub>2</sub>, and were observed mainly on chromosomes 6 (0.00-6.75 cM), 8 (0.00-15.40 cM), 11 (25.80-27.48 cM) and 12 (28.23-60.63 cM). The distortion on chromosome 8 was caused by a surplus of tomato homozygotes, whereas distortions on the other chromosomes were caused by an excess of hybrid genotypes.</p></sec><sec><title>QTL Identification</title><p>In order to identify QTLs, we first used Interval Mapping (IM) analysis that resulted in the identification of one QTL in the F<sub>2 </sub>population and six in the BC<sub>1 </sub>population (See Additional Files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). The QTL identified in F2, located on chromosome 7, overlapped for the three traits. In the BC<sub>1 </sub>analysis, this QTL also appeared for the R and PR traits. However, in this population, another five QTLs were identified on chromosomes 1, 3, 4 (at two different areas: 4a and 4b) and 8. All these QTLs were confirmed by restricted Multiple QTL Mapping (rMQM) analysis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). With the exception of the QTL on chromosome 8, all QTLs come from <italic>S. pennellii</italic>. These QTLs were named by their origin, <italic>Sp </italic>for <italic>S. pennellii </italic>or <italic>Sl </italic>for <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, followed by <italic>Rg </italic>(referring to regeneration) and the number of the chromosome on which they were located.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>QTLs for shoot regeneration traits (Bud percentage (B), Regeneration percentage (R) and Productivity Rate (PR)) found to be significant at the empirical genome wide mapping threshold by restricted Multiple QTL Mapping (rMQM) in BC<sub>1 </sub>and Interval Mapping (IM) in F<sub>2</sub></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center">Test</th><th align="center">QTL analysis</th><th align="center">Trait</th><th align="center">QTL</th><th align="center">Genome wide significant threshold level (P &#x0003c; 0.05)</th><th align="center">Chr</th><th align="center">Start<break/>(cM)</th><th align="center">Finish<break/>(cM)</th><th align="center">Coverage (cM)</th><th align="center">LOD Peak</th><th align="center">Position of LOD peak (cM)</th><th align="center">Peak marker <sup>a</sup></th><th align="center">%variance explained</th><th align="center">Estimated additive effect</th><th align="center">Estimated dominance effect</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">rMQM</td><td align="center">B</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-1</italic></td><td align="center">2.7</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3.87</td><td align="center">44.42</td><td align="center">40.55</td><td align="center">7.12</td><td align="center">22.47</td><td align="center">C2_At1g65520/C2_At2g45910</td><td align="center">23.9</td><td align="center">-31.56</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">rMQM</td><td align="center">R</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-1</italic></td><td align="center">2.7</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3.87</td><td align="center">43.42</td><td align="center">39.55</td><td align="center">5.52</td><td align="center">24.47</td><td align="center">C2_At1g65520/C2_At2g45910</td><td align="center">15.0</td><td align="center">-24.10</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">rMQM</td><td align="center">PR</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-1</italic></td><td align="center">2.8</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3.87</td><td align="center">34.42</td><td align="center">30.55</td><td align="center">4.19</td><td align="center">22.47</td><td align="center">C2_At1g65520/C2_At2g45910</td><td align="center">10.2</td><td align="center">-0.70</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="15"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">rMQM</td><td align="center">B</td><td align="center"><italic>Rg-3</italic></td><td align="center">2.7</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">42.41</td><td align="center">55.80</td><td align="center">13.39</td><td align="center">4.64</td><td align="center">50.47</td><td align="center">ME20-199</td><td align="center">12.2</td><td align="center">-21.60</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">rMQM</td><td align="center">PR</td><td align="center"><italic>Rg-3</italic></td><td align="center">2.8</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">32.77</td><td align="center">63.10</td><td align="center">30.33</td><td align="center">4.26</td><td align="center">50.47</td><td align="center">ME20-199</td><td align="center">10.6</td><td align="center">-0.68</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="15"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">rMQM</td><td align="center">R</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-4a</italic></td><td align="center">2.7</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">44.39</td><td align="center">61.24</td><td align="center">16.85</td><td align="center">4.94</td><td align="center">50.24</td><td align="center">TAHINA-4-71, 3</td><td align="center">13.3</td><td align="center">-22.29</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="15"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">rMQM</td><td align="center">PR</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-4b</italic></td><td align="center">2.8</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">81.33</td><td align="center">93.18</td><td align="center">11.85</td><td align="center">3.08</td><td align="center">86.33</td><td align="center">SSR214/SSR146</td><td align="center">7.4</td><td align="center">-0.63</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">IM</td><td align="center">B</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-7</italic></td><td align="center">3.7</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">2.20</td><td align="center">40.28</td><td align="center">38.08</td><td align="center">6.84</td><td align="center">19.51</td><td align="center">ME10-141/C2_At4g26680</td><td align="center">27.0</td><td align="center">-22.20</td><td align="center">12.32</td></tr><tr><td align="center">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">IM</td><td align="center">R</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-7</italic></td><td align="center">3.6</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">4.50</td><td align="center">40.28</td><td align="center">35.78</td><td align="center">6.18</td><td align="center">19.51</td><td align="center">ME10-141/C2_At4g26680</td><td align="center">24.8</td><td align="center">-23.29</td><td align="center">13.63</td></tr><tr><td align="center">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="center">IM</td><td align="center">PR</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-7</italic></td><td align="center">4.4</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">19.51</td><td align="center">36.28</td><td align="center">16.77</td><td align="center">5.72</td><td align="center">28.28</td><td align="center">C2_At1g17200</td><td align="center">23.1</td><td align="center">-1.53</td><td align="center">-0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="center">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">rMQM</td><td align="center">R</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-7</italic></td><td align="center">2.7</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">0.00</td><td align="center">25.08</td><td align="center">25.08</td><td align="center">5.47</td><td align="center">13.44</td><td align="center">TAHINA-7-43</td><td align="center">14.9</td><td align="center">-23.13</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">rMQM</td><td align="center">PR</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-7</italic></td><td align="center">2.8</td><td align="center">7</td><td align="center">3.54</td><td align="center">28.23</td><td align="center">24.69</td><td align="center">5.28</td><td align="center">13.44</td><td align="center">TAHINA-7-43</td><td align="center">13.5</td><td align="center">-0.77</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="15"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="center">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">rMQM</td><td align="center">B</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-8</italic></td><td align="center">2.7</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">41.18</td><td align="center">53.37</td><td align="center">12.19</td><td align="center">3.84</td><td align="center">46.37</td><td align="center">C2_At1g64150</td><td align="center">12.2</td><td align="center">21.25</td><td/></tr><tr><td align="center">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center">rMQM</td><td align="center">R</td><td align="center"><italic>SpRg-8</italic></td><td align="center">2.7</td><td align="center">8</td><td align="center">42.18</td><td align="center">58.90</td><td align="center">16.72</td><td align="center">4.25</td><td align="center">53.37</td><td align="center">C2_At1g64150/C2_At4g23840</td><td align="center">9.3</td><td align="center">19.35</td><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>In case of the absence of a peak marker, loci flanking the likely peak of a QTL are shown.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>QTLs for regeneration traits in the BC<sub>1 </sub>population</title><sec><title>Bud percentage (B)</title><p>IM analysis identified two QTLs on chromosomes 1 and 8 (<italic>SpRg-1 </italic>and <italic>SlRg-8</italic>; Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>). <italic>SpRg-1 </italic>has a maximum LOD score of 5.87 and is spanned by markers SSR316 and ME17-70. This QTL explained 22.9% of the phenotypic variation of the B trait. <italic>SpRg-8</italic>, with a maximum LOD score of 2.8, including just the C2_At1g64150 marker, explained 11.7% of the phenotypic variation in B. rMQM analysis, using C2_At2g45910 (chromosome 1) and C2_At1g64150 (chromosome 8) markers as cofactors, confirmed those QTLs detected by IM and detected a new one on chromosome 3 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>, Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>). QTL characteristics are shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. Collectively, these QTLs explained 34.6% and 48.3% of phenotypic variance in IM and rMQM, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Regeneration percentage (R)</title><p>IM analysis identified three QTLs located on chromosomes 1, 4 and 7 denominated <italic>SpRg-1, SpRg-4a </italic>and <italic>SpRg-7</italic>, respectively. The three QTLs had maximum LOD scores of 4.20, 3.92 and 3.86, and each explained around 16-17% of the phenotypic variation (see Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>). rMQM analysis, using C2_At2g45910 (chromosome 1), TAHINA-4-71.3 (chromosome 4) and TAHINA-7-43 (chromosome 7) markers as cofactors, confirmed all QTLs detected by IM and detected the <italic>SlRg-8 </italic>QTL (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>, Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In this case, the percentage of the phenotypic variation explained by each QTL was 15% for <italic>SpRg-1</italic>, 13.3% for <italic>SpRg-4a</italic>, 14.9% for <italic>SpRg-7 </italic>and 9.3% for <italic>SlRg-8</italic>. Collectively, these QTLs explained 48.7% and 52.5% of the phenotypic variance in IM and rMQM, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Productivity rate (PR)</title><p>IM detected the QTLs located previously for B and R on chromosomes 1, 3 and 7 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>, Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>), as well as another QTL on chromosome 4, denominated <italic>SpRg-4b</italic>. The maximum phenotypic variation for PR (17.4%) is explained by <italic>SpRg-7</italic>, and the lowest (11.9%) by a QTL on chromosome 3. rMQM analysis, using SSR92 (chromosome 1), ME20-199 (chromosome 3), SSR146 (chromosome 4) and TAHINA-7-43 (chromosome 7) markers as cofactors, confirmed the QTLs detected by IM (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Mapping tomato candidate genes</title><p>We selected the acid invertase gene linked to the <italic>Rg-2 </italic>regeneration gene of <italic>S. chilense </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] and the <italic>LESK1 </italic>gene, described as a marker in tomato for <italic>in vitro </italic>regeneration competence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>], as the tomato candidate genes.</p><p>The amplification products of the acid invertase gene marker (<italic>inv<sup>penn</sup></italic>) produce fragments of different sizes: 162 bp for <italic>S. lycopersicum </italic>cv. Anl27 and 173 bp for <italic>S. pennellii </italic>(see Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>). Thus, inv<italic><sup>penn </sup></italic>was used for mapping the BC<sub>1 </sub>population (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>, Additional Files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>). It was located in the QTL detected on chromosome 3, between the C2_At5g23880 and SSRB50753 markers, at positions 49.9 cM and 49.93 cM, respectively. For this reason, we named this QTL <italic>Rg-3 </italic>(a putative allele of <italic>Rg-2</italic>).</p><p>The <italic>LESK1 </italic>gene is located in the SGN Tomato-EXPEN 2000 map on chromosome 3 between markers C2_At4g18230 and cLPT-5-e7 (7 - 15 cM). As a result, in our BC<sub>1 </sub>map, <italic>LESK1 </italic>must be placed between C2_At4g18230 and TAHINA-3-44 (7 - 44 cM). Thus, this candidate gene is outside the located <italic>Rg-3 </italic>QTL.</p></sec><sec><title>Exploring QTLs</title><p>The official annotation for the tomato genome provided by the International Tomato Annotation Group at the SGN was used to carry out a preliminary search for related regeneration genes near the identified QTL peaks. We found a histidine kinase in <italic>SpRg-7</italic>, several serine/threonine kinases in all identified QTLs, ethylene response factors (ERFs) in all identified QTLs with the exception of <italic>SpRg-4b</italic>, cyclines in <italic>SpRg-1, Rg-3, SpRg-4a </italic>and <italic>SpRg-7 </italic>and MADS-box in <italic>SpRg-1, SpRg-4a </italic>and <italic>SpRg-7</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The wild tomato species <italic>S. peruvianum, S. pimpinellifolium </italic>L. <italic>and S. chilense </italic>were used as sources of regeneration genes in order to study the genetics of the <italic>in vitro </italic>regeneration in tomato [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. In this study, we used one accession of <italic>S. pennellii </italic>(PE-47) as the high regeneration parent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. This accession, along with a previously selected low regenerating tomato cultivar (cv. Anl27), was used to develop two mapping populations (F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1</sub>). The use of the introgression lines of <italic>S. pennellii </italic>in the M82 tomato background [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] had been previously ruled out for this analysis because of the high regeneration ability of both parent lines (data not shown). Data in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> seem to indicate complete dominance for B, partial dominance for R and additive effects for PR. This is in agreement with other reported studies on tomato where dominance, to different degrees, depending on the regeneration trait studied, was also reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. B and R traits show a high correlation in both populations, suggesting that common or linked genes control these traits. The correlation between PR and both B and R was lower. This could imply that other genes may be influencing the PR trait and/or variations between different biological samples are higher in PR (for instance, competition for development due to the presence of different shoots in a similar explant area). Thus, the low sample size may be also a possible explanation for the lower correlation.</p><p>Some descendants in the F<sub>2 </sub>population showed phenotypes for the PR trait that are more extreme that those shown by the regenerating parent line (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Transgressive segregation has already been described in other reports in relation to the genetic control of plant regeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], and suggests poligenic inheritance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. It also suggests the existence of alleles that promote, and others that inhibit, <italic>in vitro </italic>regeneration, with only some of the alleles with positive effects occurring in the same parent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. In fact, in this study, the <italic>SlRg-8 </italic>QTL that contributes to regeneration came from the low regenerating parent.</p><p>Plant regeneration from cultured tissues is assumed to fall under quantitative genetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>], although evidence in tomato [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] and other vegetables [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>] indicates that just a few genes could be responsible for regeneration. We identified 6 QTLs in the BC<sub>1 </sub>analysis, which is indicative of the participation of a large number of genes in this character. These QTLs are situated on chromosomes 1, 3, 4, 7 and 8 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>). The percentage of variance explained by each QTL ranges from 7.4 to 27%, which is in accordance with the most common range (6-26%) reported in the genetic mapping of QTLs for tissue culture response in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. We used three traits (B, R and PR) as a measurement of regeneration capability that could be useful for detecting chromosome regions that act at different times.</p><p>In the F<sub>2 </sub>population, only the QTL of chromosome 7 was identified for all analyzed traits (Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>); the SDMs observed in most chromosome areas where QTLs were detected in the BC<sub>1 </sub>population are most likely the cause (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The SDMs on chromosomes 1, 3, 6, 10 and 11 were also observed in similar areas in the Tomato-EXPEN 2000 map [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. SDMs affect the detection power of QTLs when QTLs and SDMs are closely linked [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>], as occurred in our case. Deviation from the expected segregation ratio is a common feature of inter-specific tomato crosses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. To wit: in a F<sub>2 </sub>population from <italic>S. lycopersicum </italic>x <italic>S. pennellii</italic>, De Vicente and Tanskley [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] reported a skewness rate of up to 80%.</p><p>In the BC1 population, three QTLs were detected for B: <italic>SpRg-1, SpRg-3 </italic>and <italic>SlRg-8</italic>. These QTLs may be associated with the first stages of regeneration, that is, hormonal induction response and bud formation. <italic>SpRg-1</italic>, which explained the highest percentage of variation for B (23.9%), was also identified for the R and PR traits. Given that bud formation is a necessary prerequisite for the production of shoots, it was expected that this major QTL for B would be found for R and PR, which in fact turned out to be the case (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). For R and PR, a common QTL on chromosome 7 (<italic>SpRg-7</italic>) was also identified. In addition, two QTLs were detected for R (<italic>SpRg-4a </italic>and <italic>SlRg-8</italic>) and PR (<italic>SpRg-4b </italic>and <italic>Rg-3</italic>). All these QTLs seem to be involved in the development of buds into shoots. As can also be observed in this study, common QTLs for the different regeneration traits, as well as a higher number of QTLs for traits related to plant development compared to those associated with bud induction, have been reported in different studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. For instance, in Arabidopsis, Schianterelli et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>] found a common area of chromosome 1 in all analyzed parameters, a peak in chromosome 4 and another in chromosome 5 when they analyzed the total number of regenerated shoots. In wheat, Ben Amer et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] identified three QTLs, two that affect green spot initiation and shoot regeneration and a third that only influences plant formation.</p><p>A partial common genetic system controlling the regeneration frequency of diverse types of explants has been reported by Molina and Nuez [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] in melon. This indicates that using different explants for loci detection may lead to the identification of some common QTLs, but also to the possible identification of other new QTLs. Root explants were used by Koornneef et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] and Satoh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] for phenotyping, at which point two alleles for regeneration ability were located on chromosome 3 of tomato. In the present study, leaves were used for phenotyping and a QTL (<italic>Rg-3</italic>) in a similar area of chromosome 3 was detected in addition to other QTLs that influence regeneration and were identified on chromosomes 1, 4, 7 and 8. Differences in root and leaf explants for QTL identification were also found in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>].</p><p>Koornneef et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] located a dominant allele from <italic>S. peruvianum </italic>(<italic>Rg-1</italic>) near the middle of chromosome 3 that determines efficient shoot regeneration in tomato root explants. Satoh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] mapped a putative allele (<italic>Rg-2</italic>) from <italic>S. chilense </italic>on this chromosome. The acid invertase gene, reported as a marker linked to <italic>Rg-2</italic>, was chosen for mapping <italic>Rg-2 </italic>in our population derived from <italic>S. pennellii</italic>. The polymorphisms detected in our parents allow us to map this gene in the QTL detected on chromosome 3 that we named <italic>Rg-3</italic>. We consider <italic>Rg-3 </italic>to be a putative allele of the <italic>Rg-2 </italic>gene. Allelism must be confirmed.</p><p>The other gene chosen as a candidate was <italic>LESK1</italic>, which encodes a serine/threonine kinase, and was reported as a marker of competence for <italic>in vitro </italic>regeneration in tomato [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. This gene was positioned on chromosome 3, but it is not located in the <italic>Rg-3 </italic>QTL.</p><p>The recent release of the entire genome sequence of tomato provides a powerful tool for interrogating QTL data. In this respect, we have taken a preliminary look at genes located at the peak areas of the detected QTLs, and which could be related to organogenesis. Histidine kinases were reported as cytokinin receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. In our QTL peaks, only one histidine kinase is located in the <italic>SpRg</italic>-7 QTL. The candidate tomato gene, <italic>LESK1</italic>, which has been described as a marker for <italic>in vitro </italic>competence, encodes a serine/threonine kinase. We looked for serine/threonine kinases and found this kind of protein in all identified QTLs. Other putative candidate genes could be <italic>ESR1 </italic>and its paralogue, <italic>ESR2</italic>, from Arabidopsis, which are the best-characterized genes related to regeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. These genes code for ethylene response factors (ERF). We found ERFs, which contain the AP2 domain, in all analysed QTLs with the exception of <italic>SpRg-4b</italic>. Cyclines related to cell division [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] were found in <italic>SpRg-1, Rg-3, SpRg-4a </italic>and <italic>SpRg-7</italic>. MADS-box genes, which have been correlated to adventitious regeneration induction and regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>], were found in the <italic>SpRg-1, SpRg-4a </italic>and <italic>SpRg-7 </italic>QTL peaks.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The results obtained in this study may very well represent a significant step toward the goal of understanding the processes underlying tomato tissue culture and regeneration responses. We have situated six QTLs on chromosomes 1, 3, 4, 7 and 8, five from <italic>S. pennellii </italic>and one from <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>. The most important QTLs are <italic>SpRg-1</italic>, which is most likely associated with the morphogenetic response, and <italic>SpRg-7</italic>, which promotes bud development. A QTL detected on chromosome 3, <italic>Rg-3</italic>, likely contains a putative allele of the <italic>Rg-1 </italic>and <italic>Rg-2 </italic>genes, as is shown by mapping the acid invertase gene linked to <italic>Rg-2</italic>. QTLs detected on chromosomes 8 and 4 most likely contain genes influencing bud formation and development, respectively.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Plant materials and growing conditions</title><p><italic>S. pennellii </italic>PE-47, which showed a high ability for regeneration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], and the tomato cultivar Anl27 (cv. Anl27), with a low ability for regeneration, were chosen for obtaining the mapping population. The initial genotypes were established <italic>in vitro</italic>, starting with the sterilization of seeds by immersion for 10 min in a solution of 25% commercial bleach (40 g L<sup>-1 </sup>active chlorine), being then washed twice with sterile deionized water for 5 min each and then sown in Petri dishes containing nutrient medium (Murashige and Skoog [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>] salts including vitamins, 2% sucrose, 0.6% plant agar (DUCHEFA, the Netherlands). The pHs of the media were adjusted to 5.8 before sterilization at 121&#x000b0;C for 20 min. Cultures were incubated in a growth chamber at 26&#x000b0;C &#x000b1; 2&#x000b0;C under a 16h photoperiod with cool white light provided by Sylvania cool white F37T8/CW fluorescent lamps (90 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>-2 </sup>s<sup>-1</sup>). Clones of one plant of each genotype were obtained and maintained in <italic>in vitro </italic>culture. The clones were multiplied by transferring nodes to tubes with fresh basal medium (BM: Murashige and Skoog -[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>]- salts including vitamins, 1.5% sucrose and 7 g L<sup>-1 </sup>plant agar) every 3-4 weeks. The tubes were 15 cm in length and 22 mm in diameter, with 15 ml of medium per tube.</p></sec><sec><title>Mapping population</title><p>One clone of tomato and another of <italic>S. pennellii </italic>were transferred to a greenhouse in order to obtain the F<sub>1 </sub>plant that was reintroduced <italic>in vitro </italic>by disinfection of shoots following a similar procedure as that carried out for seed sterilization. F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1 </sub>populations were obtained and seeds were germinated <italic>in vitro </italic>as described above.</p><p>The F<sub>2 </sub>mapping population was composed of 106 individuals obtained from selfing one F<sub>1 </sub>plant, the result of a cross between the tomato cv. Anl27 (P1) and <italic>S. pennellii </italic>PE-47 (P2). The backcross (BC<sub>1</sub>) mapping population, composed of 113 plants, was obtained by crossing the cv. Anl27 and the F<sub>1 </sub>plant. To allow the test to be reproduced, the F<sub>1 </sub>plant and F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1 </sub>individuals were clonally replicated and maintained <italic>in vitro </italic>as described above.</p></sec><sec><title>Evaluation of the regeneration capacity</title><p>A first assay was performed with cloned P1, P2 and F<sub>1 </sub>plants. Leaf disks (0.6-0.8 cm<sup>2</sup>) obtained from <italic>in vitro </italic>cultured plants that were at a similar growing stage were placed with the abaxial side in contact with the shoot induction medium (SIM) containing Murashige and Skoog salts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>], 3% sucrose, 7% plant agar and 0.2 mg L<sup>-1 </sup>zeatin riboside (ZR). This growth regulator was sterilized by filtration and added to the sterile SIM. After 30 days of culture on SIM, the explants were transferred to BM for 20 days. In this medium, buds develop into shoots. For each genotype, five explants per plate (90 &#x000d7; 25 mm with 40 ml of medium per plate) and 10 repetitions per genotype were evaluated. At the end of the experiment, the following variables were analyzed:</p><p>-Bud percentage (B): number of explants with buds &#x000d7; 100/total number of cultured explants.</p><p>-Regeneration percentage (R): number of cultures that differentiated into completely developed shoots &#x000d7; 100/total number of cultured explants.</p><p>-Productivity rate (PR): total number of completely developed shoots/total number of cultured explants that regenerated plants.</p><p>In a second assay, leaf explants of F<sub>2</sub>, BC<sub>1</sub>, P1, P2 and F<sub>1 </sub>plants were tested as explained above. In this case, for each genotype, five explants per plate and 4 repetitions per genotype were evaluated. Data for regeneration was obtained for 102 genotypes of the F<sub>2 </sub>population and 104 genotypes of BC<sub>1</sub>. The average value for each trait and genotype was used for QTL analysis.</p><p>To assess the effect of genotype on regeneration ability, data from the genetically uniform classes (P1, P2 and F<sub>1</sub>) were subjected to a unifactorial analysis of variance (ANOVA), and then means for the different traits were separated by a Duncan test. The correlations between the different traits were calculated using the Statgraphics Plus 4.0 software.</p></sec><sec><title>Genotyping</title><sec><title>Preparation of genomic DNA</title><p>Young leaves from <italic>in vitro</italic>-cultured plants were collected and immediately frozen with liquid nitrogen and then stored at -80&#x000b0;C. DNA was prepared based on the modified CTAB method of Doyle and Doyle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Subsequently, quality and quantity of the DNA was evaluated on 0.8% agarose gel stained with ethidium bromide and using the NanoDrop<sup>&#x000ae; </sup>ND-1000 Spectrophotometer.</p></sec><sec><title>Amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP) procedure</title><p>AFLPs were obtained following de Vos et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>] procedure. Fifteen and sixteen selective combinations of primers were used for the F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1 </sub>populations, respectively. The code of each selective combination is specified in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>. Each code followed by the number corresponding to each obtained band (size in bp) is used to name the polymorphic AFLPs. Electrophoresis of the PCR products was conducted using an ABI PRISM 310 Genetic Analyzer (PerkinElmer Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California, USA). GeneScan&#x02122; 600 LIZ<sup>&#x000ae; </sup>Size Standard, with fluorophore LIZ, was used as a molecular size marker. Raw data were analyzed with the GeneScan 3.1.2 analysis software (PerkinElmer Applied Biosystems) and the resulting GeneScan trace files were imported into Genographer 1.6.0. The AFLP fragments between 60 to 380 bp were scored in Genographer as present (1) or absent (0).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Selective combinations of primers used for F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1 </sub>genotyping</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Code</th><th align="left">Mapping population</th><th align="left">Selective primers combination</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">ME1</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub>, BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CTA<italic>-EcoRI </italic>AAC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME2</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAA<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME3</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAA<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME4</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub>, BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAA<italic>-EcoRI </italic>AGC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME5</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAC<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME6</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub>, BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAC-<italic>EcoRI </italic>ACG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME7</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAC<italic>-EcoRI </italic>AGC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME8</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub>, BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAA<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME9</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub>, BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAA<italic>-EcoRI </italic>AAC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME10</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CTA<italic>-EcoRI </italic>AGC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME11</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CTC<italic>-EcoRI </italic>AGC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME12</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CCG<italic>-EcoRI </italic>AAC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME13</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CCG<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME14</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CCG<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME15</td><td align="left">F<sub>2</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CTC<italic>-EcoRI </italic>AGG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME16</td><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAA<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACT</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME17</td><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CTA<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME18</td><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CTA<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ATG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME19</td><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CTA<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME20</td><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CCT<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME21</td><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CCT<italic>-EcoRI </italic>AAC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME22</td><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CCT<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ATG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME23</td><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CCT<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME24</td><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAC<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ACC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME25</td><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAC<italic>-EcoRI </italic>ATG</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ME26</td><td align="left">BC<sub>1</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>MseI </italic>CAC<italic>-EcoRI </italic>AGG</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Microsatellites (SSRs)</title><p>One hundred and forty-nine SSR markers were used to detect polymorphism between P1 and P2, which included 89 SSRs previously reported and mapped onto the Tomato-EXPEN 2000 available at SGN [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>], along with 60 new SSRs: 18 from the COMAV research group "Aprovechamiento de la variabilidad estraespec&#x000ed;fica en la mejora del tomate" and 42 designed from sequences deposited in Genbank (see Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>). Primer pairs were designed from these sequences using the SSR Primer 3 tool <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://frodo.wi.mit.edu/">http://frodo.wi.mit.edu/</ext-link>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. The criteria used for designing the primers were as follows: the primer Tm ranged from 55 to 65&#x000b0;C and GC content was 50%. The presence of G or C bases within the last five bases from the 3' end of primers (GC clamp), which helps promote specific binding at the 3' end, was taken into account. In order to design the SSRs, wherever possible the AT/TA repetitions were selected based on the results obtained by Frary et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>].</p><p>All the SSRs, with the exception of those specified below, were labelled following the M13-tail method described by Schuelke et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>]. DNA amplification was carried out in volumes of 15 &#x003bc;L using a sample of 10 ng of DNA. The reaction mixture contained 1.5 &#x003bc;L 10 &#x000d7; PCR buffer [75 mM Tris-HCl (Ph 9.0), 50 mM KCl, 20 mM (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4 </sub>and 0.001% BSA], 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 200 &#x003bc;M dNTPs, 0.133 &#x003bc;M of primers, 0.2 &#x003bc;M of fluorescent labelled M13 primer and 0.3 units of <italic>Taq</italic>I DNA polymerase (Need S. L., Valencia, Spain). An Eppendorf 5333 Thermal Cycler was used. The PCR parameters included the following: an initial 3 min at 94&#x000b0;C; 35 cycles, each with 30 s DNA denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C; 45 s at an annealing temperature (depending on the primer combination Tm) and a 1 min extension at 72&#x000b0;C, and a final extension of 10 min at 72&#x000b0;C. Amplified bands were visualized using a LI-COR sequencing gel (DNA LI-COR 4300; LI-COR Biosciences, Lincoln, Nebraska, USA); 10 &#x003bc;l of loading buffer (95% formamide, 2 mM EDTA, 0.001% bromophenol blue) and 5 &#x003bc;l of deionized water were added to the 5 &#x003bc;l PCR mix (2.5 &#x003bc;l of each IRDye 700 or IRDye800-labeled) samples which were denatured at 96&#x000b0;C for 8 min. Electrophoresis was performed in denaturing conditions at 50&#x000b0;C, using 6% acrylamide gels in TBE buffer.</p><p>The SSR356, SSR73, SSR248, SSR46 markers in which polymorphisms were visible in the agarose gels were amplified in volumes of 23.32 &#x003bc;l with: 10 ng of DNA, 1.6 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 171.52 &#x003bc;M dNTPs, 0.214 &#x003bc;M of primers, 2.5 &#x003bc;l of 10 &#x000d7; PCR buffer, and 0.6 U <italic>Taq</italic>I DNA polymerase. The PCR conditions were similar to those applied before, with the exception of a final extension of 30 min in this case. Amplified bands were run in standard agarose gels (1 or 2%) in TAE buffer at 100V and visualized by ethidium bromide staining.</p></sec><sec><title>Conserved ortholog set (COS) and cleaved amplified polymorphic sequence (CAPS) markers</title><p>Ninety-six markers (86 COSII, 6 COSI, 4 CAPS) from the Tomato-EXPEN 2000 map [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>] and one developed CAPS marker (Solyc07g049350) were tested for polymorphism between the P1 and P2 parents. The restriction enzymes used when required were those indicated in the SGN database. When restriction enzymes was needed, the protocol described in the commercial product's instructions (Fermentas, York, UK or Biolabs, Takara, Japan) was followed.</p><p>The PCR reaction was performed in a total volume of 12 &#x003bc;L using a sample of 10 ng of DNA. The reaction mixture contained 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 200 &#x003bc;M dNTPs, 0.25 &#x003bc;m of primers, 1.2 &#x003bc;L PCR buffer 10X, and 0.3 U <italic>Taq</italic>I DNA polymerase. Amplification was performed using an Eppendorf 5333 Thermal Cycler, which was programmed as follows: 5 min at 94&#x000b0;C, 35 30-s cycles each at 94&#x000b0;C, 1 min at Ta (depending on the primer combination Tm) and a 2 min extension at 72&#x000b0;C, with a final stage of 10 min at 72&#x000b0;C. Amplified bands were separated by 1 or 2% agarose electrophoresis in TAE buffer at 100V, and visualized by ethidium bromide staining.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Map construction and QTL mapping</title><p>Linkage analysis for both mapping populations was performed with the JoinMap<sup>&#x000ae; </sup>4.0 software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. Markers were grouped into linkage groups at LOD &#x02265; 3, with the exception of those in chromosomes 9 and 10 of the BC<sub>1 </sub>mapping population with LOD &#x02265; 2. Order was determined with a recombination threshold of 0.40 and distances were calculated using the Kosambi mapping function (Kosambi 1944). For the genetic map construction, AFLP, SSR, COS and CAPS markers were used (Additional File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">8</xref>). The segregation ratio of alleles was evaluated for each locus by the Chi-square test with a significance threshold of P &#x0003c; 0.05. The expected segregation ratios were 3:1 and 1:1 for F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1</sub>, respectively. Visual representations of the marker maps were created with the MapChart software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>].</p><p>QTL analysis on the F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1 </sub>phenotypic data sets was performed with the MapQTL<sup>&#x000ae; </sup>6.0 software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. Significance thresholds for the LOD values, corresponding to a genome-wide false discovery rate of 5% (p &#x0003c; 0.05) were calculated by genome-wide permutation tests using 1, 000 permutations. Firstly, IM analysis was performed (simple Interval Mapping). Then, if many putative QTLs were detected by IM, markers close to the likelihood peaks of the detected QTLs were used as cofactors for rMQM (also called composite Interval Mapping) analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>Locating candidate genes and looking for other regeneration-related genes</title><p>The <italic>S. pennellii </italic>acid invertase gene (inv<italic><sup>penn</sup></italic>) was analyzed and mapped as a marker. Primers described by Harada et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>] were used for DNA amplification using conditions previously described for COS and CAPS markers. Amplified bands were separated using the multicapillary electrophoresis QIAxcel System (Qiagen, Valencia, California, USA). We searched for the location of the <italic>LESK1 </italic>gene at SGN and for its nearest markers at International Tomato Annotation Group. This database was also used for looking for genes putatively related to organogenesis.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>CG obtained the mapping populations. CT conducted the population phenotyping and genotyping and participated in the drafting. CT and SV performed the map construction and QTL mapping. CG collaborated in the phenotyping and genotyping and conceived, supervised and drafted the manuscript. FN conceived of the study and contributed to critically reviewing the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>Regeneration response of leaf explants</bold>. Regeneration response of leaf explants from parents [tomato (cv. Anl27); <italic>S. pennellii </italic>(PE-47)], F<sub>1</sub>, F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1 </sub>populations, cultured on shoot induction medium (SIM) for 30 days and transferred to basal medium (BM) for 20 days.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-11-140-S1.PDF" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>In silico-designed SSR markers</bold>. Table with the name, band size, repeat motif, temperature of annealing and primers sequences of in silico-designed SSR markers.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-11-140-S2.PDF" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3</title><p><bold>Genetic location and LOD score profile of the F<sub>2</sub>-QTLs for regeneration components detected by Interval Mapping on chromosome 7 (<italic>SpRg-7</italic>)</bold>. Genetic location and LOD score profile of the F<sub>2</sub>-QTLs for regeneration components (Bud percentage (B), Regeneration percentage (R) and Productivity Rate (PR)). On the left, projections of QTLs as black bars indicate the <italic>SpRg-7 </italic>for B, R and PR traits. The vertical dotted line indicates the 95% significant threshold value for declaring a QTL (B LOD threshold = 3.7) (R LOD threshold = 3.6) (PR LOD threshold = 4.4). Map position (cM) and distances are based on the genetic linkage map developed in this study. QTLs characteristics in attached table.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-11-140-S3.PDF" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional file 4</title><p><bold>Genetic location and LOD score profile of the BC<sub>1</sub>-QTLs for Bud percentage (B), detected on chromosomes 1 (<italic>SpRg-1</italic>), 3 (<italic>SpRg-3</italic>) and 8 (<italic>SlRg-8</italic>)</bold>. Results from the Interval Mapping (IM) and restricted Multiple QTL Mapping (rMQM) approaches. On the left, projections as black bars (IM) and grey bars (rMQM) indicate the range of <italic>SpRg-1, SpRg-3 </italic>and <italic>SlRg-8 </italic>QTLs for B. The vertical dotted line indicates the 95% significant threshold value for declaring a QTL (B LOD threshold = 2.7). The horizontal dotted line indicates the position of the acid invertase gene (inv<italic><sup>penn</sup></italic>) marker included in the chromosome 3 QTL range. Map position (cM) and distances are based on the genetic linkage map developed in this study.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-11-140-S4.PDF" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5"><caption><title>Additional file 5</title><p><bold>Genetic location and LOD score profile of the BC<sub>1</sub>-QTLs for Regeneration percentage (R), detected in this study on chromosomes 1 (<italic>SpRg-1</italic>), 4 (<italic>SpRg-4a</italic>), 7 (<italic>SpRg-7</italic>) and 8 (<italic>SlRg-8</italic>)</bold>. Results from the Interval Mapping (IM) and restricted Multiple QTL Mapping (rMQM) approaches. On the left, projections as black bars (IM) and grey bars (rMQM) indicate the range of <italic>SpRg-1, SpRg-4a, SpRg-7 </italic>and <italic>SlRg-8 </italic>QTLs for R. The vertical dotted line indicates the 95% significant threshold value for declaring a QTL (R LOD threshold = 2.7). Map position (cM) and distances are based on the genetic linkage map developed in this study.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-11-140-S5.PDF" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S6"><caption><title>Additional file 6</title><p><bold>Genetic location and LOD score profile of the BC<sub>1</sub>-QTLs for Productivity Rate (PR), detected in this study on chromosomes 1 (<italic>SpRg-1</italic>), 3 (<italic>SpRg-3</italic>), 4 (<italic>SpRg-4b</italic>) and 7 (<italic>SpRg-7</italic>)</bold>. Results from the Interval Mapping (IM) and restricted Multiple QTL Mapping (rMQM) approaches. On the left, projections as black bars (IM) and grey bars (rMQM) indicate the range of <italic>SpRg-1, SpRg-3, SpRg-4b </italic>and <italic>SpRg-7 </italic>for PR. The vertical dotted line indicates the 95% significant threshold value for declaring a QTL (PR LOD threshold = 2.8). Horizontal dotted lines indicate the position of the acid invertase gene (inv<italic><sup>penn</sup></italic>) marker included in the chromosome 3 QTL range. Map position (cM) and distances are based on the genetic linkage map developed in this study.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-11-140-S6.PDF" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S7"><caption><title>Additional file 7</title><p><bold>Polymorphic acid invertase gene marker (<italic>inv<sup>penn</sup></italic>)</bold>. Amplified bands separated using the multicapillary electrophoresis QIAxcel System. Lane 1: <italic>S. lycopersicum </italic>L. (Anl27), band size (~162bp). Lane 2: <italic>S. pennellii </italic>PE-47, band size (~173bp). Lane 3: F<sub>1 </sub>Hybrid <italic>S. lycopersicum </italic>L. (Anl27) &#x000d7; <italic>S. pennellii </italic>PE-47, both bands (~162bp-~173bp). Lane 4: negative control.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-11-140-S7.PDF" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S8"><caption><title>Additional file 8</title><p><bold>Markers used for genotyping the F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1 </sub>population</bold>. SSR, COS, COSII, CAP markers used for genotyping the F<sub>2 </sub>and BC<sub>1 </sub>population.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-11-140-S8.PDF" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>CG and CT thank the Spanish 'Ministerio de Educaci&#x000f3;n y Ciencia' for a Ram&#x000f3;n y Cajal contract and a predoctoral fellowship, respectively. The authors acknowledge the financial support of the Instituto de Conservaci&#x000f3;n y Mejora de la Agrodiversidad Valenciana (COMAV), suggestions from Dr. J. Ca&#x000f1;izares, SSRs designed by O. Juli&#x000e1;n and the technical assistance of N. Palacios. The revision and the English revision of the manuscript by A. Monforte and J. Bergen, respectively, are also acknowledged.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashwath</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Senaratna</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Tissue culture studies of tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>)</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult</source><year>2004</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Engelmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>In vitro conservation of tropical plant germplasm</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>1991</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00039669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><article-title>Special symposium: In vitro plant recalcitrance: An introduction</article-title><source>In Vitro Cell Dev Biol Plant</source><year>2000</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11627-000-0029-z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hamza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chupeau</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>Re-evaluation of conditions for plant regeneration and Agrobacterium-mediated transformation from tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>)</article-title><source>J Exp Bot</source><year>1993</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>1837</fpage><lpage>1845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/44.12.1837</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Earle</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><article-title>An examination of factors affecting the efficiency of Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of tomato</article-title><source>Plant Cell Rep</source><year>1996</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>240</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>LEP</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgante</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Vecchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sluys</surname><given-names>MAv</given-names></name><article-title>Shoot regeneration capacity from roots and transgenic hairy roots of tomato cultivars and wild related species</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult</source><year>2001</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1010631731559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanhart</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>A genetic analysis of cell culture traits in tomato</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1987</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00288863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wijbrandi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>JGM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Transfer of regeneration capacity from <italic>Lycopersicon peruvianum </italic>to <italic>L. esculentum </italic>by protoplast fusion</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult</source><year>1988</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00040085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takashina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Egashira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Imanishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>New molecular markers linked with the high shoot regeneration capacity of the wild tomato species Lycopersicon chilense</article-title><source>Breed Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1270/jsbbs1951.48.109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Destro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bespalhok</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Illg</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><article-title>Introgression of in vitro regeneration capability of <italic>Lycopersicon pimpinellifolium </italic>Mill. into recalcitrant tomato cultivars</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2002</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1015693902836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Organogenesis in vitro</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5266(99)80012-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10047565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaux</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular analysis of in vitro shoot organogenesis</article-title><source>Crit Rev Plant Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07352680490484569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hemerly</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>de Almeida Engler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Montagu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Engler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Inze</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>cdc2a expression in Arabidopsis is linked with competence for cell division</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>1993</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1711</fpage><lpage>1723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8305869</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Skoog</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><article-title>Chemical regulation of growth and organ formation in plant tissue cultures <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Symp Soc Exp Biol</source><year>1957</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13486467</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Identification of CRE1 as a cytokinin receptor from Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>409</volume><fpage>1060</fpage><lpage>1063</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35059117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11234017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ueguchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>The AHK4 gene involved in the cytokinin-signalling pathway as a direct receptor molecule in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant and Cell Physiology</source><year>2001</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pce094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11479382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueguchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Genetic analysis of Arabidopsis histidine kinase genes encoding cytokinin receptors reveals their overlapping biological functions in the regulation of shoot and root growth in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1365</fpage><lpage>1377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.021477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15155880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Banno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>QW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><article-title>Overexpression of Arabidopsis <italic>ESR1 </italic>induces initiation of shoot regeneration</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2609</fpage><lpage>2618</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Banno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>QW</given-names></name><name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><article-title>The <italic>ENHANCER OF SHOOT REGENERATION 2 </italic>gene in Arabidopsis Regulates <italic>CUP-SHAPED COTYLEDON 1 </italic>at the transcriptional level and controls cotyledon development</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1443</fpage><lpage>1456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcl023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17056621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mase</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashiba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Banno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Expression patterns of Arabidopsis ERF VIII-b subgroup genes during in vitro shoot regeneration and effects of their overexpression on shoot regeneration efficiency</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5511/plantbiotechnology.24.481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Illg</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><article-title>Inheritance of <italic>in vitro </italic>plant regeneration ability in the tomato</article-title><source>Braz J Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>116</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Satoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takashina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Escalante</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Egashira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Imanishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Molecular markers mapped around the high shoot regeneration capacity gene <italic>Rg-2 </italic>in <italic>Lycopersicon chilense</italic></article-title><source>Breed Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>50</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>256</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pratta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>C&#x000e1;nepa</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Zorzoli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Picardi</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><article-title>Diallel analysis of in vitro culture traits in the genus <italic>Lycopersicon</italic></article-title><source>HortScience</source><year>2003</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>112</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marchionni</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratta</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zorzoli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Genetic analysis of the in vitro culture response in tomato</article-title><source>Plant Cell Tissue Organ Cult</source><year>2007</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11240-006-9195-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bade</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanhart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Horsman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Soppe</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Vekerk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Characterization and mapping of a gene controlling shoot regeneration in tomato</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>1993</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.1993.tb00016.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Torelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Soragni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrucco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>New potential markers of <italic>in vitro </italic>tomato morphogenesis identified by mRNA differential display</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>891</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00020486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8980540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Torelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Soragni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Borinato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Branca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>The expression of <italic>LESK1 </italic>morphogenetic marker along the tomato hypocotyl axis is linked to a position-dependent competence for shoot regeneration</article-title><source>Plant Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>166</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2003.09.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Torelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Borinato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Soragni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolpagni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottura</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Branca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>The delay in hormonal treatment modulates the expression of <italic>LESK1</italic>, a gene encoding a putative serine-threonine kinase, marker of in vitro caulogenesis in tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum </italic>Mill.)</article-title><source>Plant Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>167</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2004.05.007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gisbert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Arrillaga</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Roig</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Adquisition of a collection of <italic>Lycopersicon pennellii </italic>(Corr. D'Arcy) transgenic plants with <italic>uid</italic>A and <italic>npt</italic>II marker genes</article-title><source>J Hortic Sci Biotechnol</source><year>1999</year><volume>74</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>109</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu-Abied</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saranga</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Lycopersicon esculentum </italic>lines containing small overlapping introgressions from <italic>L. pennellii</italic></article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1992</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1034</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Komatsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Annaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Genetic mapping of a quantitative trait locus (QTL) that enhances the shoot differentiation rate in <italic>Hordeum vulgare </italic>L</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1993</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>720</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Taguchi-Shiobara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanno</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Komatsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Mapping quantitative trait loci associated with regeneration ability of seed callus in rice, <italic>Oryza sativa </italic>L</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>828</fpage><lpage>833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220050632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Flores Berrios</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentzbittel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokrani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Alibert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarrafi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Genetic control of early events in protoplast division and regeneration pathways in sunflower</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>606</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220051522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bolibok</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakoczy-Trojanowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Genetic mapping of QTLs for tissue-culture response in plants</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2006</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-005-9055-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Respuesta correlacionada de la capacidad de regeneraci&#x000f3;n en distintos tipos de explante en <italic>Cucumis melo</italic></article-title><source>Actas Horticultura</source><year>1989</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>118</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Correlated response of in vitro regeneration capacity from different source of explants in <italic>Cucumis melo</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell Rep</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01690269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Sexual transmission of the in vitro regeneration capacity via caulogenesis of <italic>Cucumis melo L</italic>. in a medium with a high auxin/cytokinin ratio</article-title><source>Sci Hortic</source><year>1997</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-4238(97)00024-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Asamizu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohyama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000b7;Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000b7;Tabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>An interspecific linkage map of SSR and intronic polymorphism markers in tomato</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-010-1344-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20431859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Effects of missing marker and segregation distortion on QTL mapping in F<sub>2 </sub>populations</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>1071</fpage><lpage>1082</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-010-1372-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20535442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chaerani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smulders</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Linden</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Vosman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Voorrips</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><article-title>QTL identification for early blight resistance (<italic>Alternaria solani</italic>) in a <italic>Solanum lycopersicum </italic>x <italic>S. arcanum </italic>cross</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17093974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>de Vicente</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><article-title>QTL analysis of transgressive segregation in an interspecific tomato cross</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1993</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8100788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ben Amer</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Korzun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Worland</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;rner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Genetic mapping of QTLs controlling tissue-culture response on chromosome 2B of wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum </italic>L.) in relation to major genes and RFLP markers</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>1047</fpage><lpage>1052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220050513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schiantarelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De La Pena</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Candela</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Use of recombinant inbred lines (RILs) to identify, locate and map major genes and quantitative trait loci involved with <italic>in vitro </italic>regeneration ability in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220051650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><article-title><italic>PkMADS1 </italic>is a novel MADS box gene regulating adventitious shoot induction and vegetative shoot development in <italic>Paulownia kawakamii</italic></article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2002</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0960-7412.2001.01206.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11851917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bielenberg</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhebentyayeva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reighard</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Sequencing and annotation of the evergrowing locus in peach [Prunus persica (L.) Batsch] reveals a cluster of six MADS-box transcription factors as candidate genes for regulation of terminal bud formation</article-title><source>Tree Genet Genomes</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11295-007-0126-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Murashige</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Skoog</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>A revised medium for rapid growth and bioassays with tobacco tissue cultures</article-title><source>Physiol Plant</source><year>1962</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.1962.tb08052.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><article-title>Isolation of plant DNA from fresh tissue</article-title><source>Focus</source><year>1990</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleeker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reijans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Lee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frijters</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peleman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuiper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>AFLP: a new technique for DNA fingerprinting</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1995</year><volume>23</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>4407</fpage><lpage>4414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/23.21.4407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7501463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Frary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tedeschi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Development of a set of PCR-based anchor markers encompassing the tomato genome and evaluation of their usefulness for genetics and breeding experiments</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2005</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-005-2023-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15926074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Solow</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Skwarecki</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Buels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Binns</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>The SOL Genomics Network: a comparative resource for Solanaceae biology and beyond</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>1310</fpage><lpage>1317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.060707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16010005</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Rozen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Skaletsky</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Krawetz S, Misener S</person-group><article-title>Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers</article-title><source>Bioinformatics Methods and Protocols: Methods in Molecular Biology</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>Totowa, NJ: Humana Press</publisher-name><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>386</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schuelke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>An economic method for the fluorescent labelling of PCR fragments</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><year>2000</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/72708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10657137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Hoeven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eannetta</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><article-title>Identification, analysis and utilization of a conserved ortholog set markers for comparative genomics in Higher Plants</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1457</fpage><lpage>1467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.010479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12119367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crouzillat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Petiard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><article-title>Combining Bioinformatics and Phylogenetics to Identify Large Sets of Single Copy, Orthologous Genes (COSII) for Comparative, Evolutinonary and Systematics Studies: A Test Case in the Euasterid Plant Clade</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>174</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1407</fpage><lpage>1420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.106.062455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16951058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Van Ooijen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><source>JoinMap 4, Software for the calculation of genetic linkage maps in experimental populations</source><year>2006</year><publisher-name>Wageningen, Netherlands: Kyazma BV</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Voorrips</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><article-title>MapChart: Software for the graphical presentation of linkage maps and QTLs</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>2002</year><volume>93</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jhered/93.1.77</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Van Ooijen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><source>MapQTL &#x000ae; 6, Software for the mapping of quantitative trait loci in experimental populations of diploid species</source><year>2009</year><publisher-name>Wageningen, Netherlands: Kyazma BV</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20234834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishiguro</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Genetic analysis of the trait of sucrose accumulation in tomato fruit using molecular marker</article-title><source>Breeding Sci</source><year>1995</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1270/jsbbs1951.45.429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>