<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3462117</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2229-12-133</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22871151</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-12-133</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evidence of cryptic introgression in tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> L.) based on wild tomato species alleles</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Labate</surname><given-names>Joanne A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>joanne.labate@ars.usda.gov</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>Larry D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>larry.robertson@ars.usda.gov</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>USDA-ARS Plant Genetic Resources Unit, 630 W. North Street, Geneva, NY, 14456, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>7</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9;2012 Labate and Robertson; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Labate and Robertson; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2229/12/133"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Many highly beneficial traits (e.g. disease or abiotic stress resistance) have been transferred into crops through crosses with their wild relatives. The 13 recognized species of tomato (<italic>Solanum</italic> section <italic>Lycopersicon</italic>) are closely related to each other and wild species genes have been extensively used for improvement of the crop, <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> L. In addition, the lack of geographical barriers has permitted natural hybridization between <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and its closest wild relative <italic>Solanum pimpinellifolium</italic> in Ecuador, Peru and northern Chile. In order to better understand patterns of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> diversity, we sequenced 47 markers ranging in length from 130 to 1200&#x02009;bp (total of 24&#x02009;kb) in genotypes of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and wild tomato species <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>, <italic>Solanum arcanum</italic>, <italic>Solanum peruvianum</italic>, <italic>Solanum pennellii</italic> and <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic>. Between six and twelve genotypes were comparatively analyzed per marker. Several of the markers had previously been hypothesized as carrying wild species alleles within <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, i.e., cryptic introgressions.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Each marker was mapped with high confidence (e&#x0003c;1 x 10<sup>-30</sup>) to a single genomic location using BLASTN against tomato whole genome shotgun chromosomes (SL2.40) database. Neighbor-joining trees showed high mean bootstrap support (86.8 &#x000b1; 2.34%) for distinguishing red-fruited from green-fruited taxa for 38 of the markers. Hybridization and parsimony splits networks, genomic map positions of markers relative to documented introgressions, and historical origins of accessions were used to interpret evolutionary patterns at nine markers with putatively introgressed alleles.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Of the 47 genetic markers surveyed in this study, four were involved in linkage drag on chromosome 9 during introgression breeding, while alleles at five markers apparently originated from natural hybridization with <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> and were associated with primitive genotypes of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>. The positive identification of introgressed genes within crop species such as <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> will help inform conservation and utilization of crop germplasm diversity, for example, facilitating the purging of undesirable linkage drag or the exploitation of novel, favorable alleles.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Cryptic introgression</kwd><kwd>Linkage drag</kwd><kwd>Breeding</kwd><kwd>DNA sequence</kwd><kwd><italic>Solanum</italic> species</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Introgression is the transfer of genes of one species into the gene pool of another via hybridization. As a phenomenon, it has been an important topic in animal and plant genetics research for many different reasons. For example, introgression has been implicated in the adaptation of modern humans 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] and is of concern to conservation biologists due to loss of integrity of wild bird and mammal populations 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. In plants, introgression is a key concept in studies of the risks of contamination of natural populations by genetically modified (GM) crops. More commonly in crops, favorable genes from wild relatives are intentionally transferred into breeding lines for cultivar development. This has been particularly valuable in crop species that are relatively low in genetic diversity.</p><p>According to a review of crop introgression breeding 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] the major functional categories of beneficial traits transferred from wild species are resistance or tolerance to abiotic stress or disease, yield, cytoplasmic male sterility or fertility restorers for hybrid production, and quality traits. Among the pioneering uses of wild crop relatives during the late 19<sup>th</sup> to early 20<sup>th</sup> centuries were the transfer of disease resistances into grape (<italic>Vitis vinifera</italic>) 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] and sugarcane (<italic>Saccarum officinarum</italic>) 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. A 1986 review of 23 crops estimated that 6% of total annual economic value in the US was contributed by crop wild relatives 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. For 13 major crops of global importance, it was estimated that 46 wild species have been used in released cultivars, and that furthermore, the introgression breeding approach is increasing 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Lack of information on pedigrees, unpublished activities within the private sector and changes in taxonomy are some of the factors that contribute to the uncertainty of the collective impacts of crop introgression breeding 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p><p>Some of the earliest tomato introgression breeding in the US may have been done indirectly and unwittingly via the French variety Merville des March&#x000e9;s. Recent phenotypic data collected for Merville des March&#x000e9;s PI 109834 showed it to be variable in fruit size and smoothness (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ars-grin.gov/cgi-bin/npgs/acc/display.pl?1129442">http://www.ars-grin.gov/cgi-bin/npgs/acc/display.pl?1129442</ext-link>); its genotype was segregating, showed population admixture, and was an outlier based on genetic distance relative to many other <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> accessions 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. We postulated that these were indications of <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> in its ancestry (this idea was examined in the current study). The <italic>Fusarium</italic> wilt-resistant processing variety Marvel 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] was selected from Merville des March&#x000e9;s in the early 1900s, and Marvel was a parent of Marglobe released in 1925 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], which in turn can be found in the pedigree of many important varieties from the 1930s through the late 1950s (H.M. Munger&#x02019;s tomato pedigree chart provided by E.D. Cobb, Cornell University, 2012). Direct introgression of tomato with wild species in the US commenced in the 1930s concurrent with collection expeditions to geographic centers of origin. The first released cultivar, developed from Marglobe x <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>, was aptly named Pan American 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Introgression breeding efforts of tomato increased globally post World War II, involving the screening of a wide range of traits and all wild tomato species 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Such efforts continue to be of utmost priority today using sophisticated tools such as introgression libraries for gene discovery 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p><p>Compellingly, of 96 introgressed traits tallied in released crop cultivars for 11 species (cassava, wheat, millet, rice, maize, sunflower, lettuce, banana, potato, groundnut, tomato), 55 of them were in tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> L.); the next highest numbers were found in rice and potato with 12 traits each 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The emphasis and success of introgression breeding in tomato encompasses several factors including its intrinsically narrow genetic base, relative ease of crossing with several wild taxa, production demands based on growing conditions and market niche, its susceptibility to pests and pathogens, and its sensitivity to abiotic factors. In addition to resistance or tolerance to dozens of bacterial, viral, fungal, insect, and nematode pathogens, hundreds of favorable genes or quantitative trait loci (QTL) for abiotic stress resistance, flower and fruit traits, yield, and plant architecture have been mapped in wild tomato species 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>] and thus hold the potential to be exploited.</p><p>Introgression breeding carries a cost, namely, genetic linkage of non-targeted loci that are eliminated through repeated backcrossing. Linkage drag can persist within a genome despite backcrossing, especially if recombination is suppressed. Several examples of linkage drag in tomato and other crops have been quantified using molecular markers 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Linkage drag can denote favorable, deleterious or neutral alleles that become inadvertently incorporated into breeding lines or cultivars.</p><p>In this study we apply the term &#x02018;cryptic introgression&#x02019; 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] to describe latent genetic variation in <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> that originated from wild tomato species. Various scenarios can be evoked for its origins ranging from linkage drag, hybridization between feral <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and wild relatives, to crossing in open-pollinated populations by wind or insect vectors with pollen of introgressed cultivars 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Cryptic introgression is of interest in germplasm collections such as those conserved at United States Department of Agriculture, Agricultural Research Service (USDA, ARS) Plant Genetic Resources Unit (PGRU) because it can indicate novel genetic variation for exploitation by end-users, or conversely, reveal unfavorable and hence undesirable alleles with respect to crop improvement.</p><p>In previous reports we hypothesized the detection of cryptic introgression in 5% to 10% of DNA markers that were resequenced in tomato germplasm panels 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. The aim of the current study was to gather additional evidence on these alleles by resequencing and analyzing the same markers in several accessions of wild tomato species and one accession of weedy <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> (Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Although variation within wild species gene pools made it impracticable to attempt to discover the 100% identical homologous allele, the assumption was that introgressed alleles would be more closely related to the alleles of a particular wild species than to their <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> homologs. To identify introgressed alleles we also used evidence from mapped locations of markers, phenotypic descriptions, and historical origins of lines and accessions.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Tomato samples analyzed in this study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Species</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Accession or line</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Description</bold><sup>
<bold>a</bold>
</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 126445<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">collected from Peru in 1937, source of <italic>Cyc</italic>-<italic>B</italic>, green-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum pennellii</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 414773<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">collected from Peru in 1976, source of <italic>I</italic>-<italic>1</italic>, <italic>I</italic>-<italic>3</italic>, green-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum peruvianum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">G 32592 (LA4125)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">naturally selfing, collected from Chile in 2001, green-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum peruvianum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">LA1537<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">artificially inbred from PI 128650 collected from Chile in 1938 and source of <italic>Tm-2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>, green-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum arcanum</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">G 32591 (LA2157)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">naturally selfing, collected from Peru in 1980, source of <italic>Cm</italic> QTLs, green-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum pimpinellifolium</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 370093<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">traces back to Vaughan Seed Co., Chicago, USA, circa 1930, source of <italic>Cf-2</italic>, <italic>Cf-3</italic>, <italic>Pto</italic>, red-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 303801<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Peru Wild (syn. with Utah 665) from Utah Agr. Expt. Sta., source of <italic>Ve</italic>, red-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 99782<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Tomate, collected in 1932 from Peru, red-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 109834<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Merville des March&#x000e9;s, collected in 1935 from France, red-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 129026<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">unnamed, collected in 1938 from Ecuador, red-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 129128<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">unnamed, collected in 1938 from Panama, red-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 196297<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">unnamed, collected in 1951 from Nicaragua, red-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 258474<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">unnamed, collected in 1959 from Ecuador, red-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 258478<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">unnamed, collected in 1959 from Peru, red-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic><sup>b</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 390510<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">unnamed, collected in 1974 from Ecuador, red-fruited<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic><sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">TA496</td><td align="left">from S. Tanksley, Cornell Univ., developed in 1990s from E6203 x Vendor-<italic>Tm-2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>, red-fruited</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Germplasm sources of sequenced alleles in wild and cultivated tomato accessions.</p><p><sup>a</sup> For complete references tracing history of these germplasm sources used for introgression breeding see 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>].</p><p><sup>b</sup> Sequences published in 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>].</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>Markers and <italic>in silico</italic> mapping</title><p>For the 47 markers used in this study (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S1), nucleotide primers for PCR and sequencing were originally designed against <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> sequences except for the Conserved Ortholog Set II (COSII or C2) and unigene (U) markers, which were designed against Euasterids 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Molecular markers have shown good success rates of transferability among distantly related wild tomato species such as <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>S. pennellii</italic> (for examples see 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]). In the current study, some primer pairs did not amplify or give clean or homologous reads in every wild tomato sample. The COSII and U markers did not outperform the other markers in terms of successfully generating high quality sequence data because most of them contained introns, which sometimes carried small indels in a heterozyogus condition. Such heterozygous indels were major contributors to poor quality reads and hence missing data.</p><p>In our current germplasm panel (Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> had no missing markers; sequences were available for at least two of the four green-fruited taxa for the final set of 47 markers. <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> LA1537, <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> G32592, <italic>S. arcanum</italic>, <italic>S. pennellii</italic> and <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> gave data for 32, 42, 40, 35 and 38 markers, respectively. The latter two species are usually self-incompatible (SI) and carried greater numbers of polymorphic markers within accessions than the inbred accessions of <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> and <italic>S. arcanum</italic> that were sampled. Mean SNP frequency across the polymorphic markers was 0.0127 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17) for <italic>S. habrochaites</italic>, 0.0082 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17) for <italic>S. pennellii</italic>, 0.0126 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5) for <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> LA1537, 0.0058 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2) for <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> G32592 and 0.0078 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7) for Peru Wild. TA496, Tomate and <italic>S. arcanum</italic> had no polymorphic sites in any of the markers.</p><p><italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> showed unusually high polymorphism of 0.0055 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;17) relative to the other self-compatible taxa. As one explanation, this accession was categorized as an admixture population in a simple sequence repeat (SSR) genotyping study of <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> population structure 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], so naturally represents two dissimilar <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> genomes. Because the seed source traces back to Vaughan Seed Co. in USA and Horticultural Experiment Station, Ontario, Canada 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], another possibility is that <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> was incorporated into its pedigree by one of those entities. This may be evidenced by comparing the previously estimated <italic>D</italic>, number of mutations per kb, 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] between the two species 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] which was approximately four-fold greater than our estimate reported below.</p><p>The majority of markers were mapped with high confidence to a single map location within the genome (Figure 
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S1). This is the first report in which a whole-genome sequence 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] and web based tools were available with which to do this for the expressed sequence tag (EST) -based markers 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Accordingly, 12 of the EST-based markers were newly mapped and markers 437_2, 2189_1 and 2819_5 were revised with respect to previously predicted chromosomal location based on identities to restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) markers 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. All chromosomes were represented by the 47 markers; numbers of markers per chromosome ranged from one on chromosome 12 to eight on chromosome 6. Small gaps were observed in the alignments but close examination revealed that these were in masked regions rich in runs of poly A or poly T. Only marker 1675_1 did not initially provide any hits. A lowered stringency of 1 x 10<sup>-30</sup> subsequently found the probable position.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Chromosomal map locations of 47 markers sequenced in this study.</bold> Nine markers with dashed outlines showed cryptic introgressions. Also shown on the map (color) are documented introgressions used in tomato breeding that were mentioned in this report, <italic>S. habrochaites</italic>: blue, <italic>S, lycopersicum</italic> Peru Wild: red, <italic>S. peruvianum</italic>: purple, <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>: orange, <italic>S. pennellii</italic>: green.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-12-133-1"/></fig><p>Four markers had two BLASTN hits each. These were 1260_2 for two tightly linked (2,849 nt apart) sequences on chromosome 6, 2325_3 on chromosomes 1 and 3, 2582_1 on chromosomes 4 and 5, and 2819_5 for two linked (14,114 nt apart) regions on chromosome 6. A check of the primer regions found multiple mismatches in predicted primer binding sites of the secondary hit for three of the markers; these were assumed to have amplified as single-copy. For marker 2819_5 the forward primer had a single mismatch and the reverse had no mismatches. The predicted amplicon in the mismatch region was 86% identical to the reference TA496 sequence. When the mismatch sequence was included in MEGA cluster analysis, it separated from all other (wild and cultivated) alleles with 87% bootstrap support, and the mean <italic>D</italic> among sequences increased 8-fold (<italic>D</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.5 for <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;10 alleles versus <italic>D</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;12 for <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;11 alleles). Therefore, it is unlikely that this paralog amplified and confounded the results. All markers had previously been screened in our lab for amplification of single bands and highly homozygous sequences within <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Results of <italic>in silico</italic> mapping confirmed that this set of markers provides robust results in sampling single-copy <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> genes. All sequences were deposited into the European Molecular Biology Laboratory (EMBL), European Nucleotide Archive (ENA) data base as accession numbers HE977919-HE978211.</p></sec><sec><title>Clustering patterns and divergence estimates among taxa</title><p>PI 99782 Tomate was chosen for the current study to represent a &#x02018;pre-introgression breeding&#x02019; genotype. It bears small, slightly ribbed and unimproved fruit with scarring and cracking (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ars-grin.gov/cgi-bin/npgs/acc/display.pl?1127604">http://www.ars-grin.gov/cgi-bin/npgs/acc/display.pl?1127604</ext-link>) and was homozygous for the common <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> haplotype at 48 of 50 markers for which it had been sequenced 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. For 38 of the markers there was high bootstrap support for the red-fruited clade that consisted of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> including Tomate and <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> alleles (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S2). Bootstrap values ranged from 54% to 100% (mean &#x000b1; standard error&#x02009;=&#x02009;86.8 &#x000b1; 2.34%). These bootstrap values subtracted from 100% can be interpreted as estimates of the probability of Type I error, i.e., falsely accepting a cluster that is not signified by the data (see 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>] for discussion).</p><p>Results underscored the close relationship of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> to <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> because their alleles were frequently identical or highly similar. The placement of green-fruited species with respect to the red-fruited clade and each other varied among loci. This can result from incomplete lineage sorting or introgression 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. An example was the placement of <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> near <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> for marker TG11 (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1); this example was also reported by Nesbitt and Tanksley 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>].</p><p>Of the nine markers that did not support the red-fruited clade, seven had previously been hypothesized as carrying introgressions (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S2). These are discussed below. The other two markers, 1287_1 and 2280_1, showed patterns that contained <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> within the red-fruited clade (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1) seemingly due to lack of resolution. At marker 1287_1 <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> haplotypes were only one or two mutational steps from Tomate. These mutations were not shared with any other taxa. At marker 2280_1 only four unique haplotypes were observed. These were <italic>S. habrochaites</italic><italic>S. pennellii</italic><italic>S. arcanum</italic> and {TA496, Tomate, <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>, Peru Wild, G32592, LA1537}. For the 38 markers that supported the red-fruited clade, accepted taxonomic relationships among tomato species were generally supported 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>].</p><p>Divergence estimates (<italic>D</italic>) among loci are associated with a high variance over evolutionary time due to differences in mutation and recombination rates, selective constraints, and influences of various factors such as random sampling of gametes and demography. Average <italic>D</italic> ranged from 5 for marker 4301_3 to 52 mutations per kb for marker C2_At1g44575 (mean &#x000b1; standard error&#x02009;=&#x02009;16.5 &#x000b1; 1.29). At the aggregate scale the mean <italic>D</italic> &#x000b1; standard error from PI 99782 Tomate was as follows: TA496 <italic>D</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.001 &#x000b1; 0.0005, Peru Wild <italic>D</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002 &#x000b1; 0.0006, <italic>S. pimpinellifolium D</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002 &#x000b1; 0.0004, <italic>S. arcanum D</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.020 &#x000b1; 0.0022, <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> LA1537 <italic>D</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.020 &#x000b1; 0.0025, <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> G32592 <italic>D</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.022 &#x000b1; 0.0024, <italic>S. habrochaites D</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.021 &#x000b1; 0.0024 and <italic>S. pennellii D</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.022 &#x000b1; 0.033.</p><p>The lack of precise resolution in distinguishing taxa by clustering, or by average divergence from Tomate in the case of the green-fruited taxa was a function of shared polymorphisms in many instances, e.g., at 24 markers at least one single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) within a species was also segregating between other species pairs. This has been observed in other studies of crop species and their closely related wild relatives (
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] and references therein). In addition, random sampling contributed to low resolution, e.g., <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> haplotypes appeared to be derived from Tomate at marker 1287_1 based on a small number of noninformative SNPs.</p></sec><sec><title>Evidence for introgression</title><p>In previous studies we reported nine markers (Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) with highly diverged alleles within <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and hypothesized that this was due to introgression from wild species. These were 220_1, 437_2, 2325_3, 2534_1R (redesigned into 2534_1b), 2486_1 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], 2819_5, C2_At1g73180 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], U146140 and C2_At1g44575 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Of the 47 markers in the current study, seven of these nine showed patterns in cladograms that did not cluster together members of the red-fruited clade (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1). Hybridization networks (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1), descriptive information of the accessions, map positions of markers, and species origins of documented introgressed disease resistance alleles (e.g. 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]) were used as total evidence to categorize the divergent markers into putative linkage drag during introgression breeding versus natural out crossing with <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> (Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). This categorization did not constitute proof of natural hybridization versus introgression breeding. However, it was a useful concept from which to synthesize independent lines of evidence and can serve as a basis for future hypothesis testing of the two scenarios.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Tomato markers tested for cryptic introgression</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Marker</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>SGN gene model, predicted protein</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Chromosome location (MB)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Divergent line or accession</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Genetic-distance based clustering results</bold><sup>a</sup></th><th align="left"><bold>Observations</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td colspan="6" align="left" valign="bottom">Introgression from crop improvement<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">220_1<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Solyc09g014280, hydroxycinnamoyl transferase<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">ch09, 5.77<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">TA496<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">TA496 intermediate between LA1537 and <italic>S. pennelli</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Major disease resistance genes on ch09 include:<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ve2</italic>, 0.05 MB, (11.002 cM<sup>b</sup>), from Peru Wild<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">2486_1<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Solyc09g014350, glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase 6<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">ch09, 5.90<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">TA496<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">low bootstrap values overall except {TA496, LA1537}<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ve1</italic>, 0.06 MB, (11.002 cM), from Peru Wild<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">2534_1b<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Solyc09g018790, succinic semialdehyde reductase isofom1<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">ch09, 17.00<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">TA496<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">TA496 clustered with two <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> accessions<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Cm9.1</italic>, (4.0 &#x02013; 24.0 cM), from <italic>S. peruvianum</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Frl</italic>, (27.0 &#x02013; 37.0 cM), from <italic>S. peruvianum</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">437_2<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">Solyc09g061440, uncharacterized protein<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">ch09, 54.71<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">TA496<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">TA496 intermediate between {<italic>S. peruvianum</italic>, <italic>S. arcanum</italic>, Peru Wild, <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>, Tomate} and {<italic>S. pennellii</italic>, <italic>S. habrochaites</italic>}<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Tm2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>, 13.62 MB, (32.002 cM), from <italic>S. peruvianum</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Sw-5</italic>, 67.30 MB, (78.001 cM), from <italic>S. peruvianum</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ph-3</italic>, 66.71 &#x02013; 66.78 MB, (63.0 &#x02013; 78.0 cM), from <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" align="left" valign="bottom">Introgression from natural hybridization with <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">2325_3<sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Solyc01g073640, alcohol dehydrogenase-3<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">ch01, 70.26<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">TA496<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">red-fruited clade was supported<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">PI 258478 was collected from Peru in 1959, highly variable, fasciated fruit.<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 258478<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">C2_At1g44575<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">Solyc06g060340, chloroplast photosystem II-associated protein<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">ch06, 34.71<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">PI 258478<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="bottom">red-fruited clade was supported<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Introgressions on ch06 include:<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Cyc-B</italic>, 42.29 MB, (106 cM), from <italic>S. habrochaites</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">2819_5<sup>c</sup><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Solyc06g082670, ribosomal protein L10<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ch06, 44.70<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 258478<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">red-fruited clade was split into {Peru Wild-1, Tomate, TA496} and {Peru Wild-2, <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>, PI 258478}<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">U146140<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Solyc06g083360, DNA-directed RNA polymerase II subunit<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">ch06, 45.08<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 109834<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">red-fruited clade was split into {PI 109834, <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>} and {TA496, Peru Wild, Tomate}<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 109834 Merville des March&#x000e9;s was collected from France in 1935.<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">C2_At1g73180<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">Solyc08g014060, eukaryotic translation initiation factor 3 subunit 9-like protein<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">ch08, 3.57<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 129026<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">{PI 196297, PI 390510} were divergent from other members of red-fruited clade<hr/></td><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom">PI 196297 was collected in Nicaragua in 1951, fasciated fruit, reported as introgressed by Rick 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]; carries same allele as PI 129026 (from Ecuador, 1938, fasciated fruit), PI 129128 (from Panama, 1938, fasciated fruit), PI 258474 (from Ecuador, 1959, fasciated fruit). PI 390510 was collected in Ecuador in 1974, described as a wild cherry tomato.<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 129128<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 196297<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">PI 258474<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">PI 390510</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Nine tomato markers previously identified as carrying highly divergent alleles within <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>.</p><p><sup>a</sup> (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1).</p><p><sup>b</sup> Genetic linkage map positions from 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] or 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>].</p><p><sup>c</sup> Sequence mapped to two locations, see Results and discussion.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Linkage drag was inferred for at least three of the four markers at which TA496 carried an allele that was highly divergent from all other members of the red-fruited clade. All four mapped to chromosome 9 and spanned from 5.77&#x02009;MB to 54.71&#x02009;MB (Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Introgressed disease resistance loci documented on chromosome 9 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>] include <italic>Ve1</italic> (0.06&#x02009;MB) and <italic>Ve2</italic> (0.05&#x02009;MB) both from Peru Wild, <italic>Frl</italic> (physical map position not annotated), <italic>Tm-2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup> (13.62&#x02009;MB) and <italic>Sw-5</italic> (67.30&#x02009;MB), all three from <italic>S. peruvianum</italic>, and <italic>Ph-3</italic> (66.71-66.78&#x02009;MB) from <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> (Figure 
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). LA1537 was the most closely related allele to TA496 in cladograms for the three markers spanning 5.77 &#x02013; 17.00&#x02009;MB on chromosome 9, which encompasses the <italic>Tm-2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup> locus at position 13.62&#x02009;MB. LA1537 is an inbred accession that was derived from PI 128650, the original source of <italic>Tm-2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup> (Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><p>Hybridization networks placed TA496 in various positions for each of the three markers surrounding <italic>Tm-2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>: near the red-fruited alleles with reticulation back towards <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> for marker 2486_1 (Figure 
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>a and Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1), between the red-fruited alleles and <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> with reticulation back towards both for marker 2534_1b (Figure 
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>b and Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1), and within the green-fruited wild species alleles between the two <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> accessions, with no reticulation for marker 220_1 (Figure 
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>c and Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1). The size of the <italic>Tm-2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup> introgressed region was estimated by mapping in segregating F<sub>2</sub> populations 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. RFLP marker TG101 at chromosome 9 location 50.41&#x02009;MB was tightly linked (&#x02264; 1&#x02009;cM) to <italic>Tm-2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>. The chromosomal position of <italic>Tm-2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup> has been characterized as very near the centromere with extremely repressed recombination 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. It is therefore probable that markers 220_1 (5.77&#x02009;MB), 2486_1 (5.90&#x02009;MB) and 2534_1b (17.00&#x02009;MB) were part of the introgressed segment in TA496.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Examples of splits networks at markers with cryptic introgressions in</bold><bold><italic>S. lycopersicum.</italic></bold> Dashed boxes indicate accessions with introgressed alleles (a-d: hybridization networks using marker U146437 as a control, e: parsimony splits network); <bold>a</bold>) TA496 showed reticulation with <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> LA1537 and other green-fruited species, <bold>b</bold>) TA496 showed reticulation with red-fruited and green-fruited species, <bold>c</bold>) TA496 nested within green-fruited species, <bold>d</bold>) Merville des March&#x000e9;s PI 109834 was closely related to <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>, which showed reticulation to Tomate PI 99782, <bold>e</bold>) parsimony splits network used only conservative, global signal within the marker to illustrate the hybrid origin of Merville des March&#x000e9;s PI 109834.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-12-133-2"/></fig><p>The TA496 allele at marker 437_2 (54.71&#x02009;MB) was not as definitively related to <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> and its origin was more difficult to interpret. The cladogram placed TA496 in an intermediate position between two clades, namely, {<italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>, Tomate, <italic>S. arcanum</italic>, Peru Wild, <italic>S. peruvianum</italic>} versus {<italic>S. habrochaites</italic><italic>S. pennellii</italic>} (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1). The hybridization network showed reticulation with <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> and the red-fruited alleles (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1). Several genes commonly found in tomato varieties have originated from <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> (<italic>Cf-4</italic><italic>Tm-1</italic><italic>Ol-1</italic><italic>Cyc-B</italic> and <italic>Del</italic>) or <italic>S. pennellii</italic> (<italic>I</italic><italic>1</italic> and <italic>I</italic><italic>3</italic>) but none of these map to chromosome 9 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. The chromosome 9 introgressions listed in Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> were judged to be commonly used in cultivars based on an informal survey of descriptions from online seed catalogs (unpublished observations) as well as comprehensive reviews of tomato breeding (e.g. 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]).</p><p>Linkage drag of 437_2 in TA496 with <italic>Ph-3</italic> (66.71&#x02009;MB) or <italic>Sw-5</italic> (67.30) was rejected because they originated from <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> and <italic>S. peruvianum</italic>, respectively. Based on a BLASTN search of TA496 marker 437_2 against the Solanaceae PlantGDB-assembled Unique Transcipts (PUTs) in the Solanaceae Genomics Resource database (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://solanaceae.plantbiology.msu.edu/">http://solanaceae.plantbiology.msu.edu/</ext-link>), TA496 and <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> shared a sympleisiomorphy at nucleotide position 46 that was absent from all other alleles that we resequenced. This provided tentative but inconclusive evidence of a direct relationship between the introgression and <italic>S. habrochaites</italic>. As alternative evidence, FM6203, a progenitor of TA496, purportedly carries <italic>Asc</italic> resistance (pers comm. S. Loewen, University of Guelph, 2005) for which <italic>S. pennellii</italic> has served as one of the original sources on chromosome 3 in tomato 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>].</p><p>The remaining five markers with divergent alleles showed patterns consistent with introgression from <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> in natural populations. At four markers (2325_3, C2_At1g44575, 2819_5 and U146140) the divergent alleles were more closely related to red-fruited rather than green-fruited taxa with bootstrap values ranging from 82% &#x02013; 100% (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S2), although markers 2819_5 and U146140 did not support monophyly of red-fruited alleles (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1). Hybridization networks showed red-fruited species alleles to be distinct from green-fruited species alleles for 2325_3 and C2_At1g44575, while 2819_5 and U146140 showed connections between red-fruited and green-fruited species (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1). Marker U146140 nicely illustrated the <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> x <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> hybrid origin of Merville des March&#x000e9;s PI 109834 (Figures&#x02009;
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>d
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>e). Marker C2_At1g73180 showed an unusual pattern in that PI 196297 (and three additional accessions with the identical allele, Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) and PI 390510 were divergent from all other alleles in the cluster analysis with 99% bootstrap support (Figure 
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>a and Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>: Figure S1). This suggested a potential paralog. However, no heterozygotes were observed, the marker did not map to more than one genomic location, and COSII markers were designed to amplify highly conserved single copy genes 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>].</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Extreme divergence of marker C2_At1g73180.</bold><bold>a</bold>) Clustering at marker C2_At1g73180 showed the distinctiveness of PI 129026 and PI 196297 with 99% bootstrap support, <bold>b</bold>) the splits network showed a combination of introgression of PI 129026 and PI 196297 (among others, see Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) with <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> and retention of ancient polymorphisms that reticulated down to the root; the latter supported genetic hitchhiking and rejection of selective neutrality.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2229-12-133-3"/></fig><p>The divergent C2_At1g73180 alleles were unlikely to have originated from a green-fruited species because chromosome 8 does not carry any introgressed disease resistance alleles 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. The hybridization network depicted PI 196297 and PI 390510 as branching from <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>, with complex reticulations at the base of the red-fruited clade that extended through the green-fruited taxa, down to <italic>S. pennellii</italic> at the root (Figure 
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>b). Among the seven unique polymorphisms carried by PI 196297 and PI 390510, two were non-conservative amino acid substitutions, two were synonymous and three were intronic. One possibility is that selection at or near this locus has caused ancient polymorphism to have been retained. A significant HKA test 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.36, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.007) strengthened this interpretation. Therefore, diversity at this marker showed patterns of both natural selection and introgression.</p><p>Additional evidence that these five markers represent <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> introgressions in natural populations includes geographical origins of three accessions from Ecuador where the two species hybridize extensively 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>], original collection of three accessions dating to 1935 and 1938 (likely precluding the influence of direct introgression breeding), the primitive fruit phenotype of fasciation (four accessions) or wild cherry tomato (one accession, n.b., cherry tomato was described as an admixture of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> by 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]), and previously reported introgression of PI 196297 with <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> by Rick 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. In estimates of population structure 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>] PI 109834, PI 129128, PI 258474 and PI 258478 all showed high probability of membership in the second of two populations inferred for <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> genotypes, consistent with interspecific hybridization 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>It was useful to delineate cryptic introgression within <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> into linkage drag stemming from breeding versus natural hybridization with <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>, although this categorization was not definitive and should be subjected to further scrutiny. Sequences of the wild tomato species markers in the context of their physical map locations have strengthened our previous interpretations of detection of introgressed alleles in domesticated tomato 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Genomic tools for fine resolution of introgressed regions in crop species are increasingly available. The strengths and weaknesses of comparative genotyping to verify introgression have been illustrated here using <italic>Solanum</italic> section <italic>Lycopersicon</italic> taxa.</p><p>In the current study the implications of linkage drag of introgressed alleles on phenotype remain unknown. At least one marker (2534_1b) codes for an enzyme involved in fruit ripening (Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In cultivars or breeding lines it will be more useful to estimate the proportion of a genome that harbors linkage drag. This should be feasible for TA496 using bioinformatics given the vast amount of public EST sequence data available for this particular line and wild tomato species (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://solgenomics.net/tools/blast/dbinfo.pl">http://solgenomics.net/tools/blast/dbinfo.pl</ext-link> as of June 2012 reported 323,465 Lycopersicon mRNAs). Importantly, an understanding of linkage drag will help to distinguish it from selection during crop improvement. Four of six markers that previously rejected neutrality tests (437_2, 2486_1, 2534_1b and 2819_5) (Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> in 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]) were found to be introgressed rather than selected. It is anticipated that next-generation sequencing will be utilized to more rapidly eliminate linkage drag in crops 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>].</p><p>Natural hybrids will carry high proportions of wild alleles making them somewhat easy to detect using large numbers of molecular markers. The intrinsic value of naturally introgressed germplasm was recognized in common bean (<italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>) as a source of new alleles for traits such as disease resistance 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. In <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, if horticultural effects of introgression are subtle then accessions such as Merville des March&#x000e9;s may be prime sources to screen for new alleles. A search of the literature for accessions that were part of the current study (Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) found that PI 129128 showed high lycopene content, similar to lines containing pigment mutations such as <italic>og</italic><sup><italic>c</italic></sup><italic>, hp, and dg</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>].</p><p>Finally, it is worth noting that Rick 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] reported the potential of natural hybridization of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> with <italic>Solanum chilense</italic><italic>S. habrochaites</italic> (formerly <italic>Lycopersicon hirsutum</italic> f. <italic>glabratum</italic>), and <italic>Lycopersicon peruvianum</italic> (now revised into four species, 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]) in regions of Chile, Ecuador and Peru where sympatric populations grow in close contact, although he found no evidence of this based on phenotypes and severe postzygotic barriers are well known. Genotyping of populations sampled from these regions would provide evidence to reexamine whether introgression from these wild tomato species into <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> has played a role in the crop&#x02019;s evolutionary history.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Plant material</title><p>Marker genotypes used in this study were previously reported for <italic>Solanum arcanum</italic> and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] or were newly collected from each of five wild tomato accessions and one weedy <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> accession Peru Wild. The specific accessions of <italic>S. habrochaites</italic><italic>S. pennellii</italic><italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> and Peru Wild have served historically as sources of important disease resistance alleles for tomato cultivars (Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The two <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> accessions were chosen because they were known to be inbred and predicted to be highly homozygous. One of these, <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> LA1537, originated from accession PI 128650 which was the original source of <italic>Tm-2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]. Two plants per each of the six accessions were sampled as seedlings for genomic DNA isolation and sequencing of markers. Three accessions included in this study had previously published sequences for the markers 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] (Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). These were &#x02212; a breeding line with documented multiple introgressions in its pedigree including <italic>Tm-2</italic><sup><italic>a</italic></sup> (TA496) 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>], an accession that predated tomato introgression breeding (Tomate, PI 99782), and <italic>S. arcanum</italic> (G 32591) a naturally self-fertilizing accession formerly classified as <italic>Lycopersicon peruvianum</italic>. For a few markers, published sequences from additional <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> accessions (PI 109834 Merville des March&#x000e9;s, PI 129026, PI 129128, PI 196297, PI 258474, PI 258478, PI 390510, Table 
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) were included in analyses because they were previously reported as carrying highly divergent alleles, i.e. putative introgressions, at those loci 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>DNA sequences</title><p>Genomic DNA extraction from seedlings, PCR amplification and two-pass sequencing were as described in Labate et al. 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Initially, 49 of 50 markers from Labate et al. 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] were sequenced. These represent random loci including expressed genes (expressed sequence tag, EST-based), highly conserved genes (COSII and U) and arbitrary loci. Marker 1523_4 was excluded without testing because it tended to give poor quality sequence within <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>. Markers 175_1 and 1909_2 were dropped during this study because they did not consistently amplify <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> homologs in wild tomato species, leaving 47 markers representing approximately 24&#x02009;kb in total (Additional file 
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>: Table S1). Software packages phred, phrap and Consed 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] and Staden 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>] were used for assembly and base calling of reads. Pregap4 (ver. 1.5) of the Staden package was configured to apply a base-calling algorithm &#x0201c;Estimate Base Accuracies&#x0201c; that is different from phred in order to independently verify the data. Sequence data were trimmed to remove primer binding sites and low quality ends (phred&#x0003c;40), and manually aligned in BioEdit 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. All SNPs and heterozygous positions were confirmed by visual examination of trace files by two people. If the two plants from one accession had different sequences they were kept distinct; if they were identical they were treated as a single representative sequence of that accession. Heterozygous sites were manually edited to use IUPAC nucleotide ambiguity codes. GeneSeqer (ver. 08 Oct. 2008) 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>] was used to compare exon and intron prediction for all markers against previous annotations 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>].</p><p>All sequences were mapped using BLASTN 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>] against tomato whole genome shotgun chromosomes (SL2.40) database with an e-value threshold of 1 x 10<sup>-40</sup> on the SGN web site 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]. Gene models within markers and adjacent regions were identified in the SGN genome browser using ITAG2.3 Release: genomic annotations. For marker 437_2, tomato sequences were compared to transcribed sequences from an evolutionary out group (potato, <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic>) by BLASTN searches of the Solanaceae Genomics Resource database at Michigan State University (
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://solanaceae.plantbiology.msu.edu/">http://solanaceae.plantbiology.msu.edu/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>For each of the 47 markers, relationships among genotypes (also referred to as taxa) were first examined by applying the neighbor-joining (NJ) clustering method 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>] as implemented in MEGA 4.0.2 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>] with 1,000 bootstrap replicates. Genetic distance and average evolutionary divergence (<italic>D</italic>) were estimated using the Jukes-Cantor method 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]; positions with alignment gaps or missing data were eliminated in pairwise sequence comparisons. For each of 11 markers that did not support the red-fruited clade based on MEGA results, consensus trees were generated by Phylip ver. 3.69 using Seqboot to produce 100 datasets by bootstrap resampling, Dnadist to estimate genetic distances using the Jukes-Cantor method, Neighbor to produce unrooted NJ trees and Consense to compute a consensus tree by the majority-rule consensus tree method 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>]. SplitsTree4 ver. 4.12.3 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>] was used to create splits networks from DNA sequences or NJ trees 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>]. Hybridization splits networks were created using the consensus tree of marker U146437 as a control that highly supported the red-fruited clade (99%) plus the consensus tree of the marker being tested for an introgression, with balanced sets of taxa (same taxa in each tree). A neutrality test 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] of marker C2_At1g73180 was carried out in DnaSP v. 5.10 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>] using marker TG11 as a control and <italic>S. arcanum</italic> as the out group.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>ARS, Agricultural research service; COSII, Conserved Ortholog Set II; EMBL, European Molecular Biology Laboratory; ENA, European Nucleotide Archive; EST, Expressed sequence tag; NJ, Neighbor joining; GM, Genetically modified; PGRU, Plant Genetic Resources Unit; PUT, PlantGDB-assembled Unique Transcipts; QTL, Quantitative trait loci; RFLP, Restriction fragment length polymorphism; SGN, Sol genomics network; SI, Self-incompatible; SNP, Single nucleotide polymorphism; U, Unigene; USDA, United States Department of Agriculture.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>JAL and LDR conceived and designed the study. JAL acquired, analyzed and interpreted the data, and drafted the manuscript. LDR gave final approval of the version to be published. Both authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>Table S1.</bold>Virtual mapping of 47 sequence-based markers. BLASTN results of 47 markers against tomato whole genome shotgun chromosomes from version 2.40 of the WUR assembly, current as of 10 Jan, 2012. <bold>Table S2.</bold>Evolutionary relationships among taxa at 47 markers. Bootstrap support and evolutionary divergence of 47 tomato markers sequenced in wild and cultivated tomato accessions. Marker names in bold were previously hypothesized as carrying introgressions.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-12-133-S1.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>Clustering and network analyses of tomato genotypes.</bold> Neighbor joining trees for 47 markers and hybridization networks for nine markers sampled from wild and cultivated tomato.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2229-12-133-S2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank S. Sheffer and P. Kisly for excellent technical support and E. Cobb for stimulating discussions. This work was funded by CRIS project 1910-21000-019-00D. USDA is an equal opportunity provider and employer.</p><p>The use of trade, firm, or corporation names in this publication is for the information and convenience of the reader. Such use does not constitute an official endorsement or approval by the United States Department of Agriculture or the Agricultural Research Service of any product or service to the exclusion of others that may be suitable.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekel-Bobrov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallender</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lahn</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><article-title>Evidence that the adaptive allele of the brain size gene microcephalin introgressed into Homo sapiens from an archaic Homo lineage</article-title><source>P Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><issue>48</issue><fpage>18178</fpage><lpage>18183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0606966103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Randi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Detecting hybridization between wild species and their domesticated relatives</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>2008</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2007.03417.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18173502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tosi</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Detwiler</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><article-title>X-chromosomal synapomorphies provide a non-invasive test for introgression among Cercopithecus monkeys</article-title><source>Conserv Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10592-005-9072-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hajjar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>The use of wild relatives in crop improvement: a survey of developments over the last 20&#x02009;years</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2007</year><volume>156</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-007-9363-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dearing</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Muscadine grape breeding</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>1917</year><volume>8</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>424</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bremer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>A cytological investigation of some species and species hybrids within the genus Saccharum</article-title><source>Genetica</source><year>1923</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01489607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Prescott-Allen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Prescott-Allen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><source>The first resource: Wild species in the North American economy</source><year>1986</year><publisher-name>Yale University, New Haven</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baldo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Caramante</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Labate</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><article-title>AlleleCoder: a PERL script for coding codominant polymorphism data for PCA analysis</article-title><source>Plant Genetic Resources: Characterization and Utilization</source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Labate</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheffer</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Balch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><article-title>Diversity and population structure in a geographic sample of tomato accessions</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>51</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1068</fpage><lpage>1079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2010.05.0305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Breeze F</person-group><article-title>Indiana plant diseases, 1920</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science</source><year>1920</year><publisher-name>Fort Wayne Printing Co., Fort Wayne, Indiana</publisher-name><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>208</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Boswell</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><name><surname>Work</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>MacGillivray</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Seaton</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayles</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Friend</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawthorn</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><etal/><source>Descriptions of types of principal American varieties of tomatoes. In: Misc Pub No 160</source><year>1933</year><publisher-name>USDA, Washington, DC</publisher-name><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>206</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Porte</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><source>The Pan American tomato, a new red variety highly resistant to Fusarium wilt</source><year>1941</year><publisher-name>USDA Circ 611, Washington, DC</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chetelat</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><article-title>Utilization of related wild species for tomato improvement</article-title><source>Acta Hort</source><year>1995</year><volume>412</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Improving plant breeding with exotic genetic libraries</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35103589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11733751</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Plant breeders go back to nature</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng0308-269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18305476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Foolad</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><article-title>Genome mapping and molecular breeding of tomato</article-title><source>Int J of Plant Genomics</source><year>2007</year><volume>2007</volume><fpage>64358</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18364989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Haanstra</surname><given-names>JPW</given-names></name><name><surname>Laug&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer-Dekens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnema</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>PJGM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>The Cf-ECP2 gene is linked to, but not part of, the Cf-4/Cf-9 cluster on the short arm of chromosome 1 in tomato</article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>262</volume><issue>4/5</issue><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>845</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10628868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van der Beek</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Verkerk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Mapping strategy for resistance genes in tomato based on RFLPs between cultivars: Cf9 (resistance to Cladosporium fulvum) on chromosome 1</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1992</year><volume>84</volume><issue>1/2</issue><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>112</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganal</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><article-title>Use of isogenic lines and simultaneous probing to identify DNA markers tightly linked to the Tm-2a gene in tomato</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1988</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17246482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Randhawa</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutti</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidwell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><article-title>Rapid and targeted introgression of genes into popular wheat cultivars using marker-assisted background selection</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e5752</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0005752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19484121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullet</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rooney</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Menz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><article-title>The effect of tropical Sorghum conversion and inbred development on genome diversity as revealed by high-resolution genotyping</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>S12</fpage><lpage>S26</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rieseberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Hybridization, introgression, and linkage evolution</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1006340407546</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><article-title>The role of natural hybridization in the derivation of cultivated tomatoes of western South America</article-title><source>Econ Bot</source><year>1958</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02860023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Labate</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><article-title>Tomato SNP discovery by EST mining and resequencing</article-title><source>Mol Breed</source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-005-1911-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Labate</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><article-title>Multilocus sequence data reveal extensive departures from equilibrium in domesticated tomato (Solanum lycopersicum L.)</article-title><source>Heredity</source><year>2009</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hdy.2009.58</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19436327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Labate</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Razdan MK, Mattoo AK</person-group><article-title>Genetic resources of tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum Mill.) and wild relatives</article-title><source>Genetic improvement of Solanaceous crops</source><series>Tomato, Volume 2</series><year>2007</year><publisher-name>Science Publishers, Enfield, NH</publisher-name><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crouzillat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Petiard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><article-title>Combining bioinformatics and phylogenetics to identify large sets of single-copy orthologous genes (COSII) for comparative, evolutionary and systematic studies: A test case in the Euasterid plant clade</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>174</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1407</fpage><lpage>1420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.106.062455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16951058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Labate</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><article-title>EST, COSII, and arbitrary gene markers give similar estimates of nucleotide diversity in cultivated tomato (Solanum lycopersicum L.)</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2009</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-008-0957-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19153710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Hoeven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eannetta</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Identification, analysis, and utilization of conserved ortholog set markers for comparative genomics in higher plants</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1457</fpage><lpage>1467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.010479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12119367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maloof</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><article-title>Sequence diversity in three tomato species: SNPs, markers, and molecular evolution</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biology</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>85</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-9-85</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19575805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Asamizu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuoka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohyama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>An interspecific linkage map of SSR and intronic polymorphism markers in tomato</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2010</year><volume>121</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-010-1344-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20431859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadirvel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Symonds</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Geethanjali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><article-title>Using SSR markers to map genetic diversity and population structure of Solanum pimpinellifolium for development of a core collection</article-title><source>Plant Genetic Resources: Characterization and Utilization</source><year>2012</year></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pitblado</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><article-title>Resistance to bacterial speck (Pseudomonas tomato) in tomato</article-title><source>Acta Hort (ISHS)</source><year>1980</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>382</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Jukes</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantor</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Munro H</person-group><article-title>Evolution of protein molecules</article-title><source>Mammalian protein metabolism</source><year>1969</year><publisher-name>Academic, New York</publisher-name><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>132</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nesbitt</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><article-title>Comparative sequencing in the genus Lycopersicon: Implications for the evolution of fruit size in the domestication of cultivated tomatoes</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2002</year><volume>162</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>The Tomato Genome Consortium</collab><article-title>The tomato genome sequence provides insights into fleshy fruit evolution</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>485</volume><issue>7400</issue><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22660326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><article-title>Applying the bootstrap in phylogeny reconstruction</article-title><source>Stat Sci</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/ss/1063994980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><article-title>Gene flow and species delimitation: a case study of two pine species with overlapping distributions in southeast China</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>2010</year><volume>64</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2342</fpage><lpage>2352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20298431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>An&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Spooner</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><article-title>Do potatoes and tomatoes have a single evolutionary history, and what proportion of the genome supports this history?</article-title><source>BMC Evol Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>191</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-9-191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19664206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zuriaga</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanca</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Classification and phylogenetic relationships in Solanum section Lycopersicon based on AFLP and two nuclear gene sequences</article-title><source>Genet Resour Crop Ev</source><year>2009</year><volume>56</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10722-008-9392-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaut</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Multilocus analysis of nucleotide variation of Oryza sativa and its wild relatives: Severe bottleneck during domestication of rice</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17218640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Domestication and breeding of tomatoes: What have we gained and what can we gain in the future?</article-title><source>Ann Bot</source><year>2007</year><volume>100</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1085</fpage><lpage>1094</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcm150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17717024</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caranta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Saliba-Colombani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Damidaux</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rousselle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Enhancement of tomato genetic resources via molecular markers</article-title><source>Cahiers Agricultures</source><year>2000</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>210</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grube</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Radwanski</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Jahn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Comparative genetics of disease resistance within the Solanaceae</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2000</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>873</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10835406</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ria&#x000f1;o-Pach&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Neigenfind</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Basekow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller-Roeber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kersten</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>GabiPD: the GABI primary database &#x02013; a plant integrative &#x02018;omics&#x02018;database</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><issue>database issue</issue><fpage>D954</fpage><lpage>D959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18812395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mutschler</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><article-title>1987 Linkage maps of the tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum)</article-title><source>TGC Report</source><year>1987</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pillen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Construction of a high-resolution genetic map and YAC-contigs in the tomato Tm-2a region</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>233</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van der Biezen</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Glagotskaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Overduin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nijkamp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hille</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Inheritance and genetic mapping of resistance to Alternaria alternata f. sp. lycopersici in Lycopersicon pennellii</article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1995</year><volume>247</volume><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00293147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7770053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreitman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguad&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>A test of neutral molecular evolution based on nucleotide data</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1987</year><volume>116</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3110004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nakazato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Housworth</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><article-title>Spatial genetics of wild tomato species reveals roles of the Andean geography on demographic history</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2011</year><volume>98</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.1000272</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21613087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustamante</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><article-title>An MCMC approach for joint inference of population structure and inbreeding rates from multilocus genotype data</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2007</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>1635</fpage><lpage>1651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.107.072371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berkman</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenc</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Next-generation sequencing applications for wheat crop improvement</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2012</year><volume>99</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3732/ajb.1100309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22268223</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>FMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Beebe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohme</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Redden</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Basford</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><article-title>Using molecular markers to assess the effect of introgression on quantitative attributes of common bean in the Andean gene pool</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>108</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-003-1437-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14657984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledesma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsou</surname><given-names>SCS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><article-title>Variation for antioxidant activity and antioxidants in tomato</article-title><source>J Am Soc Hortic Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>129</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>704</fpage><lpage>711</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peralta</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Spooner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>The taxonomy of tomatoes: a revision of wild tomatoes (Solanum section Lycopersicon) and their outgroup relatives (Solanum sections Juglandifolium and Lycopersicoides)</article-title><source>Syst Bot Mngr</source><year>2008</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>186</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><article-title>Resistance at the Tm-2 locus in the tomato to tomato mosaic virus</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>1980</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00037266</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernachi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck-Bunn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmatty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Inai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Petiard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sayama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhlig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Yield and quality evaluations on a pair of processing tomato lines nearly isogenic for the Tm-2a gene for resistance to the tobacco mosaic virus</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>1998</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1018320232663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Base-calling of automated sequencer traces using phred. II. Error probabilities</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendl</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Base-calling of automated sequencer traces using phred. I. Accuracy assessment</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Staden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>The Staden sequence analysis package</article-title><source>Mol Biotechnol</source><year>1996</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02900361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8837029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><article-title>BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT</article-title><source>Nucl Acids Symp Ser</source><year>1999</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schlueter</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Brendel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>GeneSeqer@ PlantGDB: Gene structure prediction in plant genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>31</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>3597</fpage><lpage>3600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkg533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12824374</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>3402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.17.3389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bombarely</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Menda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tecle</surname><given-names>IY</given-names></name><name><surname>Buels</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Strickler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer-York</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pujar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gosselin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><article-title>The Sol Genomics Network (solgenomics.net): growing tomatoes using Perl</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D1149</fpage><lpage>D1155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20935049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>The neighbor-joining method: A new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1987</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3447015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1596</fpage><lpage>1599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msm092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>PHYLIP -- Phylogeny Inference Package (Version 3.2)</article-title><source>Cladistics</source><year>1989</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>166</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huson</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Application of phylogenetic networks in evolutionary studies</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16221896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Huson</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Klopper</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Miyano JM S, Kasif S, Istrail S, Pevzner P, Waterman M</person-group><article-title>Reconstruction of reticulate networks from gene trees</article-title><source>Research in computational biology, Lecture notes in computer science</source><year>2005</year><publisher-name>Springer, Berlin</publisher-name><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>249</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Librado</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>DnaSP v5: A software for comprehensive analysis of DNA polymorphism data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>1452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19346325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>