<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3134339</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/err055</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Genetic dissection of vitamin E biosynthesis in tomato</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>Juliana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quadrana</surname><given-names>Leandro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>As&#x000ed;s</surname><given-names>Ram&#x000f3;n</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Setta</surname><given-names>Nathalia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Godoy</surname><given-names>Fabiana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berm&#x000fa;dez</surname><given-names>Luisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Otaiza</surname><given-names>Santiago N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Corr&#x000ea;a da Silva</surname><given-names>Junia V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>Alisdair R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Carrari</surname><given-names>Fernando</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>Magdalena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn5">5</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Departamento de Bot&#x000e2;nica-IB-USP, 277, 05508-900, S&#x000e3;o Paulo, SP, Brazil</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Instituto de Biotecnolog&#x000ed;a, Instituto Nacional de Tecnolog&#x000ed;a Agropecuar&#x000ed;a (IB-INTA), and Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas y T&#x000e9;cnicas (CONICET), PO Box 25, B1712WAA Castelar, Argentina (partner group of the Max Planck Institute for Molecular Plant Physiology, Potsdam-Golm, Germany)</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>CIBICI, Facultad de Ciencias Qu&#x000ed;micas Universidad Nacional de C&#x000f3;rdoba, CC 5000, C&#x000f3;rdoba, Argentina</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Max Planck Institute for Molecular Plant Physiology, Wissenschaftspark Golm, Am M&#x000fc;hlenberg 1, Potsdam-Golm, D-14476, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>fcarrari@cnia.inta.gov.ar</email>; E-mail: <email>mmrossi@usp.br</email></corresp><fn id="fn5"><label>5</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>7</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>62</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3781</fpage><lpage>3798</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>07</day><month>2</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2011 The Author(s).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p><license-p>This paper is available online free of all access charges (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html">http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/open_access.html</ext-link> for further details)</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Vegetables are critical for human health as they are a source of multiple vitamins including vitamin E (VTE). In plants, the synthesis of VTE compounds, tocopherol and tocotrienol, derives from precursors of the shikimate and methylerythritol phosphate pathways. Quantitative trait loci (QTL) for &#x003b1;-tocopherol content in ripe fruit have previously been determined in an <italic>Solanum pennellii</italic> tomato introgression line population. In this work, variations of tocopherol isoforms (&#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, &#x003b3;, and &#x003b4;) in ripe fruits of these lines were studied. In parallel all tomato genes structurally associated with VTE biosynthesis were identified and mapped. Previously identified VTE QTL on chromosomes 6 and 9 were confirmed whilst novel ones were identified on chromosomes 7 and 8. Integrated analysis at the metabolic, genetic and genomic levels allowed us to propose 16 candidate loci putatively affecting tocopherol content in tomato. A comparative analysis revealed polymorphisms at nucleotide and amino acid levels between <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>S. pennellii</italic> candidate alleles. Moreover, evolutionary analyses showed the presence of codons evolving under both neutral and positive selection, which may explain the phenotypic differences between species. These data represent an important step in understanding the genetic determinants of VTE natural variation in tomato fruit and as such in the ability to improve the content of this important nutriceutical.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Fruit metabolism</kwd><kwd><italic>Solanum pennellii</italic></kwd><kwd>tocopherol</kwd><kwd>tomato</kwd><kwd>vitamin E</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Vegetables are critical for human health as they are a source of multiple vitamins and other essential compounds. In particular, tomato fruits are an important dietary source of antioxidants for humans due both to the fact that have a high intrinsic content of these compounds and the elevated consumption of this crop by the western population. The main non-enzymatic antioxidants found in tomato fruits are ascorbic acid (VTC), lycopene and carotenoids, phenolics, and vitamin E (VTE) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Abushita <italic>et al.</italic>, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">Frusciante <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Recent studies have reinforced the hypothesis of beneficial effects of VTE on human health, mainly in the prevention of coronary heart disease, breast cancer, and protection against nicotine-induced oxidative stress in the brain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Das <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">Ros 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib97">Zhang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Although its function in plants remains somewhat undefined, several reports link VTE to the protection of pigments, proteins, and polyunsaturated fatty acids of the photosynthetic apparatus against reactive oxygen species (ROS) generated during photosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">Semchuk <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). It has additionally been proposed that VTE interacts with other antioxidant mechanisms in order to maintain cellular redox homeostasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">Foyer and Noctor, 2005</xref>).</p><p>The synthesis of VTE occurs in photosynthetic organisms and its major constituents are a group of amphipathic molecules containing a polar chromanol head group derived from homogentisate and a polyprenyl lipophilic side chain, products of the shikimate (SK) and methylerythritol phosphate (MEP) pathways, respectively. VTE compounds, collectively termed tocochromanols, can be classified into two groups on the basis of the degree of saturation of their hydrophilic tails. Tocopherols, which are the most abundant in plants, have saturated tails derived from phytyl 2P, whereas tocotrienols have an unsaturated tail derived from geranylgeranyl 2P. The VTE biosynthesis pathway proceeding from the reduction of hydroxyphenylpyruvate to homogentisate is considered the &#x02018;VTE core pathway&#x02019; and comprises seven enzymes: 4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate dioxygenase (HPPD, EC 1.13.11.27), homogentisic acid geranylgeranyl transferase (HGGT/HST, EC 2.5.1.-), homogentisate phytyl transferase (VTE2, EC 2.5.1.-), dimethyl-phytylquinol methyl transferase (VTE3, EC 2.1.1.-), tocopherol cyclase (VTE1, EC 5.3.-.-), &#x003b3;-tocopherol C-methyl transferase (VTE4, EC 2.1.1.95), and phytol kinase (VTE5, EC 2.7.-.-). There are four naturally occurring forms of tocopherols and tocotrienols (&#x003b1;, &#x003b2;, &#x003b3;, and &#x003b4;), which differ in the position and number of methyl groups on the chromanol ring (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">Munn&#x000e9;-Bosch and Alegre, 2002</xref>). Although all VTE isoforms are potent antioxidants <italic>in vitro</italic>, &#x003b1;-tocopherol is the most active in terms of vitamin activity, partly because it is retained in the human body in preference to other tocopherols and tocotrienols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88">Traber and Sies, 1996</xref>). In plants, tocochromanol has been found exclusively in plastids. Since it has not been proved thus far that any isoform can be transported within the plant, and the enzymes of the core pathway have been found in plastids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">Sun <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>), it is assumed that the biosynthesis also occurs in this compartment.</p><p>Although the VTE biosynthetic pathway was elucidated in 1979 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">Soll and Schultz, 1979</xref>), the identification of the genes involved is much more recent. In the last decade, via the use of genetic and genomics-based methods, the genes encoding the enzymes for most of the steps of the VTE core biosynthesis pathway have been identified and cloned. However, as yet, this is confined to the model organisms <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Synechocystis</italic> sp. PCC6803 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Indeed, the characterization of VTE mutants and transgenic lines has provided considerable insight into the regulatory network of tocochromanol biosynthesis (for review see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">M&#x000e8;ne-Saffran&#x000e9; and DellaPenna, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Falk and Munn&#x000e9;-Bosch, 2010</xref>). These combined studies have additionally suggested roles for VTE compounds beyond their antioxidant function including their participation in diverse physiological processes including germination, photoassimilate partitioning, growth, leaf senescence, and plant responses to abiotic stress (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Falk and Munn&#x000e9;-Bosch, 2010</xref>). Moreover, several studies have demonstrated a close interaction between VTE and other metabolic pathways. Tomato fruits overexpressing phytoene synthase (PSY), a key enzyme in carotenoid biosynthesis, displayed increased levels of tocopherol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">Fraser <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Moreover, tocochromanol content is additionally affected when the post-chorismate pathway is manipulated. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> transgenic plants overexpressing the bacterial bi-functional chorismate mutase (CM)/prephenate dehydratase (PDT), displayed significantly higher levels of phenylalanine, as well as &#x003b3;-tocopherol and &#x003b3;-tocotrienol, besides other secondary metabolites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib89">Tzin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Plant tocochromanol biosynthesis is furthermore subjected to control by both environmental and endogenous signals. In agreement with this statement, the silencing of the light response factor DE-ETIOLATED1 resulted in tomato fruits with enhanced levels of antioxidants, including carotenoids, flavonoids, and tocopherol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Davuluri <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Enfissi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Cultivated tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) is the most consumed vegetable globally. The fact that its wild relatives display tremendous variation in metabolite content in both leaves and fruits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">Schauer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>), renders wild germplasm an important source for metabolic gene discovery focused on aiding efforts to improve the nutritional and industrial quality of crop species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib96">Zamir, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">Fernie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87">Tohge and Fernie, 2010</xref>). Utilizing this approach, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Schauer <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> reported a detailed metabolite profile of 76 tomato introgression lines (ILs) containing chromosome segments of the wild species <italic>Solanum pennellii</italic> in the genetic background of the cultivated <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> (cv M82; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Eshed and Zamir, 1995</xref>). Following the quantification of 74 metabolites of known chemical structure, they were able to identify 889 quantitative fruit metabolic loci for variations in the content of amino and organic acids, sugars, alcohols, fatty acids, VTC, and VTE. Two of these quantitative trait loci (QTL), explaining variation in the &#x003b1;-tocopherol fruit content, were located on chromosomes 6 and 9. Independent experiments available at the Tomato Functional Genomics Database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">Fei <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ted.bti.cornell.edu/">http://ted.bti.cornell.edu/</ext-link>) have also revealed differences in tocopherol content associated with the exact same genomic regions. However, the mechanisms explaining these variations are currently not understood, partially due to a lack of knowledge of the complete VTE biosynthetic pathway in tomato.</p><p>The aim of the current report is to provide a framework for associating gene sequence with fruit tocopherol content phenotypes by (i) characterizing and mapping all genes involved in the VTE biosynthesis pathway in tomato, (ii) identifying QTL for the content of the vitamers of VTE and their candidate genes, (iii) cloning and sequencing these genes from <italic>S. pennellii</italic>, and (iv) examining evolutionary patterns of candidates genes by comparing orthologues from <italic>S. pennelli</italic>, <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, and <italic>A. thaliana.</italic> The combined results of this study will be discussed in the context of the fundamental understanding of the accumulation of VTE opening further stages for functional analyses.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Plant material</title><p>Tomato seeds from <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> L. (cv M82) and <italic>S. pennellii</italic> introgressed lines were obtained from Tomato Genetic Resource Center (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tgrc.ucdavis.edu">http://tgrc.ucdavis.edu</ext-link>). Tomato plants were grown in 20-l pots under greenhouse conditions: 16/8 h photoperiod, 24&#x000b1;3 &#x000b0;C, 60% humidity, and 140&#x000b1;40 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> incident photo-irradiance. Cloning was carried out from fully expanded source leaves and mature fruits (60 d after flowering). For tocopherol quantification six ripe fruits were taken from six individual plants of ILs 6-1, 6-2, 7-4, 7-4-1, 7-5, 8-2, 8-2-1, 9-1, 9-2-6. Tissue was collected, immediately frozen into liquid nitrogen, and stored at &#x02013;80 &#x000b0;C until use.</p></sec><sec><title>Survey of tocopherol biosynthesis enzymes, genome mapping, and expression analyses</title><p>The VTE pathway presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref> was outlined by combining data reported for enzymatic steps involved in SK, MEP, and VTE biosynthesis available on KEGG (Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/</ext-link>) and related scientific literature. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> loci were obtained from the KEGG database and these sequences were used to perform TBLASTN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Altschul <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>) searches against tomato expressed sequences from the Lycopersicon Combined Build # 3 unigene database housed by the Solanaceae Genomics Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://solgenomic.net">http://solgenomic.net</ext-link>). The criteria used to determine orthology were &#x02265;40% identity at the amino acid level and &#x02265;65% coverage of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> protein. For uncompleted unigenes, the coverage cut-off was set at &#x02265;30%. Based on BLASTN results, all unigene sequences were used as queries to identify the corresponding genomic sequences from the <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> genome assembly&#x02014;version 2.31 (3,230 sequences; 781,381,961 total letters)&#x02014;The International Tomato Genome Sequencing Project at the Solanaceae Genomics Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://solgenomic.net">http://solgenomic.net</ext-link>). <italic>In silico</italic> prediction of the subcellular localization of tomato unigenes was performed using TargetP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TargetP">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TargetP</ext-link>) and ChloroP program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ChloroP">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ChloroP</ext-link>) based on their deduced amino acid sequences.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>VTE biosysnthesis pathway. The MEP, SK, and tocopherol core pathways are highlighted in red, green, and blue, respectively. Candidate genes of the VTE-related pathways (carotenoid, chlorophyll, tryptophan and folate metabolism, and the SEC14 protein) are not highlighted. Enzymes are named according to their abbreviations in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>. Genes for which wild alleles were cloned, sequenced, and analysed are underlined.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexboterr055f01_3c"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Identification of tomato genes involved in VTE biosynthesis and QTL- associated candidate genes. <italic>A. thaliana</italic> loci used for evolutionary analyses are underlined.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enzyme<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn1">a</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>A. thaliana</italic> locus (no. amino acids)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Curated localization <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn2">b</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tomato unigene<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn3">c</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal peptide<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4">d</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genomic id<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn5">e</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linked marker <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn6">f</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosome position<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn7">g</xref>(cM)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1-Deoxy-D-xylulose-5-P synthase (DXS, EC 2.2.1.7)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">At4g15560 (717)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U567647 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc05941</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1704</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (39 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U316204 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03748</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG523</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (29 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-C-methyl-D-erythritol 4-phosphate synthase (DXR, EC 1.1.1.267)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At5g62790 (477)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U585813</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03701</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At5g23060</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (102.5 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-C-methyl-D-erythritol 4-phosphate cytidylyltransferase (CMS, EC 2.7.7.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At2g02500 (302)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U566797</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc04323</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG528</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (127.5 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-(Cytidine 5&#x02019;-diphospho)-2-C-methyl-D-erythritol kinase (ISPE, EC 2.7.1.148)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At2g26930 (383)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U583224</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc04133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cTOC-4-C7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (19 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-C-methyl-D-erythritol 2,4-cyclodiphosphate synthase (ISPF, EC 4.6.1.12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At1g63970 (231)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U568497</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03923</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At3g27530</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (78 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-Hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-enyl- diphosphate synthase (HDS, EC 1.17.7.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At5g60600 (717)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U567167</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03876</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At5g60600</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (79 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4-Hydroxy-3-methylbut-2-enyl- diphosphate reductase (HDR, EC 1.17.1.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At4g34350 (466)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U580658</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc04323</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At4g34350</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (154 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Isopentenyl diphosphate &#x003b4;-isomerase (IPI, EC 5.3.3.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At3g02780 (284)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U577516 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc06101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U49812</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (64 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At5g16440 (291)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">Phillips <italic>et al.,</italic> 2008</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U569721 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03902</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At5g04270</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (112.7 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geranyl pyrophosphate synthase (GPPS, EC 2.5.1.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At2g34630 (422)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">(Bouvier <italic>et al.,</italic>2000</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U573523</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03835</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At1g30360</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (21.3 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" colspan="1">Geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthase (GGPS, EC 2.5.1.29)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><underline>At4g36810</underline>(371)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U574849 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03748</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At5g16710</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (31.4 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U571085 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc04135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At1g19340</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (112 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><underline>At4g38460</underline>(326)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U573348 (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03665</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CT232</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (90.1 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U575882 (4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03771</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0532</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (30 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geranylgeranyl reductase (GGDR, EC 1.3.1-)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At1g74470 (467)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U564571</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03701</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At1G74470</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (122 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">3-Deoxy-D-arabino-heptulosonate-7-P synthase (DAHPS, EC 2.5.1.54)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At1g22410 (527)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">U581552 (1)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03748</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">T0408</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">11 (26 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At4g33510 (432)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At4g39980 (525 )</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Entus <italic>et al.,</italic>2002</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U566921 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc04135</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1560</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (83.5 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-Dehydroquinate synthase (DHQS, EC 4.2.3.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At5g66120 (442)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U568781</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03665</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At3g01160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (83.4 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Shikimate dehydrogenase (SDH, EC 1.1.1.25) / 3-Dehydroquinate dehydratase (DHQ, EC 4.2.1.10)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">At3g06350 (603)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U570855(1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc05941</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1704</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (39 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U570070(2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03622</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG221</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (101 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Shikimate kinase (SK, EC 2.7.1.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At2g21940 (276)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">U582040</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">SL2.31sc06101</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">C2_At3g62940</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4 (56 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At4g39540 (300)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">5-Enolpyruvylshikimate-3-P synthase (EPSPS, EC 2.5.1.19)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At1g48860 (521)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">U577580</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">SL2.31sc04323</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">C2_At2g45240</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">1 (57 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At2g45300 (520)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chorismate synthase (CS, EC 4.2.3.5)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">At1g48850 (380)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U563165(1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc06101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At3g07950</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (56.7 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U563163(2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03604</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG370</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (21.5 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" colspan="1">Chorismate mutase (CM, EC 5.4.99.5)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">At1g69370 (316)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chloroplast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">Mobley <italic>et al.,</italic>1999</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03665</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">T1480</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">2 (106 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U575627(1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">At5g10870 (340)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chloroplast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Eberhard <italic>et al.,</italic> 1996</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03748</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">TG147</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">11 (45 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At3g29200 (265)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytosol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Eberhard <italic>et al.,</italic> 1996</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U585231(2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prephenate aminotransferase (PAT, EC 2.6.1.57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At2g22250 (475)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U567172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc06101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At4g39830</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (61 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Arogenate dehydrogenase (TyrA, EC 1.3.1.78)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>At1g15710 (</underline>358)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U567861 (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03731</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At5g34850</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (0.4 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At5g34930 (640)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Rippert <italic>et al.,</italic> 2009</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U570951 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03771</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1212</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (48 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Tyrosine aminotransferase (TAT, EC 2.6.1.5)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><underline>At5g53970</underline>(414)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U577103(1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc05925</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At1g53000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (7.5 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U563404 (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03685</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At1g03820</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (43 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">4-Hydroxyphenylpyruvate dioxygenase (HPPD, EC 1.13.11.27)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><underline>At1g06570</underline>(473)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cytosol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">Garcia <italic>et al.,</italic>1999</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U580457(1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03685</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG584</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (36.5 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U578997(2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03902</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CLET-6-I4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (70 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homogentisate geranylgeranyl transferase/ homogentisate solanesyl transferase (HGGT/HST, EC 2.5.1.-)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At3g11945.2 (393)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U585005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc06725</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C2_At3g58490</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (72.6cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homogentisate phytyl transferase [HPT (VTE2), EC 2.5.1.-]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>At2g18950</underline>(393)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U327540(5&#x02019;) U576207(3&#x02019;)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03731</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>cTOA-13-K15</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (17 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Dimethyl-phytylquinol methyl transferase [MPBQMT (VTE3), EC 2.1.1.-]</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><underline>At3g63410</underline>(338)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U578249(1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc04777</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T0565</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (52 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U581492(2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc04439</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG324</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (4.6 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tocopherol cyclase [TC (VTE1), EC 5.3.-.-]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>At4g32770</underline>(488)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U570602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc04948</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At4g32770</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (34 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;-Tocopherol C-methyl transferase [&#x003b3;-TMT (VTE4), EC 2.1.1.95]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At1g64970 (348)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">Ferro <italic>et al.,</italic> 2010</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U584511</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03923</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TG282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (41.8 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phytol kinase [PK (VTE5), EC 2.7.-.-]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>At5g04490</underline>(304)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U583081</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03771</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At5g58240</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (50.5 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anthranilate phosphoribosyltransferase (APT, EC 2.4.2.18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>At5g17990</underline>(444)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U566340</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc05054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C2_At5g17990</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (59 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Phosphoribosylanthranilate isomerase (PRAI, EC 5.3.1.24)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>At1g07780 (</underline>275)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">U564371</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">SL2.31sc05732</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">cLET-1-I13</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">6 (24 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At1g29410 (244)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib98">Zhao and Last, 1995</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At5g05590 (275)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Folylpolyglutamate synthase (FPGS, EC 6.3.2.17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>At5g41480</underline>(530)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">Ravanel <italic>et al.,</italic> 2001</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U581922<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn8">h</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mitochondria</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc05732</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At5g41480</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (26 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phospholipid transporter SEC14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>At3g51670</underline>(409)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">Peterman <italic>et al.,</italic> 2004</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U583419</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc03771</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">T1095</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (50.5 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Chlorophyllase (CHL, EC 3.1.1.14)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>At5g43860 (</underline>318)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cytosol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">Schenk <italic>et al.,</italic> 2007</xref>)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">U574853</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">nd</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">SL2.31sc05732</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">T0834</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">6 (32 cM)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">At1g19670 (324)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lycopeno &#x003b2;-cyclase LYCB</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><underline>At3g10230</underline>(369)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast(Ferro <italic>et al.,</italic> 2010)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U570109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chloroplast</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SL2.31sc05054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cLET-19-J2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (74 cM)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>a</label><p>Enzyme name, number according to KEGG (www.genome.jp/kegg/) and abbreviation.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn2"><label>b</label><p><italic>A. thaliana</italic> enzyme localization according to The Plant Proteome Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ppdb.tc.cornell.edu">ppdb.tc.cornell.edu</ext-link>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">Sun <italic>et al.,</italic> 2009</xref>) or specific reference.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn3"><label>c</label><p>Tomato unigene number according to SGN (solgenomics.net).</p></fn><fn id="tblfn4"><label>d</label><p>Sub-cellular localization prediction according to TargetP 1.1 software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TargetP/">www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TargetP/</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">Emanuelsson <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>) and ChloroP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ChloroP">www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ChloroP</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn id="tblfn5"><label>e</label><p><italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> scaffold spanning the corresponding gene (version 2.31).</p></fn><fn id="tblfn6"><label>f</label><p>Closest markers within scaffold.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn7"><label>g</label><p>Chromosome and genetic position in Tomato-EXPEN 2000 v52.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn8"><label>h</label><p>5&#x02019; incomplete unigene</p></fn><fn><p>Nd, not determined</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The identified tomato genes were mapped onto the Tomato-EXPEN 2000 genetic map available at the Solanaceae Genomics Network. The genetic positions were obtained by BLASTN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Altschul <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>) searches of the identified unigenes and/or their corresponding genomic sequences against the entire Tomato-EXPEN 2000 map marker sequences database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://solgenomics.net/index.pl">http://solgenomics.net/index.pl</ext-link>). Map Chart software 2.2 (Voorrips, 2000) was used to construct the graphical representation of the genetic map.</p><p>Expression data for the set of genes analysed here were extracted from a TOM1 microarray experiment previously published (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Carrari <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). This experiment comprises transcript analyses from tomato fruits harvested along development and ripening stages (10, 15, 20, 21, 35, 49, 56, and 70 d after anthesis).</p></sec><sec><title>Tocopherol quantification by HPLC and QTL mapping</title><p>Tocopherol extraction was performed as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">Fraser <italic>et al.</italic> (2000)</xref> with the following modifications: tomato fruit were ground to a fine powder in liquid nitrogen and 500 mg of material was extracted with 1.5 ml of methanol and, after vortex-mixing, 1 ml of chloroform was added. Following 5 min of sonication, 1 ml of Tris buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.5/1 M NaCl) was added. The chloroform phase was recovered and the methanol phase (remaining pellet) was re-extracted with chloroform (2 ml). Chloroform extracts were pooled and adjusted to a final volume of 4 ml. Two millilitres were dried under nitrogen gas and re-suspended in 0.2 ml of 99.5:0.5 hexane/isopropanol. The tocopherol content was determined using a Hewlett-Packard series 1100 HPLC system coupled with a fluorescence detector (Agilent Technologies series 1200). Separation was carried out on a normal-phase column Metasil Si (250 mm&#x000d7;4.6 mm, 5 &#x003bc;m, Varian; Metachem, Torrance, CA, USA) maintained at room temperature using an isocratic solvent system (mobile phase) consisting of 99.5:0.5 hexane/isopropanol with a flow rate of 1 ml min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Eluting compounds were detected and quantified by fluorescence with excitation at 296 nm and emission at 340 nm. Identification and quantification of tocopherol compounds was achieved by comparison with the retention times and peak areas of standards purchased from Merck (tocopherol set; Calbiochem #613424). A daily calibration curve was carried out using a tocopherol solution with a concentration range between 0.31 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 5 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for each isoform. Data of tocopherol isoforms or total tocopherol content were statistically analysed according to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">Sokal and Rohlf (1981)</xref>. When the data pull presented homoscedasticity, with or without data transformation using ln or square root, an ANOVA followed by a Dunnett test (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05) was used to compare tocopherol content between ILs and M82 control. Due to lack of homoscedasticity, a non-parametric comparison was also performed by Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 and <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.1). Statistical tests were performed with Bioestat 5.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Ayres <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) and InfoStat v. 2009 (Grupo InfoStat, FCA, Universidad Nacional de C&#x000f3;rdoba, Argentina).</p><p>The position of tocopherol QTL on the Tomato-EXPEN 2000 map was determined according to the flanking markers of the <italic>S. pennellii</italic> introgression fragments in the analysed ILs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Eshed and Zamir, 1995</xref>) and mapping of unigenes performed as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">Kamenetzky <italic>et al.</italic> (2010)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Identification of VTE-related pathway candidate genes</title><p>Candidate genes were surveyed along the genomic regions spanned by the identified VTE QTL as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Berm&#x000fa;dez <italic>et al.</italic> (2008)</xref>. All molecular markers mapped onto the selected genomic regions were identified in the comparison merging the Tomato-EXPEN 2000, the Tomato-EXPEN 1992, and the Tomato IL maps by using the comparative map web interface of the Solanaceae Genomics Network (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">Mueller <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). All marker sequences were used as query to identify the corresponding unigenes in the Solanaceae Genomics Network database. Gene product functions were determined according to homology to a previously characterized protein, whose function had been experimentally demonstrated in other related plant species, by using the BLASTX algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Altschul <italic>et al.</italic>, 1990</xref>) against the NCBI non-redundant (nr) protein database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>). The cut-off criteria were: &#x02265;40% identity at amino acid level and &#x02265;65% coverage of the orthologous <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> protein. For uncompleted unigenes the coverage cut-off was set at &#x02265;30%.</p></sec><sec><title>Amplification, cloning, and sequencing</title><p>Total RNA from 100 mg of source leaf or fruit tissue was isolated using Trizol reagent (Invitrogen, #15596-026) and 1 &#x003bc;g from each sample was treated with amplification grade DNase I (Invitrogen, #18068-015) to remove potential contamination of genomic DNA. The treated RNA was reverse-transcribed to first-strand cDNA and primed with oligo(dT) using Superscript First-Strand (Invitrogen, #18080-044) following the manufacturer's protocol.</p><p>Primers were designed using the software Oligo Analyzer 3.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.idtdna.com">http://www.idtdna.com</ext-link>) on the basis of unigene sequences including the sequence surrounding the putative ATG start and stop codons. The primer sequences are available in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err055/DC2">Table S1 in Supplementary data</ext-link> available at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p><p>Full-length cDNA fragments were generated by PCR using <italic>Taq</italic> Platinum <italic>pfx</italic> DNA polymerase (Invitrogen, #11708-013). The PCR reactions were conducted in a total volume of 50 &#x003bc;l containing 0.3 mM each dNTPs, 0.4 &#x003bc;M each primer, 1.5&#x000d7; reaction buffer, 1 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, &#x0223c;150 ng of cDNA, and 2.5 IU of enzyme. The amplification conditions were: 94 &#x000b0;C for 3 min; 35 cycles of 94 &#x000b0;C for 15 s; primer-specific annealing temperature for 30 s; and then 68 &#x000b0;C for 2 min. Amplification products were purified with GFX purification Kit (Amersham Biosciences, #289034-70) and cloned into a pCR-Blunt II TOPO vector using a TOPO-Zero Blunt cloning kit (Invitrogen, #45-0245). Plasmid DNA was isolated using a Qiagen Miniprep Kit (#27106) and inserts were sequenced with BigDye Terminator (Applied Biosystems, #4336919) on an ABI3700 automated sequencer (Applied Biosystems). Sequence data from this article have been deposited in the GenBank Data Libraries under accession number HQ014366&#x02013;HQ014383 and HQ219713&#x02013;HQ219716. Polymorphisms were detected at nucleotide and amino acid levels by aligning <italic>S. pennellii</italic> and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> sequenced alleles (excluding primer regions) using the MULTALIN program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www-archbac.u-psud.fr/genomics/multalin.html">http://www-archbac.u-psud.fr/genomics/multalin.html</ext-link>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Corpet, 1988</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Evolutionary analyses</title><p>The coding region alignments of <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, and <italic>S. pennellii</italic> were performed with BioEdit Sequence Alignment Editor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">Hall, 1999</xref>) using the ClustalW package (v1.81 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">Thompson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994</xref>) and were manually curated according to amino acid alignment. Non-synonymous (<italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>) and synonymous (<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub>) distances and their SE values were estimated with MEGA 4.1 software (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib84">Tamura <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>) using the Nei&#x02013;Gojobori method (p-distance). In order to preserve the reading frames, the alignment gaps were deleted prior to estimation of <italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>. Codon bias was determined by the effective number of codons (<italic>N</italic><sub>c</sub>) value computed in the CodonW program (mobyle.pasteur.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py?form=codonw). <italic>N</italic><sub>c</sub> varies between 21 for maximum codon bias, when only one codon is used per amino acid, and 61 for minimum codon bias, when synonymous codons for each amino acid are used at similar frequencies. One-way ANOVA with Tukey's <italic>post-hoc</italic> test in the InfoStat software was performed to evaluate significant differences in codon usage.</p><p>In order to compare codon evolution models to determine selective constraint, three models were fitted using the CODEML program of the PAML suite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib94">Yang, 2007</xref>). The first model, M0, assumes that all codons across the sequences have the same level of <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> and estimates these values and the <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> ratio (&#x003c9;). &#x003c9; is a signal of the selection at protein level thus, 0&#x0003c;&#x003c9;&#x0003c;1 indicates purifying selection, &#x003c9;=1 neutral selection, and &#x003c9;&#x0003e;1 points to the presence of positive selection. The model M1a proposes the existence of two classes of codon, a proportion with 0&#x0003c;&#x003c9;&#x0003c;1 and the remainder of codons with &#x003c9;=1. Finally, model M2a divides codons into three classes: those with 0&#x0003c;&#x003c9;&#x0003c;1, &#x003c9;=1, and &#x003c9;&#x02265;1. The fit of model M0 versus M1a or M1a versus M2a is evaluated by a likelihood ratio test comparing twice the difference in log likelihoods with a &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> distribution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib94">Yang, 2007</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Identification, mapping, and expression analyses of tomato genes involved in VTE biosynthesis</title><p>VTE compounds, tocopherols, and tocotrienols, are products of the convergence of the plastidial MEP and SK pathways. With the aim of identifying every metabolic step in tocochromanol biosynthesis in tomato, the two routes from their primary metabolism precursors were linked to the VTE core pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>) based on data available in the KEGG database. After an in-depth search of the unigene database deposited in the Solanaceae Genomics Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://solgenomics.net">http://solgenomics.net</ext-link>), using <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> loci as reference sequences, all the putative tomato enzyme encoding genes were identified (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Twenty-nine biochemical reactions constitute the VTE biosynthesis pathway and these are catalyzed by 28 enzymes, for which a total of 41 different tomato encoding loci were described. For eleven of the enzymes, the number of surveyed tomato genes differs from those described for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, according to the criteria adopted here. Only one point in the pathway shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref> remains obscure in plant metabolism, which is the phosphorylation of phytyl P to provide phytyl 2P from phytol via VTE5, as an alternative to the MEP pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib91">Valentin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><p>The subcellular localization of the protein products of previously identified <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> loci were predicted by the TargetP and ChloroP softwares. Enzymes that did not contain a predicted targeting peptide were considered cytosolic. This <italic>in silico</italic> prediction was in general agreement with the experimental evidence reported for the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> orthologues (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). For two proteins, however, predictions revealed unexpected results. The tomato geranyl pyrophosphate synthase (GPPS) enzyme was predicted to be targeted to the mitochondria, while for the bi-functional shikimate dehydrogenase/3-dehydroquinate dehydratase (SDH/DHQ) no signal peptides were detected for any of the identified loci. Moreover, none of the tomato CMs presented a predicted plastid signal peptide. The fact that the last enzyme of the post-chorismate portion of the SK pathway, tyrosine aminotransferase (TAT), and HPPD appeared to be localized in the cytosol in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> cells provides intrigue regarding the transport of homogentisate across the chloroplast envelope (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Joyard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). These predictions, with regard to the tomato proteins, also failed to propose a subcellular localization for TAT, even though one of the HPPD unigenes exhibited a chloroplast signal peptide prediction.</p><p>As a second step in the characterization of the genetic basis of tocochromanol biosynthesis, the 41 tomato loci involved in MEP, SK, and VTE core pathways were localized onto the tomato genetic map (Tomato-EXPEN 2000) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figs 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). Mapping was based on physical linkage between mapped markers and the unigenes and/or their corresponding genomic sequences. With the exception of chromosome 12, all other tomato chromosomes harbour at least one of the identified loci. Interestingly, most of the tocochromanol core pathway enzyme-encoding loci were localized on chromosomes 7, 8, and 9, except for <italic>hst</italic> and <italic>vte3(2)</italic>, mapping to chromosome 3, and <italic>hppd(2)</italic>, mapping to chromosome 5. Remarkably, the four genes mapped on chromosome 9, <italic>vte3(1)</italic>, <italic>vte5</italic>, arogenate dehydrogenase [<italic>tyra(2)</italic>], and geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthase [<italic>ggps(4)</italic>] all co-localize with a previously reported QTL for &#x003b1;-tocopherol content described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Schauer <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref>.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Genomic localization of tocopherol biosynthesis and candidate genes. All genes were localized in the Tomato-EXPEN 2000 genetic map available at the Solanaceae Genomics Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://solgenomics.net/index.pl">http://solgenomics.net/index.pl</ext-link>). Markers and genes are indicated on the left side of the chromosomes. Tocopherol QTL are indicated on the right side of the chromosomes. Gene colour code is in accordance with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexboterr055f02_3c"/></fig><p>Of the 41 identified genes, the expression patterns of 27 of them could be evaluated across fruit development and ripening, by retrieving data from a previously published microarray experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Carrari <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). This analysis revealed that all 27 genes were expressed in tomato fruits in at least one time point. The *omeSOM model of neural clustering recently developed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">Milone <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>) revealed six groups. Whilst these clusters grouped genes from all three evaluated pathways, no specific pathway patterns were identified (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>QTL for fruit tocopherol content and identification of candidate genes</title><p>As mentioned above, these mapping results revealed that the majority of the VTE core pathway enzyme-encoding genes are grouped within chromosomes 7, 8, and 9. Previously, using GC-MS analysis, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Schauer <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref> reported two QTL for fruit &#x003b1;-tocopherol content localized to chromosomes 6 and 9. In order to investigate further the presence of other QTL associated with the genomic regions that harbour the tocopherol core biosynthesis genes, and as such to obtain a precise and detailed quantification, an HPLC protocol for measuring all four tocopherol isoforms was applied.</p><p>The content of &#x003b1;-, &#x003b2;-, &#x003b3;-, &#x003b4;-, and total tocopherol was determined from ripe tomato fruits from the ILs 6-1, 6-2, 7-4, 7-4-1, 7-5, 8-2, 8-2-1, 9-1, 9-2-6 as well as fruits from the corresponding <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> control (cv M82). The amount of each isoform and their ratios are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>, whereas the identified QTL are positioned on the genetic map presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>. On chromosome 9, two QTL were identified for &#x003b1;- and total tocopherol (ILs 9-1 and 9-2-6), one for &#x003b2;-tocopherol (IL 9-1), and one for &#x003b3;-tocopherol (IL 9-1). Both QTL for total tocopherol are in agreement with the results reported in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Schauer <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref>. The QTL on IL 9-2-6 co-localize with two VTE core pathway encoding genes: <italic>vte3(1)</italic> and <italic>vte5</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>), whilst the QTL on IL 9-1 spans the genomic region containing <italic>tyra(2)</italic> and <italic>ggps(4)</italic>. Measurements performed in fruits from ILs with <italic>S. pennellii</italic> introgressions on chromosome 6 showed significant differences from M82 fruits in the levels of &#x003b2;-tocopherol (IL 6-2), &#x003b4;-, and total tocopherol (IL 6-1). Moreover, QTL were also identified on chromosome 7 (ILs 7-4 and 7-4-1 for &#x003b1;- and &#x003b2;-tocopherol, respectively) and 8 (IL 8-2-1 for total tocopherol) also co-localizing with the genes encoding the VTE core pathway enzymes: <italic>vte2</italic> and <italic>hppd(1)</italic> on chromosome 7 and <italic>vte1</italic> and <italic>vte4</italic> on chromosome 8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>). Besides the mentioned genes, the presence of <italic>tyra(1)</italic> at 0.4 cM and <italic>tat(2)</italic> at 43 cM on chromosome 7 could also be responsible for the &#x003b1;- and &#x003b2;-tocopherol QTL mapped onto these regions.</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Tocopherol content. Tocopherol content was determined by HPLC. Grey bars indicate means of six biological replicates. Significant differences compared with the M82 control cultivar (black bars) according to Dunnett test (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05) and/or Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 ** and <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.1*) are indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexboterr055f03_ht"/></fig><p>By surveying the genomic regions spanning the identified QTL, six novel candidate genes belonging to VTE-related pathways were found. On chromosome 6, at 32 cM, a chlorophyllase encoding gene (CHL, EC 3.1.1.14) was identified. It has been proposed that the first step in the degradation of chlorophyll during senescence and fruit ripening is catalysed by this enzyme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">H&#x000f6;rtensteiner, 2006</xref>) through the synthesis of phytol, providing phytyl 2P to the VTE pathway via VTE5. Moreover, three enzyme-encoding genes for the two branching pathways from chorismate to tryptophan and folate were also identified: a phosphoribosylanthranilate isomerase (PRAI, EC 5.3.1.24), a folylpolyglutamate synthase (FPGS, EC 6.3.2.17), and an anthranilate phosphoribosyltransferase (APT, EC 2.4.2.18) mapping at 24, 26, and 59 cM, respectively. Finally, the lycopene &#x003b2;-cyclase (LYCB) encoding gene was found at 74 cM of chromosome 6. This enzyme, which catalyses the last step in &#x003b2;-carotene biosynthesis, has been deeply characterized after a positional cloning strategy by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">Ronen <italic>et al.</italic> (2000)</xref> and constitutes a strong candidate for tocopherol content due to the common precursor geranylgeranyl 2P. Another putative candidate, the SEC14 protein-encoding gene, was found on chromosome 9. Several studies have demonstrated the involvement of this protein in tocopherol transport in mammalian cells and lipid traffic in plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">Saito <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Bankaitis <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). With the exception of the <italic>chl</italic> these novel candidates are expressed in tomato fruits at least one time point of the developmental analysis performed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Carrari <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref>.</p><p>Taken together the results obtained from tomato gene identification, mapping, tocopherol quantification, and QTL localization, 16 candidate loci putatively affecting tocopherol content in tomato can be proposed: <italic>prai</italic>, <italic>fpgs</italic>, <italic>chl</italic>, <italic>apt</italic>, and <italic>lycb</italic> on chromosome 6; <italic>tyra(1)</italic>, <italic>vte2</italic>, <italic>hppd(1)</italic>, and <italic>tat(2)</italic> located on chromosome 7; <italic>vte1</italic> and <italic>vte4</italic> on chromosome 8; and <italic>ggps(4)</italic>, <italic>tyra(2)</italic>, <italic>vte5</italic>, <italic>sec14</italic>, and <italic>vte3(1)</italic> on chromosome 9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1 fig2 fig3">Figs 1&#x02013;3</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Allele characterization of QTL-associated candidates</title><p>The identification of 16 QTL-associated candidate genes prompted us to unearth the allelic differences between <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>S. pennellii</italic> (underlined genes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>). The coding regions of wild alleles were thus subsequently cloned from the corresponding ILs using primers annealing to the initial and stop codons. Although only minor size differences were observed between the two alleles for most of the genes, TyrA(2)-, VTE4-, PRAI-, and CHL-encoding genes exhibited different amplicon length. These results indicated that neither vast allelic polymorphisms, nor large genomic rearrangements, span the chromosomal region encompassing the analysed genes. This comparison revealed that all analysed candidate genes present at least one non-synonymous polymorphism (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). The most divergent alleles are those encoding the PRAI enzyme for which the <italic>S. pennelli</italic> allele encodes a protein 26 amino acids shorter in comparison with the <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> allele.</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Comparison of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>S. pennellii</italic> alleles of cDNA encoding VTE candidate genes. LYC, <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>; PEN, <italic>S. pennellii</italic>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gene</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Unigene</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Coding sequence (nt)<hr/></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Predicted protein (no. amino acids)<hr/></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">No. of polymorphic nucleotides<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn9">a</xref></td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">No. of polymorphic amino acids<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn9">a</xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LYC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEN</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LYC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PEN</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ggps</italic>(4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U575882</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1005</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">334</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">334</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tat</italic>(2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U563404</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1269</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1269</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">422</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">422</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tyra</italic>(1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U567861</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">377</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">377</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tyra</italic>(2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U570951</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1173</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1182</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">390</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">393</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24+9insertions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9+3insertions</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vte4</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U584511</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1089</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">362</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">361</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9+3deletions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2+1deletion</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vte1</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U570602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1497</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1497</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">498</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">498</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vte3(1)</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U578249</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1020</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">339</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">339</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vte2</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U327540 (covers 5&#x02019; end)U576207 (covers 3&#x02019; end)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1209</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1209</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">402</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vte5</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U583081</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">882</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">882</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">293</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">293</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hppd</italic>(1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U580457</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1263</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1263 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">b</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">420</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">420 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn10">b</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>apt</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U566340 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn11">c</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1097 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn11">c</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1097 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn11">c</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">365</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">365</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>prai</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U564371</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">906</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">828</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">275</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12+78deletions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3+26deletions</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>fpgs</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U581922 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn11">c</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1457 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn11">c</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1457 <xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn11">c</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">485</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">485</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>chl</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U574853</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">939</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">948</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">312</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">315</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22+9insertions</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9+3insertions</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sec14</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U583419</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1275</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1275</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">424</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">424</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>lycb</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">U570109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1497</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1497</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">498</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">498</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn9"><label>a</label><p>Nucleotide or amino acid insertions or deletions in <italic>S. pennellii</italic> sequences.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn10"><label>b</label><p><italic>S. pennellii</italic> does not present a stop codon along the analysed region.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn11"><label>c</label><p>Probably lacking 3' end.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>VTE biosynthesis genes: evolutionary analyses of cultivated and wild tomato alleles</title><p>The fate of cellular metabolic networks generally depends on the products of many loci. The inter-relationships between loci at the phenotypic level raise the question of whether they evolved independently. In this work QTL for tocopherol content using <italic>S. pennelli</italic> ILs were mapped, and 16 candidate loci linked to those QTL were identified and the wild species alleles cloned. Furthermore, in order to study how the structure of the VTE metabolic pathway could have influenced protein evolution rates, the evolutionary pattern among the candidate genes and their paralogues was also investigated, estimating the pairwise synonymous (<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub>), non-synonymous (<italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>), and <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> divergence between <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>S. pennellii</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). The <italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub> values varied greatly between genes, ranging from 4.8 to 16 times for <italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>, respectively. Four genes, <italic>ggps(2)</italic>, <italic>tyra(2)</italic>, <italic>chl</italic>, and <italic>lycb</italic>, displayed particularly high values of <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>, above the mean. The <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> also varied remarkably among the 22 loci analysed with the highest value being 17.4 times the lowest. The genes of MEP, post-chorismate SK, and tocopherol biosynthesis core pathways displayed values similar to or lower than the average with the exception of those presenting more than one locus. Among candidate genes of related pathways <italic>apt</italic>, <italic>chl</italic>, and <italic>lycb</italic> displayed higher <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> values than the mean. Interestingly, the five genes for which more than one locus was identified displayed variations of <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> values between paralogues. The <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> values for the different <italic>ggps</italic>, <italic>tat</italic>, <italic>tyra</italic>, v<italic>te3</italic> and <italic>hppd</italic> varied by 3.5, 2.1, 7.6, 3.4, and 1.9 times, respectively. Differences in <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> values between the paralogues might be due to high <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub> caused by a weak selection at non-synonymous sites, or related to the intensity of natural selection on synonymous codon usage. To investigate the existence of codon usage bias, the effective number of codons (<italic>N</italic><sub>c</sub>) was calculated for each gene and species (<italic>S. pennellii</italic> and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>). No statistically significant differences (ANOVA, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003e;0.01) in <italic>N</italic><sub>c</sub> were observed between <italic>ggps</italic>, <italic>tat</italic>, <italic>tyra</italic>, and v<italic>te3</italic> paralogues, suggesting that the <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> differences are most probably due to a constraint relaxation for one of the gene copies rather than codon bias. In contrast, for the <italic>hppd</italic> pair a significant <italic>N</italic><sub>c</sub> bias was observed (ANOVA, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01). This can be also visualized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref> comparing <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> values, suggesting that the <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> rate differences between <italic>hppd</italic> paralogues might not be explained by constraint relaxation.</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Evolutionary rates at synonymous (dS) and non-synonymous (dN) sites of candidate genes linked to tocopherol QTL. Genes belonging to MEP, SK, and tocopherol core pathways are highlighted in red, green, and blue, respectively. VTE-related pathway candidates are not highlighted. Lines indicated estimated means.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="jexboterr055f04_3c"/></fig><p>Although <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> is a useful indicator of selective pressure, there is some oversimplification in its application since it may be that only certain codons in a gene can change in a way that enhances fitness whereas all others cannot accept substitutions without cost to fitness. Thus, to better explore patterns of sequence variation, the orthologous sequences from <italic>A. thaliana</italic>, <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, and <italic>S. pennellii</italic> for all 22 genes under study were aligned and a Likelihood Ratio Test (LRT) with three models of molecular evolution was applied. The first, M0, assumes that all positions across the sequences have the same level of <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub> and <italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub>. The second, M1a, proposes that a proportion of codons is under purifying selection while the remainder have neutral evolution. Finally, M2a divides codons into three classes, those with purifying selection, those with neutral evolution pattern, and the remainder with positive selection. In order to avoid data misinterpretation, the <italic>N</italic><sub>c</sub> was estimated and the comparison between species did not show statistically significant differences (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003e;0.01), indicating that there is no codon bias usage. Comparison of the three models showed that for 19 genes M1a displayed the best fit, indicating that, even when a proportion of the codons for every gene are evolving neutrally, there is no support for positive selection. Nevertheless, for <italic>ggps(2)</italic>, <italic>ggps(4)</italic>, and <italic>vte1</italic>, M2a presented a better fit than M1a, with different levels of significance, showing that these genes exhibited signs of positive selection. Interestingly, while <italic>ggps(2)</italic> and <italic>vte1</italic> showed a higher proportion of codons evolving under positive selection (&#x0223c;25%) than <italic>ggps(4)</italic> (0.8%), they displayed lower significance levels. This can be explained by the high &#x003c9; value of <italic>ggps(4)</italic> indicating that there is no variation in the synonymous sites along the codons under positive natural selection (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Parameter estimates and tests of selection.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">M0<hr/></td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">M1a<hr/></td><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">M2a<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lnL<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn13">a</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c9;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn14">b</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lnL<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn13">a</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c9;0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn15">c</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c1;0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn16">d</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn17">e</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">lnL<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn13">a</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c9;0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn18">f</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c1;0<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn19">g</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c9;2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn20">h</xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c1;2<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn21">i</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn22">j</xref></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ggps(1)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2640.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2598.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.734**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2598.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.743</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ggps(2)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2594.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2551.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.730**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2549.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.746</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.474</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.254*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ggps(3)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2444.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2411.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.812**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2411.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.813</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.134</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.187</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ggps(4)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2233.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2200.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.811**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2196.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.811</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">999.000</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tat(1)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2718.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2690.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.792**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2690.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.044</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.792</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tat(2)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2857.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.077</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2841.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.817**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2841.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.817</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tyra(1)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2487.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2461.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.740**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2461.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.740</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tyra(2)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2657.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2615.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.612**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2615.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.612</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vte4</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2425.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.062</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2391.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.765**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2391.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.765</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vte1</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;3430.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.072</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;3373.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.730**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;3371.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.742</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.165</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.257*</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vte3(1)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2138.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.051</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2124.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.900**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2124.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.900</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vte3(2)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2256.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2231.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2231.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vte2</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2693.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2653.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.739**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2653.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.739</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>vte5</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2302.1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2287.6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.541**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2287.6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.541</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hppd(1)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2586.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2552.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.818**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2552.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.820</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.258</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>hppd(2)</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2617.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2579.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.805**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2579.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.805</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>apt</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2447.7</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2400.6</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.770**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;2399.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.799</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.629</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.201</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>prai</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1556.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.144</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1551.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.732**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1551.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.104</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.732</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>fpgs</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3435.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.100</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3410.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.742**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-3410.5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.742</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>chl</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2198.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.127</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2186.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.846**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2185.9</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.080</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.853</td><td align="char" char="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.124</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.146</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>sec14</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2547.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.030</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2527.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.894**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2527.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.894</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>lycb</italic></td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2628.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2608.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.772**</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2608.2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.772</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn13"><label>a</label><p>Log likehood of model.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn14"><label>b</label><p>Parameter estimate assuming a single <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub><italic>/d</italic><sub>S</sub> ratio per gene.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn15"><label>c</label><p>Estimated <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub><italic>/d</italic><sub>S</sub> for proportion of codons (&#x003c1;<sub>0</sub>) under purifying selection; the rest of codons assumed to be evolving neutrally.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn16"><label>d</label><p>Estimated proportion of codons under purifying selection.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn17"><label>e</label><p>Test of M1a versus M0. ** &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test using <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn18"><label>f</label><p>Estimated <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub><italic>/d</italic><sub>S</sub> for proportion of codons (&#x003c1;<sub>0</sub>) under purifying selection.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn19"><label>g</label><p>Estimated proportion of codons under purifying selection.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn20"><label>h</label><p>Estimated <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub><italic>/d</italic><sub>S</sub> for proportion of codons (&#x003c1;<sub>2</sub>) under positive selection.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn21"><label>i</label><p>Estimated proportion of codons under positive selection.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn22"><label>j</label><p>Test of M2a versus M1a. * &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test using <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.10; **&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> test using <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01.</p></fn><fn><p>&#x02013;, not available.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The two pathways feeding the main precursors of VTE biosynthesis, MEP and SK, as well as the tocopherol core route, were surveyed across the tomato genome with the aim of identifying regulatory steps of the VTE fruit biosynthesis. The metabolic reconstruction of VTE metabolism resulted in the identification of 29 reactions catalysed by the protein products of 28 genes, for which 41 different <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> loci were identified (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>). In the course of reconstructing these routes, certain assumptions concerning the presence or absence of reactions involved in VTE metabolism had to be made. First, in the MEP pathway, GPPS is the enzyme leading to monoterpene biosynthesis, while GGPS is responsible for the production of geranylgeranyl 2P by the sequential coupling of three isopentenyl 2P (IPP) molecules to dimethylallyl 2P (DMAPP). Geranylgeranyl 2P serves as a precursor for carotenoid, tocochromanol, gibberelin, and chlorophyll biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Aharoni <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">Joyard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Hence, the classical trend is to assume that GPPS would not be involved in tocochromanol production. Tomato plants silenced for GPPS even displayed a dwarfed phenotype and reduced gibberellin levels, and did not alter carotenoid and chlorophyll content (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib92">Van Schie <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). These results thus indicated that pigments are originated from a geranyl 2P-independent geranylgeranyl 2P pool and suggested that GPPS might not influence VTE biosynthesis. However, further functional experiments that validate this hypothesis are clearly needed. Secondly, HGGT, which condenses homogentisate with geranylgeranyl 2P during tocotrienol synthesis, was identified in grass species in which tocotrienols are the most abundant tocochromanol forms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Cahoon <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>). Neither in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> nor in tomato was HGGT identified. However, tocotrienol traces have been detected in both tomato and tobacco (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Chun <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). This might be explained by the promiscuous activity in substrate acceptance of other prenyl transferases such as homogentisate solanesyl transferase (HST) and/or the homogentisate phytyl transferase (VTE2). Flux changes through the SK, MEP, and/or tocopherol pathway could conceivably shift the substrate preference of both these enzymes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">Herbers, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Falk and Munn&#x000e9;-Bosch, 2010</xref>). This hypothesis is supported by the fact that under certain conditions tobacco plants, which do not have a canonical HGGT, and co-express the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> HPPD and the yeast prephenate dehydrogenase, exhibit higher levels of tocotrienols (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Rippert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>). Therefore, the enhanced supply of homogentisate may affect the substrate specificity of prenyl transferases leaking through tocotrienol synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">Falk and Munn&#x000e9;-Bosch, 2010</xref>). In addition, <italic>A. thaliana</italic> HST, which is essential for plastoquinone-9 biosynthesis&#x02014;catalysing the condensation of solanesyl 2P (SDP) and HGA&#x02014;also accepts farnesyl 2P and geranylgeranyl 2P as prenyl donors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">Sadre <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">Tian <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), providing further evidence in support of tocotrienol production in the absence of a specific HGGT.</p><p>Prephenate aminotransferase (PAT, EC 2.6.1.57), which converts prephenate intermediate into arogenate, has been characterized in bacteria. Although its activity had also been detected in plants, no associated loci were identified with this enzymatic function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib89">Tzin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Recently, two independent reports performed biochemical and functional characterization of this plant enzyme thus, completing the identification of the genes involved in phenylalanine and tyrosine biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">Graindorge <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">Maeda <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p><p>One missing links still remains within the metabolic network under study, which is the absence of a phytol-P kinase that could provide phytyl 2P as an alternative to the MEP pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">Ischebeck <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib91">Valentin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>).</p><p>All the MEP enzyme-encoding genes surveyed here are in accordance with sequences previously reported for tomato (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">Lois <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">Rohdich <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Botella-Pav&#x000ed;a <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Ament <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">Paetzold <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; and GenBank database direct submission for IPI -GQ169536 and EU253957-), with the exception of the 2-C-methyl-<sc>D</sc>-erythritol 4-phosphate cytidylyltransferase (CMS)- and geranylgeranyl reductase (GGDR)-encoding genes, which have not been reported before in this species. Moreover, two additional loci for GGPS were identified here. For the SK pathway, enzyme-encoding genes involved in reactions upstream of the prephenate intermediate have already been reported in tomato (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">Gasser <italic>et al.</italic>, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">Schmid <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">G&#x000f6;rlach <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Eberhard <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Bischoff <italic>et al.</italic>, 1996</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">2001</xref>). Moreover, novel loci for SDH/DHQ and CM were identified, whilst the loci encoding PAT, TyrA, and TAT were first described in tomato.</p><p>Protein localization data are highly valuable information in order to elucidate gene function. The MEP and SK pathways are well accepted to operate in the chloroplast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">Rippert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Even so, the recent identification of some cytosolic isoforms points to the existence of an extraplastidial SK pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Ding <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). The results presented here for the <italic>in silico</italic> prediction of the subcellular localization of the tomato deduced protein sequences indicated that the reactions of VTE metabolism occur mostly in chloroplasts. In contrast, for the bi-functional SDH/DHQ no signal peptide was detected, most probably due to the failure to detect true targeting, since reported analysis of subcellular fractions indicated that tomato SDH/DHQ is localized in the chloroplast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Bischoff <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). However, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Ding <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref> functionally characterized a cytosolic SDH/DHQ isoform in tobacco and identified the tomato orthologue (BF096277/SGN-U578253). This locus was not included in this study due to its low identity to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> protein according to the Pipeline criteria adopted and the absence of functional support so far. Unsuccessful subcellular prediction is not an unusual scenario, since <italic>in silico</italic>, signal peptides are occasionally misidentified. However, these predictions indicated mitochondrial targeting for the <italic>A. thaliana</italic> GPPS (data not shown), whilst experimental data revealed that this enzyme is directed to the plastid (Bouvier <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000). It is important to point out the existence of some ambiguous reports on actual GPPS localization where experimental evidence supports its localization either in plastid or in the cytosol depending on the species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">Nagegowda, 2010</xref>). Moreover, for the TAT and CM enzymes, the plastidial localization could not be confirmed by <italic>in silico</italic> analysis in agreement with the undetermined subcellular occurrence of the post-chorismate portion of the SK pathway.</p><p>Following the identification of the tomato genes encoding all enzymes for the tocochromanol synthesis pathway, the 41 loci were further mapped. Furthermore, a detailed profile for all tocopherol isoforms was performed in fruits from ILs harbouring introgressed regions spanning the VTE biosynthesis core pathway genes (ILs 7-4, 7-4-1, 8-2, 8-2-1, 9-1, and 9-2-6) along with those in chromosome 6 (ILs 6-1 and 6-2) for which &#x003b1;-tocopherol QTL have been previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Schauer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). Although VTE content has been demonstrated to be a highly environmentally affected trait (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">Schauer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>), the results reported here indicate that at least those QTL mapped on chromosomes 6 and 9 show a relatively high heritability level as they are in accordance with previous experiments reported by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">Schauer <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref>. Moreover it is worth noting that, as opposed to the previous study, which was carried out on field-grown plants, the data reported here were obtained from greenhouse plants.</p><p>Integrated analysis at metabolic, genomic, and genetic levels allowed us to propose 16 candidate loci putatively affecting tocopherol content in tomato: <italic>prai</italic>, <italic>fpgs</italic>, <italic>chl</italic>, <italic>apt</italic>, and <italic>lycb</italic> on chromosome 6; <italic>tyra(1)</italic>, <italic>vte2</italic>, <italic>hppd(1)</italic>, and <italic>tat(2)</italic> located on chromosome 7; <italic>vte1</italic> and <italic>vte4</italic> on chromosome 8; and <italic>ggps(4)</italic>, <italic>tyra(2)</italic>, <italic>vte5</italic>, <italic>sec14</italic>, and <italic>vte3(1)</italic> on chromosome 9. In plants, several QTL controlling tocopherol content have been identified in soybean, maize, oilseed rape, and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. As revealed in this report, only some of those QTL localized to areas of the genome where tocopherol core pathway genes occur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">Marwede <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">Gilliland <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Chander <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Detailed analysis of the identified QTL together with the co-localizing genes raised interesting features concerning VTE content regulation. None of chromosome 6 QTL co-localize with any of the MEP, SK, or tocopherol core pathway genes, thus suggesting that tocopherol content variation observed in ILs 6-1 and 6-2 might be determined by the effect of genes belonging to VTE-related pathways. IL 6-1 showed elevated &#x003b4;- and total tocopherol content in comparison with <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> (M82) control. This line harbours the <italic>S. pennellii</italic> alleles of the <italic>prai</italic>, <italic>fpgs</italic>, and <italic>chl</italic> genes. The first two could be regulating hydroxyphenylpyruvate fluxes into the tocopherol pathway by the deviation of chorismate from tryptophan and folate biosynthetic routes. On the other point of the pathway drawn in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Fig. 1</xref>, the hypothesis that chlorophyll degradation-derived phytol serves as an important intermediate for tocopherol synthesis has been demonstrated by characterization of the <italic>Arabidopsis vte5</italic> mutant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib91">Valentin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). In this sense, the presence of <italic>S. pennellii chl</italic> allele in IL 6-1 might be raising the phytyl 2P input into tocopherol synthesis. On the same chromosome, IL 6-2 displayed significantly higher levels of &#x003b2;-tocopherol than the control. This IL carries <italic>S. pennellii</italic> alleles of <italic>chl</italic>, <italic>apt</italic>, and <italic>lycb</italic>. Even when these genes are linked to intermediate metabolites of the tocopherol pathway (chorismate and geranylgeranyl 2P) no evident links can be specifically associated with the &#x003b2;-isoform. The candidature of genes not directly involved in the VTE structural pathway is supported by the regulatory network acting on branching points. The CM acting on the SK pathway is allosterically feedback-inhibited in plants by phenylalanine and tyrosine and induced by tryptophan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib90">Tzin and Galili, 2010</xref>). Allelic variation in <italic>prai</italic> and <italic>apt</italic> could be modifying tryptophan synthesis, altering influx through the SK pathway and then, increasing homogentisate precursor, finally resulting in the tocopherol content variation observed in ILs 6-1 and 6-2.</p><p>Two QTL have been detected on chromosome 7; while IL 7-4 displayed lower levels of &#x003b1;-tocopherol, IL 7-4-1 showed reduced amounts of the &#x003b2;-isoform. The introgressed wild genome fragments in these ILs harbour <italic>S. pennellii</italic> alleles of <italic>tyra(1)</italic>, <italic>vte2</italic>, and <italic>hppd(1)</italic>. IL 7-4 also spans the wild allele of <italic>tat(2)</italic>. These four candidates can alter total precursor influx to tocopherol biosynthesis. Nevertheless, the way that these genes could differentially modify the amounts of tocopherol isoforms is currently unclear.</p><p>On chromosome 8, the IL 8-2 displayed a significantly lower &#x003b1;/&#x003b3;-tocopherol ratio when compared with control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). Interestingly, this IL bears <italic>S. pennellii</italic> alleles of <italic>vte1</italic> and <italic>vte4</italic> genes whose protein product activities synthesize these two tocopherol isoforms. Therefore, the low &#x003b1;/&#x003b3;-tocopherol ratio could be caused by lower VTE1 and/or higher VTE4 activity of wild alleles. Intriguingly, IL 8-2-1 also harbours the wild alleles of <italic>vte1</italic> and <italic>vte4</italic>. Even though no significant alteration in &#x003b1;/&#x003b3;-tocopherol ratio was observed, a significant increase in total tocopherol was detected in the fruits.</p><p>IL 9-1 exhibits increased levels of &#x003b1;-, &#x003b2;-, and total tocopherol most probably due to differential activity levels of the enzymes encoded by the <italic>S. pennellii</italic> allele of the <italic>tyra(2)</italic> and <italic>ggps(4)</italic> loci that could lead to higher input of hydroxyphenylpyruvate and phytyl 2P to the tocopherol core pathway. Elevated &#x003b1;/&#x003b3; and &#x003b2;/&#x003b3; ratios support this hypothesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>). Interesting to note is the fact that <italic>tyra(2)</italic> shows one of the highest <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub> values, indicating protein divergences between <italic>S. pennellii</italic> and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). In this sense, the results presented here reinforce the hypothesis of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">Rippert <italic>et al.</italic> (2004)</xref> that hydroxyphenylpyruvate is a key step in the accumulation of VTE in plants. IL 9-2-6 exhibits increased levels of &#x003b1;- and total tocopherol and harbours the <italic>S. pennellii</italic> allele of the <italic>vte5</italic> gene, which could improve the input of phytyl 2P via the phytol alternative pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib91">Valentin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). However, levels of &#x003b2;-tocopherol are not increased in IL 9-2-6, which could be explained by the more efficient activity of the <italic>S. pennellii vte3</italic> allele. This is also reflected in the significant differences found in the &#x003b1;/&#x003b2; ratio (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><p>Although there is a reliable link between the identified candidate genes and fruit tocopherol content, the effect of unidentified loci within the QTL cannot be discarded and, due to the considerable size of the <italic>S. pennellii</italic> fragments in the ILs, the differences observed in tocopherol accumulation could also be caused by undetected genes located within them.</p><p>Candidate gene approach has proved to be extremely powerful for studying the genetic architecture of complex traits (Zhu and Zao, 2007). By revealing the pattern of molecular genetic variation, the evolutionary analyses offer complementary data for strengthening gene candidature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">Moyle and Muir, 2010</xref>). In this sense, the pattern of selection of different genes within a metabolic pathway allows the determination of whether they are subject to equivalent evolutionary forces underlying trait phenotypic variation. Comparing <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>S. pennellii</italic> alleles, out of the 22 genes studied, those encoding MEP, post-chorismate SK, and VTE core pathway enzymes presented <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub><italic>/d</italic><sub>S</sub> ratios below the mean, excluding those with more than one loci. In contrast, out of the six analysed candidate genes of related pathways, <italic>apt</italic>, <italic>chl</italic>, and <italic>lycb</italic> displayed <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub><italic>/d</italic><sub>S</sub> ratios values above the mean (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig4">Fig. 4</xref>). This constraint relaxation cannot be related to a higher region-specific mutation rate on chromosome 6 because two other genes mapped also on chromosome 6, <italic>prai</italic> and <italic>fpgs</italic>, presented low <italic>d<sub>N</sub>/d<sub>S</sub></italic> ratios. Therefore, these results suggest a strong purifying selection for tocopherol central biosynthesis genes while there is a more relaxed constraint for those genes of related pathways. When the selection constraint is evaluated codon by codon applying a likelihood ratio test, new insights about the evolutionary history of the genes are revealed. Nineteen genes exhibit purifying selection associated with neutral evolving codons (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>) in agreement with the <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> analysis and previous reports that concluded that significant heterogeneity of evolutionary rates in metabolic pathway genes is mainly ascribed to differential constraint relaxation rather than to positive selection (Livingston and Anderson, 2009; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib95">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Even so, three loci exhibited patterns consistent with positive selection evolving codons. In tomato, loci showing positive selection have been identified associated with biotic and abiotic stresses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">Jim&#x000e9;nez-Gomez and Maloof, 2009</xref>). It would be unexpected to envisage signs of positive selection in loci of major biosynthetic pathways that feed multiple metabolic routes such as MEP and SK. However, the signs of diversifying selection found for <italic>ggps(2)</italic> and <italic>ggps(4)</italic> could be explained by the existence of two other paralogues evolving under a more conservative evolutionary pattern. In the case of <italic>vte1</italic>, the reduction in protein negative selective pressure might indicate that this is not a committed step in tocopherol production.</p><p>Studies of evolutionary rates of genes in the plant anthocyanin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">Lu and Rausher, 2003</xref>) and carotenoid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">Livingstone and Anderson, 2009</xref>) pathways have demonstrated that upstream genes in the pathway evolved more slowly than downstream genes. However, this seems not to be a constant trend. Downstream genes in the gibberellin pathway did not exhibit elevated substitution rates and instead, genes encoding either the branch point enzyme or those catalysing multiple steps in the pathway showed the lowest evolutionary rates due to strong purifying selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib95">Yang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). This observation is in close agreement with the theory of pathway fluxes, which indicates that natural selection would target enzymes controlling metabolic fluxes between converging pathways. Consequently, these branch points are usually targets of selection, experiencing higher evolutionary constraints (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">Flowers <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). In this sense, the lowest value of <italic>d</italic><sub>N</sub>/<italic>d</italic><sub>S</sub> was observed for the <italic>tyra(1)</italic> gene whose protein product shares its substrate with phenylalanine/tyrosine biosynthesis resulting in branching points, whilst the <italic>tyra(2)</italic> paralogue displays a relaxed evolutionary constraint, indicative of a functional divergence.</p><p>Genes responsible for adaptive morphological and physiological differences between species carry signatures of positive selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Aguileta <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). In this sense, regarding the variation in VTE content observed in the <italic>S. pennellii</italic> introgressed lines in comparison with that of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, the presence of neutral and/or positive evolving codons could result in novel protein features being a source of new functional profiles. Even when coding sequences are relevant to phenotype, they might not be the location at which key evolutionary changes occur. Analyses across coding sequences do not reveal allelic differences in regulatory sequences that could also be determining the observed phenotypic variations. In fact, a co-response analysis of 32 of the genes identified here revealed an intricate network suggesting these pathways to be finely regulated at the level of gene expression (data not shown).</p><p>This report describes a comprehensive survey of the genes encoding VTE biosynthesis pathway enzymes in tomato, and the methods adopted allowed the identification of novel tocopherol QTL. By an integrated analysis of the genome sequence data together with a well-characterized biosynthetic pathway, like that for VTE in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> model species, this genetic/genomic approach described loci and allelic variations that probably impact antioxidant content in tomato fruit. The identified candidate genes support cross-talk between the MEP, SK, and tocopherol core pathways through the control of VTE accumulation in tomato fruit. In addition, the VTE-related pathway genes might contribute to regulation of the supply of intermediates for plastid tocopherol biosynthesis. The data produced provide a platform for functional studies that will contribute to elucidation of the biosynthesis and catabolism of tocochromanols, and their role in plant physiology.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary data</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err055/DC2">Supplementary data</ext-link> are available at <italic>JXB</italic> online.</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/err055/DC2">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> lists the gene primers used.</p>
      
         <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
            <caption>
               <title>Supplementary Data</title>
            </caption>
            <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_62_11_3781_v2_index.html"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
                   xlink:href="supp_err055_00055194-file001.pdf"/>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank Gregorio Ceccantini for assistance with statistical analyses. This work was partially supported by grants from FAPESP, CNPq, and USP (Brazil); Max Planck Society (Germany); INTA, CONICET, and ANPCyT (Argentina); and under the auspices of the EU SOL Integrated Project FOOD-CT-2006-016214. J.A. was a recipient of a CAPES (Brazil). L.B., F.G., and N.S. were recipients of a FAPESP (Brazil) fellowships. L.Q. was a recipient of an ANPCyT (Argentina) fellowship. R.A. and F.C. are members of CONICET (Argentina). This work was carried out in compliance with current laws governing genetic experimentation in Brazil and in Argentina.</p></ack><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term>IL</term><def><p>introgression line</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LRT</term><def><p>likelihood ratio test</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MEP</term><def><p>methylerythritol phosphate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>QTL</term><def><p>quantitative trait loci</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROS</term><def><p>reactive oxygen species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SK</term><def><p>shikimate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VTC</term><def><p>vitamin C</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VTE</term><def><p>vitamin E</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abushita</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hebshi</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Daood</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Biacs</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of antioxidant vitamins in tomatoes</article-title><source>Food Chemistry</source><year>1997</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>212</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguileta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lengelle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marthey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Finding candidate genes under positive selection in non-model species: examples of genes involved in host specialization in pathogens</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>292</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20041992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jongsma</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volatile science? Metabolic engineering of terpenoids in plants</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16290212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title><source>Journal of Molecular Biology</source><year>1990</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ament</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Schie</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Haring</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuurink</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of a leaf specific geranylgeranyl pyrophosphate synthase and emission of (E, E)-4,8,12-trimethyltrideca-1,3,7,11-tetraene in tomato are dependent on both jasmonic acid and salicylic acid signaling pathways</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2006</year><volume>224</volume><fpage>1197</fpage><lpage>1208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16786318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayres J&#x000fa;nior</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioestat &#x02013; aplica&#x000e7;&#x000f5;es estat&#x000ed;sticas nas &#x000e1;reas das ci&#x000ea;ncias bio-m&#x000e9;dicas</article-title><source>Sociedade Civil Mamirau&#x000e1;/MCT CNPq, Bel&#x000e9;m, PA</source><year>2007</year><comment>Brasil</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bankaitis</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mousley</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaaf</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Sec14 superfamily and mechanisms for crosstalk between lipid metabolism and lipid signaling</article-title><source>Trends in Biochemical Sciences</source><year>2009</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19926291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berm&#x000fa;dez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Urias</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Milstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamenetzky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Asis</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Sluys</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A candidate gene survey of quantitative trait loci affecting chemical composition in tomato fruit</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2008</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>2875</fpage><lpage>2890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18552354</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bischoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;sler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raesecke</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;rlach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrhein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning of a cDNA encoding 3-dehydroquinate synthase from a higher plant, and analysis of the organ-specific and elicitor-induced expression of the corresponding gene</article-title><source>Plant Molecular Biology</source><year>1996</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8704160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bischoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrhein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of tomato 3-dehydroquinate dehydratase-shikimate:NADP oxidoreductase</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2001</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>1891</fpage><lpage>1900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11299368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botella-Pav&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Besumbes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carretero-Paulet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Concepcion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of carotenoid biosynthesis in plants: evidence for a key role of hydroxymethylbutenyl diphosphate reductase in controlling the supply of plastidial isoprenoid precursors</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2004</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15447646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Suire</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>d'Harlingue</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Backhaus</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Camara</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning of geranyl diphosphate synthase and compartmentation of monoterpene synthesis in plant cells</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2000</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11069698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cahoon</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ripp</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganzke</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hitz</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coughlan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic redesign of vitamin E biosynthesis in plants for tocotrienol production and increased antioxidant content</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><year>2003</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1082</fpage><lpage>1087</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated analysis of metabolite and transcript levels reveals the metabolic shifts that underlie tomato fruit development and highlight regulatory aspects of metabolic network behaviour</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2006</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>1380</fpage><lpage>1396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17071647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chander</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic dissection of tocopherol content and composition in maize grain using quantitative trait loci analysis and the candidate gene approach</article-title><source>Molecular Breeding</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>365</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Exler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eitenmiller</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tocopherol and tocotrienol contents of raw and processed fruits and vegetables in the United States diet</article-title><source>Journal of Food Composition and Analysis</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>204</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corpet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple sequence alignment with hierarchical clustering</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><year>1988</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>10881</fpage><lpage>10890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2849754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Maiti</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress in the brain of nicotine-induced toxicity: protective role of <italic>Andrographis paniculata Nees</italic> and vitamin E</article-title><source>Applied Physiology, Nutrition, and Metabolism</source><year>2009</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>135</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davuluri</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>van Tuinen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fruit-specific RNAi-mediated suppression of DET1 enhances tomato nutritional quality</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><year>2005</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>895</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajirezaei</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;rnke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnewald</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of the essential bifunctional tobacco enzyme 3-dehydroquinate dehydratase/shikimate dehydrogenase in transgenic tobacco plants</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2007</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>2053</fpage><lpage>2067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17463052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eberhard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bischoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raesecke</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrhein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of a cDNA from tomato coding for an unregulated, cytosolic chorismate mutase</article-title><source>Plant Molecular Biology</source><year>1996</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>917</fpage><lpage>922</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8806422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Locating proteins in the cell using TargetP, SignalP and related tools</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>953</fpage><lpage>971</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Enfissi</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Barneche</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrative transcript and metabolite analysis of nutritionally enhanced DE-ETIOLATED1 downregulated tomato fruit</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1190</fpage><lpage>1215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20435899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Entus</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Poling</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redox regulation of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> 3-deoxy-D-arabino-heptulosonate 7-phosphate synthase</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2002</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>1866</fpage><lpage>1871</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12177500</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An introgression line population of <italic>Lycopersicon pennellii</italic> in the cultivated tomato enables the identification and fine mapping of yield-associated QTL</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1995</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>1147</fpage><lpage>1162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8582620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Munn&#x000e9;-Bosch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tocochromanol functions in plants: antioxidation and beyond</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2010</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1549</fpage><lpage>1566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20385544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tomato Expression Database (TED): a suite of data presentation and analysis tools</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>D766</fpage><lpage>D770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaakov</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural genetic variation for improving crop quality</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16480915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugiere</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>AT_CHLORO: a comprehensive chloroplast proteome database with sub-plastidial localization and information for functional genomics using quantitative label-free analyses</article-title><source>Molecular and Celllular Proteomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1063</fpage><lpage>1084</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flowers</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sezgin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumagai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Duvernell</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Matzkin</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eanes</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive evolution of metabolic pathways in</article-title><source>Drosophila. Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1347</fpage><lpage>1354</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foyer</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Noctor</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redox homeostasis and antioxidant signaling: a metabolic interface between stress perception and physiological responses</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1866</fpage><lpage>1875</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15987996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Enfissi</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Halket</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Truesdale</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerrish</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bramley</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Manipulation of phytoene levels in tomato fruit: effects on isoprenoids, plastids and intermediary metabolism</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3194</fpage><lpage>3211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17933904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bramley</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of high-performance liquid chromatography with photodiode array detection to the metabolite profiling of plant isoprenoids</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2000</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11115136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frusciante</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Carli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ercolano</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pernice</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Matteo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fogliano</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant nutritional quality of tomato</article-title><source>Molecular Nutrition and Food Research</source><year>2007</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17427261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hssich</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Matringe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization and subcellular compartmentation of recombinant 4-hydroxyphenylpyruvate dioxygenase from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> in transgenic tobacco</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>1999</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>1507</fpage><lpage>1516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10198110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasser</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hironaka</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure, expression, and evolution of the 5-enolpyruvylshikimate-3-phosphate synthase genes of petunia and tomato</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1988</year><volume>263</volume><fpage>4280</fpage><lpage>4287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3346248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilliland</surname><given-names>LU</given-names></name><name><surname>Magallanes-Lundback</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemming</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Supplee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentsink</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dellapenna</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic basis for natural variation in seed vitamin E levels in</article-title><source>Arabidopsis thaliana. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>18834</fpage><lpage>18841</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f6;rlach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Henstrand</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Handa</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrhein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential expression of tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic> L.) genes encoding shikimate pathway isoenzymes: I. 3-deoxy-D-arabino-heptulosonate 7-phosphate synthase</article-title><source>Plant Molecular Biology</source><year>1993</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7902741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000f6;rlach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raesecke</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehrli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrhein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organ-specific differences in the ratio of alternatively spliced chorismate synthase (LeCS2) transcripts in tomato</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>1995</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7550381</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graindorge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giustini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacomin</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Curien</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Matringe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a plant gene encoding glutamate/aspartate-prephenate aminotransferase: the last homeless enzyme of aromatic amino acids biosynthesis</article-title><source>FEBS Letters</source><year>2010</year><volume>584</volume><fpage>4357</fpage><lpage>4360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20883697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NT</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Symposium Series</source><year>1999</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herbers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamin production in transgenic plants</article-title><source>Journal of Plant Physiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>821</fpage><lpage>829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12940549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000f6;rtensteiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chlorophyll degradation during senescence</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>77</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ischebeck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zbierzak</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanwischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dormann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A salvage pathway for phytol metabolism in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>2470</fpage><lpage>2477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16306049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joyard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Masselon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Seigneurin-Berny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Garin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolland</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chloroplast proteomics and the compartmentation of plastidial isoprenoid biosynthetic pathways</article-title><source>Molecular Plant</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1154</fpage><lpage>1180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19969518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez-Gomez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maloof</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence diversity in three tomato species: SNPs, markers, and molecular evolution</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biology</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>85</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19575805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamenetzky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>As&#x000ed;s</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic analysis of wild tomato introgressions determining metabolic- and yield-associated traits</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2010</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>1772</fpage><lpage>1786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20118271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The current opinions on the functions of tocopherol based on the genetic manipulation of tocopherol biosynthesis in plants</article-title><source>Journal of Integrative Plant Biology</source><year>2008</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1057</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18844774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of QTL underlying vitamin E contents in soybean seed among multiple environments</article-title><source>TAG Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source><year>2010</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>1405</fpage><lpage>1413</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livingstone</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of variation in the evolution of carotenoid biosynthetic pathway enzymes of higher plants</article-title><source>Journal of Heredity</source><year>2009</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>754</fpage><lpage>761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19520763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lois</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallego</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Carotenoid biosynthesis during tomato fruit development: regulatory role of 1-deoxy-d-xylulose 5-phosphate synthase</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2000</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10886770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rausher</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary rate variation in anthocyanin pathway genes</article-title><source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><year>2003</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1844</fpage><lpage>1853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12885963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudareva</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prephenate aminotransferase directs plant phenylalanine biosynthesis via arogenate</article-title><source>Nature Chemical Biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marwede</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gul</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping of QTL controlling tocopherol content in winter oilseed rape</article-title><source>Plant Breeding</source><year>2005</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000e8;ne-Saffran&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>DellaPenna</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis, regulation and functions of tocochromanols in plants</article-title><source>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</source><year>2009</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20036132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milone</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stegmayer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamenetzky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>*omeSOM: a software for clustering and visualization of transcriptional and metabolite data mined from interspecific crosses of crop plants</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>438</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20796314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mobley</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunkel</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification, characterization and comparative analysis of a novel chorismate mutase gene in</article-title><source>Arabidopsis thaliana. Gene</source><year>1999</year><volume>240</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>123</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moyle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reciprocal insights into adaptation from agricultural and evolutionary studies in tomato</article-title><source>Evolutionary Applications</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>421</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Skwarecki</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Buels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Menda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The SGN Comparative Map Viewer</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18202028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munn&#x000e9;-Bosch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alegre</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The function of tocopherols and tocotrienols in plants</article-title><source>Critical Reviews in Plant Sciences</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>57</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagegowda</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant volatile terpenoid metabolism: biosynthetic genes, transcriptional regulation and subcellular compartmentation</article-title><source>FEBS Letters</source><year>2010</year><volume>584</volume><fpage>2965</fpage><lpage>2973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20553718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paetzold</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Garms</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieczorek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Uros-Gracia</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Concepci&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boland</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hause</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The isogene 1-deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate synthase II controls isoprenoid profiles, precursor pathway allocation and density of tomato trichomes</article-title><source>Molecular Plant</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>904</fpage><lpage>916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20591838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterman</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohol</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>McReynolds</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patellin1, a novel Sec14-like protein, localizes to the cell plate and binds phosphoinositides</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2004</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>3080</fpage><lpage>3094</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Auria</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichersky</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> type I isopentenyl diphosphate isomerases are targeted to multiple subcellular compartments and have overlapping functions in isoprenoid biosynthesis</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>696</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18319397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravanel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherest</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jabrin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunwald</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Surdin-Kerjan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Douce</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebeille</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tetrahydrofolate biosynthesis in plants: molecular and functional characterization of dihydrofolate synthetase and three isoforms of folylpolyglutamate synthetase in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>1523</fpage><lpage>1535</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rippert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Scimemi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubald</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matringe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Engineering plant shikimate pathway for production of tocotrienol and improving herbicide resistance</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2004</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14684842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rippert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Puyaubert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grisollet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Derrier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Matringe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tyrosine and phenylalanine are synthesized within the plastids in</article-title><source>Arabidopsis. Plant Physiology</source><year>2009</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>1251</fpage><lpage>1260</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahumada</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Diez-Juez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauret-G&#x000fc;eto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lois</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallego</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Carretero-Paulet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>1-Deoxy-D-xylulose 5-phosphate reductoisomerase and plastid isoprenoid biosynthesis during tomato fruit ripening</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2001</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11532167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Concepci&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Querol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lois</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Imperial</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boronat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioinformatic and molecular analysis of hydroxymethylbutenyl diphosphate synthase (GCPE) gene expression during carotenoid accumulation in ripening tomato fruit</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2003</year><volume>217</volume><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12721677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohdich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wungsintaweekul</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;ttgen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenreich</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuhr</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fellermeier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schramek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenk</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of terpenoids: 4-diphosphocytidyl-2-C-methyl-d-erythritol kinase from tomato</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>8251</fpage><lpage>8256</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ronen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmel-Goren</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirschberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An alternative pathway to &#x003b2;-carotene formation in plant chromoplasts discovered by map-based cloning of <italic>Beta</italic> and <italic>old-gold</italic> color mutations in tomato</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>11102</fpage><lpage>11107</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ros</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuts and novel biomarkers of cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>American Journal of Clinical Nutrition</source><year>2009</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1649S</fpage><lpage>1656S</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19321561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadre</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Frentzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of homogentisate prenyltransferases involved in plastoquinone-9 and tocochromanol biosynthesis</article-title><source>FEBS Letters</source><year>2006</year><volume>580</volume><fpage>5357</fpage><lpage>5362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16989822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tautz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mustelin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The lipid-binding SEC14 domain</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source><year>2007</year><volume>1771</volume><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17428729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Semel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Balbo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinfath</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Repsilber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Selbig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pleban</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mode of inheritance of primary metabolic traits in tomato</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18364465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Semel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Roessner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive metabolic profiling and phenotyping of interspecific introgression lines for tomato improvement</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><year>2006</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>454</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic profiling of leaves and fruit of wild species tomato: a survey of the <italic>Solanum lycopersicon</italic> complex</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15596477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leibinger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Boll</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Amrhein</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>in-vitro</italic> synthesized tomato shikimate kinase precursor is enzymatically active and is imported and processed to the mature enzyme by chloroplasts</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>1992</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1338949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schelbert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanwischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000f6;rmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;rtensteiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The chlorophyllases At CLH1 and AtCLH2 are not essential for senescence-related chlorophyll breakdown in</article-title><source>Arabidopsis thaliana. FEBS Letters</source><year>2007</year><volume>581</volume><fpage>5517</fpage><lpage>5525</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semchuk</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lushchak</surname><given-names>OV</given-names></name><name><surname>Falk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupinska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lushchak</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inactivation of genes, encoding tocopherol biosynthetic pathway enzymes, results in oxidative stress in outdoor grown</article-title><source>Arabidopsis thaliana. Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</source><year>2009</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>390</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sokal</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohlf</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biometry</source><year>1981</year><edition>Second Edition</edition><comment>Freeman, New York</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of geranylgeranyl and phytyl substituted methylquinols in the tocopherol synthesis of spinach chloroplasts</article-title><source>Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications</source><year>1979</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">526275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zybailov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Majeran</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Friso</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Olinares</surname><given-names>PDB</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wijk</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PPDB, the Plant Proteomics Database at Cornell</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><year>2009</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>969</fpage><lpage>974</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0</article-title><source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1596</fpage><lpage>1599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><year>1994</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4673</fpage><lpage>4680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>DellaPenna</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pds2 mutation is a lesion in the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homogentisate solanesyltransferase gene involved in plastoquinone biosynthesis</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2007</year><volume>226</volume><fpage>1067</fpage><lpage>1073</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17569077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tohge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combining genetic diversity, informatics and metabolomics to facilitate annotation of plant gene function</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1210</fpage><lpage>1227</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Traber</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamin E in humans: demand and delivery</article-title><source>Annual Review of Nutrition</source><year>1996</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>347</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib89"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Malitsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Galili</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of a bacterial bi-functional chorismate mutase/prephenate dehydratase modulates primary and secondary metabolism associated with aromatic amino acids in</article-title><source>Arabidopsis. The Plant Journal</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>167</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib90"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Galili</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights into the shikimate and aromatic amino acids biosynthesis pathways in plants</article-title><source>Molecular Plant</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>956</fpage><lpage>972</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20817774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valentin</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Moshiri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The <italic>Arabidopsis vitamin E pathway gene5-1</italic> mutant reveals a critical role for phytol kinase in seed tocopherol biosynthesis</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16361393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib92"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Schie</surname><given-names>CCN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ament</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Haring</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuurink</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geranyl diphosphate synthase is required for biosynthesis of gibberellins</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2007</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17877699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voorrips</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MapChart: software for the graphical presentation of linkage maps and QTLs</article-title><source>Journal of Heredity</source><year>2002</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib94"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PAML 4: a program package for phylogenetic analysis by maximum likelihood</article-title><source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1586</fpage><lpage>1591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib95"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary rate patterns of the gibberellin pathway genes</article-title><source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19689796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib96"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving plant breeding with exotic genetic libraries</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>989</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib97"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Greater vegetable and fruit intake is associated with a lower risk of breast cancer among Chinese women</article-title><source>International Journal of Cancer</source><year>2009</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>188</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib98"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Last</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunological characterization and chloroplast localization of the tryptophan biosynthetic enzymes of the flowering plant Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><fpage>6081</fpage><lpage>6087</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7890741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib99"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Candidate gene identification approach: progress and challenges</article-title><source>International Journal of Biological Sciences</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17998950</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>