<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5181584</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27856709</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erw411</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association mapping reveals the genetic architecture of tomato response to water deficit: focus on major fruit quality traits</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>Elise</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>Vincent</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gricourt</surname><given-names>Justine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bonnefoi</surname><given-names>Julien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Derivot</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>Mathilde</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><sup>1</sup><institution>INRA</institution>, <addr-line>UR1052, G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique et Am&#x000e9;lioration des Fruits et L&#x000e9;gumes, 67 All&#x000e9;e des Ch&#x000ea;nes, Centre de Recherche PACA, Domaine Saint Maurice, CS60094, Montfavet, 84143</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="AF0002"><sup>2</sup><institution>INRA</institution>, <addr-line>UR0588, Am&#x000e9;lioration, G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique et Physiologie Foresti&#x000e8;res, 2163 Avenue de la Pomme de Pin, Centre de Recherche Val de Loire, CS 40001, Orl&#x000e9;ans, 45075</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="AF0003"><sup>3</sup><institution>GAUTIER Semences</institution>, <addr-line>route d&#x02019;Avignon, Eyragues, 13630</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">* Correspondence: <email>Mathilde.Causse@paca.inra.fr</email></corresp><fn id="fn0001" fn-type="other"><p>Editor: Ariel Vicente, CONICET-National University of La Plata</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>67</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>6413</fpage><lpage>6430</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="precis"><title>Highlight</title><p>Tomato quality could be improved under deficit irrigation while maintaining yield. The underlying genetic architecture is polygenic and varies with water availability. Candidate genes related to primary metabolism were identified.</p></abstract><abstract><p>Water scarcity constitutes a crucial constraint for agriculture productivity. High-throughput approaches in model plant species identified hundreds of genes potentially involved in survival under drought, but few having beneficial effects on quality and yield. Nonetheless, controlled water deficit may improve fruit quality through higher concentration of flavor compounds. The underlying genetic determinants are still poorly known. In this study, we phenotyped 141 highly diverse small fruit tomato accessions for 27 traits under two contrasting watering conditions. A subset of 55 accessions exhibited increased metabolite contents and maintained yield under water deficit. Using 6100 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), association mapping revealed 31, 41, and 44 quantitative trait loci (QTLs) under drought, control, and both conditions, respectively. Twenty-five additional QTLs were interactive between conditions, emphasizing the interest in accounting for QTLs by watering regime interactions in fruit quality improvement. Combining our results with the loci previously identified in a biparental progeny resulted in 11 common QTLs and contributed to a first detailed characterization of the genetic determinants of response to water deficit in tomato. Major QTLs for fruit quality traits were dissected and candidate genes were proposed using expression and polymorphism data. The outcomes provide a basis for fruit quality improvement under deficit irrigation while limiting yield losses.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key words:</title><kwd>Acid and vitamin C content</kwd><kwd>candidate genes</kwd><kwd>drought</kwd><kwd>fleshy fruit quality</kwd><kwd>genotype by environment interaction</kwd><kwd>GWA</kwd><kwd>QTL</kwd><kwd><italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic></kwd><kwd>sugar.</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="18"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Global water scarcity will constitute a crucial challenge in the coming years (<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Jury and Vaux, 2005</xref>). Agriculture, which is consuming up to 80% of the worldwide water resources through irrigation, has to move towards a more sustainable use of water (<xref rid="CIT0082" ref-type="bibr">Rost <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>). Utilization of advanced irrigation strategies and development of drought-adapted crops are among the solutions to solve this dilemma (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Fereres and Soriano, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Costa <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Beyond these concerns, deficit irrigation practices constitute a way to manage fruit flavor by exploiting the morphological, physiological, and molecular changes (referred to as &#x02018;phenotypic plasticity&#x02019;) occurring in water-stressed plants (<xref rid="CIT0081" ref-type="bibr">Ripoll <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Under water deficit, plants close their stomata to limit transpiration, impacting resource availability from photosynthetic sources, which may result in a decrease in number and/or size of the fruits. On the other hand, a mild water deficit tends to shift photo-assimilate partitioning towards synthesis of antioxidant compounds (in particular vitamin C) involved in defense against stress-induced reactive oxygen species and compatible solutes (including sugars and acids) involved in osmotic adjustment (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Lemoine <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Albacete <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">Osorio <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Evidence for the efficiency of deficit irrigation to concentrate the major flavor and nutritional components in fleshy fruits (mainly sugars, acids, and antioxidants), either by a concentration or an accumulation effect, was obtained in many species such as tomato (<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Kirda <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0109" ref-type="bibr">Zheng <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), grapevine (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Chaves <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>), apple (<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Leib <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), and mango (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Dur&#x000e1;n Zuazo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). However, these studies focused on a small number of genotypes, while responses to deficit irrigation seem to be highly genotype dependent (<xref rid="CIT0079" ref-type="bibr">Ripoll <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016a, b</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Gene expression studies have revealed hundreds of genes involved in plant survival under severe water limitation, but usually associated with detrimental effects on yield under a realistic drought scenario (<xref rid="CIT0097" ref-type="bibr">Tardieu, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Bac-Molenaar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). These studies focused on model species, mainly <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0092" ref-type="bibr">Seki <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Des Marais <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) and cereals (<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">Langridge, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Barnabas <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). Up to now, the identification of the genetic determinants of drought response from the natural diversity of fleshy fruit crops remains limited. Quantitative trait locus (QTL) mapping might be particularly valuable to address this question (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Des Marais <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Two complementary approaches are commonly applied to dissect genotype by environment interactions into their underlying QTLs (QTL by environment interactions). The first one consists of computing the effects of a given QTL across the environmental conditions using multivariate QTL mapping models (<xref rid="CIT0100" ref-type="bibr">van Eeuwijk <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">El-Soda <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014<italic>b</italic>
</xref>). The second one uses the construction of composite variables measuring phenotypic plasticity and univariate mapping models (<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">El-Soda <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014<italic>a</italic>
</xref>). With both approaches, QTLs can be classified according to the prevalence of their effect under the different conditions. A QTL is considered &#x02018;constitutive&#x02019; when its effect is conserved whatever the environment. QTLs whose effect is not significant in every environment are called &#x02018;specific&#x02019;, while the effect of &#x02018;interactive&#x02019; QTLs changes direction (&#x02018;antagonist&#x02019;) or intensity (&#x02018;differential&#x02019;) according to the environment. With the availability of a high-throughput genotyping assay, this classification can be considered in crop species via conventional linkage mapping (<xref rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr">Malosetti <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0101" ref-type="bibr">Verbyla <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) as well as genome-wide association studies (GWASs) (<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Korte <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0086" ref-type="bibr">Sa&#x000ef;dou <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). A GWAS has the advantage over linkage mapping that it allows exploration of the genetic diversity and the numerous recombination events present in germplasm collections and may lead to higher resolution mapping if the LD (linkage disequilibrium) is low enough in the population (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Brachi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Korte and Farlow, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">El-Soda <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">Pascual <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">In tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> L.), QTLs were mapped for fruit quality traits measured under optimal watering conditions using linkage (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Causse <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0087" ref-type="bibr">Saliba-Colombani <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0098" ref-type="bibr">Tieman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0108" ref-type="bibr">Zanor <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009<italic>b</italic>
</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Capel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) and association mapping (<xref rid="CIT0106" ref-type="bibr">Xu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr">Ruggieri <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0090" ref-type="bibr">Sauvage <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0085" ref-type="bibr">Sacco <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). The studies of QTLs by water regime interactions focused on introgression lines between the cultivated tomato and its wild relatives (mainly <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> and <italic>S. pennellii</italic>), leading to low mapping resolution (<xref rid="CIT0093" ref-type="bibr">Semel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Gur <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Arms <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Recently, we analyzed QTLs by watering regime interaction in a segregating population derived from a cross between a small- and a large-fruited <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> accession (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Albert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). A total of 56 QTLs were identified for 19 traits, among which 20% were interactive between the control and deficit watering regimes. Nevertheless, these QTLs were limited to the allelic diversity present in the two parental accessions, and the confidence intervals were broad.</p><p content-type="indent">The aims of the present study were (i) to explore the pattern of genotype by watering regime interaction in a GWAS panel with a broad genetic basis (including <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic>, <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> var. <italic>cerasiforme</italic>, and admixture genotypes) grown under two different watering regimes in two locations and phenotyped for 27 traits; (ii) to identify with a high resolution QTLs and QTL by watering regime interactions in this collection; (iii) to combine the results with those obtained in the bi-parental progeny to draw an accurate picture of the genetic variability and the genetic determinants of tomato response to water deficit; and (iv) to identify candidate genes related to the variation of major fruit quality traits under water deficit by dissecting some of the QTLs.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s3"><title>Plant material</title><p>The population consisted of 141 accessions (2&#x02013;46 g FW) encompassing the genetic diversity of the cultivated small fruit tomato. Among these, 105 accessions were previously investigated in <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">Blanca <italic>et al.</italic> (2015)</xref>. Preliminary genetic analysis of our collection confirmed the genetic structure described by these authors, with clusters reflecting the species and the geographic origin of the accessions (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1A&#x02013;D</ext-link> at <italic>JXB</italic> online). Ten accessions were <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> (SP; closest wild ancestor of the tomato) originating from Peru and Ecuador. A total of 110 accessions were <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> var. <italic>cerasiforme</italic> (SLC) originating mainly from South America. Finally, 21 accessions belonged to a mixed genetic group mainly including commercial cherry tomatoes and admixed genotypes between SP, SLC, and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> var. <italic>lycopersicum</italic>. A description of the accessions and their origin is available in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>. The genetic groups (SLC, SP, and mixture) are used below in the statistical analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Experimental design</title><p>The plants were cultivated with the same experimental design as in <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Albert <italic>et al.</italic> (2016)</xref>. Plants were grown in a heated glasshouse in INRA Avignon (Avi, France) from March to July 2014 and in an unheated plastic greenhouse on the experimental site of the seed company GAUTIER Semences in Agadir (Aga, Morocco) from December 2013 to March 2014. Two watering regimes were applied to the plants: control (C) and drought (D). The control treatment was set according to ET (evapotranspiration) and the cultural coefficient for tomato under greenhouse conditions (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">FAO Water, 2015</xref>). A maximal drainage of 25% and a relative humidity of the substrate of 65% were established in the control pots. Drought treatment was applied progressively after flowering of the second truss of the earliest accession. Watering was first reduced by 25% compared with the control for 1 week and then reduced by 60% until the end of the experiments. Relative humidity of the peat substrate was controlled with GRODAN<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> moisture probes and monitored between 25% and 30% in drought pots. In both experiments, two plants per watering regime per accession were randomized in the greenhouse.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Plant and fruit phenotyping</title><p>A total of 27 traits were assessed in the GWA population as described in <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Albert <italic>et al.</italic> (2016)</xref>. Flowering date (Flw, days after sowing), stem diameter (Diam, mm), leaf length (Leaf, cm), and truss implantation height (Ht, cm) were measured on each plant both in Avignon (sixth truss) and in Agadir (fifth truss). Plant fruit number (Nbfruits, all fruits from the third to sixth truss) was measured only in Avignon.</p><p content-type="indent">Fruit quality measurements were carried out on a minimum of 20 mature fruits per accession per watering regime harvested daily on the third to the sixth truss. All the fruits were weighed (FW, g) and their firmness was measured with a Durofel device (FIR). Only in Avignon, fruits were pooled in three groups in each watering regime. Half of the fruits of each pool were used to assess dry matter weight (DMW, %), pH, and soluble solid content (SSC, &#x000b0;Brix). From the second half of the fruit replicates, pericarps were crushed in liquid nitrogen and assayed for total vitamin C content (VitCFM) according to the microplate method described in <xref rid="CIT0096" ref-type="bibr">Stevens <italic>et al.</italic> (2006)</xref>, for sugar content (glucose and fructose) according to the enzymatic method described in <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Gomez <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>, and for organic acid content (malic and citric) according to the HPLC method reported in <xref rid="CIT0105" ref-type="bibr">Wu <italic>et al.</italic> (2002)</xref>. The different metabolite concentrations were expressed relative to fresh matter (g 100 g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> of FM) and relative to dry matter (g 100 g<sup>&#x02013;1</sup> of DM). Yield (g per plant) was computed by multiplying average fruit FW by average fruit number per plant.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Plant genotyping and SNP filtering</title><p>The GWA population was genotyped using the Tomato Infinium Array developed within the SolCAP project (<uri xlink:href="http://solcap.msu.edu/">http://solcap.msu.edu/</uri>) (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Hamilton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Sim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). The maximum rates of missing data were fixed at 25% per accessions and 10% per SNP. A minor allele frequency threshold of 0.04 was applied to discard markers with very rare alleles according to <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Aulchenko <italic>et al.</italic> (2007)</xref>. After filtering, the set of markers was constituted of 6100 SNPs. Prior to any genetic analysis, the remaining missing genotypes were replaced by the allele frequency of the major allele. The SNPs were renamed according to their positions on the tomato genome (SL2.50), as S01_58000085 at base pair 58 000 085 on chromosome 1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S2</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Statistical analysis of the phenotypic data</title><p>All statistical analyses were performed using R (<xref rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr">R Development Core Team, 2012</xref>). Because fewer and different traits were measured in Agadir experiments, data from both locations were analysed separately (Pearson correlations for the common trait means available in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S4</ext-link>&#x02014;all significant). Prior to the ANOVAs and when distributions were skewed, phenotypic data were normalized using Box and Cox transformations. The ANOVAs were performed according to the following model:</p><disp-formula><mml:math id="equation1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000b5;</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mtext>j</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><p>
<italic>Y</italic>
<sub><italic>ijkl</italic></sub> was the phenotypic value of accession <italic>j</italic> from genetic group <italic>i</italic> in watering regime <italic>k</italic>, &#x000b5; the overall mean, <italic>Gr</italic>
<sub><italic>i</italic></sub> the fixed effect of genetic group <italic>i</italic>, <italic>Gr</italic>
<sub><italic>i</italic></sub>(<italic>G</italic>
<sub><italic>j</italic></sub>) the fixed effect of accession <italic>j</italic> nested in genetic group <italic>i</italic>, <italic>W</italic>
<sub><italic>k</italic></sub> the fixed effect of watering regime <italic>k</italic>, and <italic>e</italic>
<sub><italic>ijkl</italic></sub> the residual error effect. No significant microenvironment pattern was identified and we chose not to include any spatial effect in the model. When the interaction <italic>Gr</italic>&#x000d7;<italic>W</italic> was significant, we computed a Tukey&#x02019;s post-hoc test to compare the means.</p><p content-type="indent">Then, in both watering regimes, restricted maximum likelihood estimates of the genetic and residual variances (&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<sub>G</sub> and &#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<sub>e</sub>) were computed with a second linear model: <italic>Y</italic>
<sub><italic>ijk=</italic></sub>&#x000b5;<italic>+Gr</italic>
<sub><italic>i</italic></sub>
<italic>+Gr</italic>
<sub><italic>i</italic></sub>(<italic>G</italic>
<sub><italic>j</italic></sub>)<italic>+e</italic>
<sub><italic>ijk</italic></sub> (<italic>Gr</italic>
<sub><italic>j</italic></sub> fixed, <italic>G</italic>
<sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>e</italic>
<sub><italic>ijk</italic></sub> random). Broad-sense heritabilities (<italic>H</italic>
<sup>2</sup>) were calculated under both watering regimes as the ratio between the genetic variance and the total phenotypic variance: <italic>H</italic>
<sup>2</sup>=&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<sub>G</sub>/&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<sub>Total</sub>, with &#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<sub>Total</sub>=&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<sub>G</sub>+1/<italic>n</italic>&#x000d7;&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<italic>e</italic> (with <italic>n</italic> the number of replicates per accession). Spearman coefficients estimated the correlations between <italic>H</italic>
<sup>2</sup> and &#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<sub>G</sub> under drought and control conditions for the same trait.</p><p content-type="indent">Average values per accession in each watering regime and location were used for subsequent analyses. Plasticity was computed on the accession means as: <italic>&#x02206;ki</italic>=(<italic>D</italic>
<sub><italic>ki</italic></sub>
<italic>&#x02013;C</italic>
<sub><italic>ki</italic></sub>)<italic>/C</italic>
<sub><italic>ki</italic></sub>, with &#x02206;<italic>ki</italic> the plasticity value for trait <italic>k</italic> and accession <italic>i</italic>, <italic>D</italic>
<sub><italic>ki</italic></sub> the mean of trait <italic>k</italic> under drought condition for accession <italic>i</italic>, and <italic>C</italic>
<sub><italic>ki</italic></sub> the mean of trait <italic>k</italic> under control condition for accession <italic>i.</italic>
</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>Construction of kinship and structure matrices</title><p>We performed a principal co-ordinate analysis (PCoA) on the genotype matrix. The co-ordinates of the accessions on the first three components are available in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S3</ext-link> and displayed graphically in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link>. A kinship matrix (K) based on identity by state among the 6100 SNPs was estimated.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>GWA mapping</title><p>Average values for each trait following the transformation giving the least skewed distribution were used in the mapping models. GWASs were performed using correction for population structure (PCoA) and modeling genetic variance with the kinship matrix (K). Two mixed models were implemented.</p><p content-type="indent">First, the bivariate multitrait mixed model (MTMM) developed by <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Korte <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> to take into account the correlation structure of multienvironment data sets and increase the detection power was implemented. The MTMM approach includes two different tests: (i) the &#x02018;global test&#x02019; compared a model including only the genotype effect with a null model to identify markers with common effect between watering regimes (&#x02018;constitutive QTLs&#x02019;); and (ii) the &#x02018;G&#x000d7;W test&#x02019; compared a full model with a model including only the genotype effect to identify markers with an interactive effect between the watering conditions (&#x02018;interactive QTLs&#x02019;). SNPs with a <italic>P</italic>-value &#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup> were considered as significant. From each test, the percentage of variation explained by the marker (individual PVE for each significant marker) was computed.</p><p content-type="indent">Secondly, the univariate multilocus mixed model (MLMM) developed by <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Segura <italic>et al.</italic> (2012)</xref> to increase the detection power for polygenic characters was used to identify associations for each trait under each watering regime (&#x02018;specific QTLs&#x02019;) and for the &#x02206; values (&#x02018;interactive QTLs&#x02019;). We implemented a new model selection criterion in the MLMM framework to allow for a more permissive detection threshold to compromise between type I (false-positive) and type II (false-negative) errors, while limiting the number of cofactors selected to avoid overestimation of the <italic>P</italic>-values due to the relatively small size of the population. Models with a maximum of five cofactors all having a raw <italic>P</italic>-value &#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup> were retained. From the optimal model selected, the percentage variation explained by the selected markers (global PVE for all the significant markers) was computed for each trait.</p><p content-type="indent">For all the QTLs identified, we computed phenotypic effects under both watering conditions as: (Minor allele mean&#x02212;Major allele mean)/2. Among the interactive QTLs, we distinguished between &#x02018;antagonist QTLs&#x02019; (effect changing direction according to the watering regime) and &#x02018;differential QTLs&#x02019; (effect changing intensity according to the watering regime).</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>Linkage disequilibrium estimation and confidence interval definition</title><p>To define intervals around QTLs, we used a strategy based on LD between pairs of markers inspired from <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Cormier <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref>. We used the <italic>r</italic>
<sup>2</sup> estimator implemented in the package &#x02018;genetics&#x02019; (<xref rid="CIT0104" ref-type="bibr">Warnes and Leisch, 2012</xref>) to assess LD between marker pairs. First, we performed LD calculation between 100 000 randomly chosen pairs of unlinked loci (on different chromosomes). The 95th percentile of the unlinked-<italic>r</italic>
<sup>2</sup> distribution equal to 0.28 was considered as the critical LD threshold. Then, for each significant marker, we computed LD with all the markers upstream and downstream on the same chromosome. We defined the lower (upper) boundary of the interval as the last marker downstream (upstream) on the chromosome that presented an LD with the significant marker above the &#x02018;critical LD&#x02019; threshold. For the QTLs detected with the MTMM procedure, when two markers presented a LD higher than the LD threshold, we considered them as a unique QTL. The number of genes within each interval was identified from the tomato genome (ITAG2.4).</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>Comparison between linkage and association QTLs and identification of candidate genes</title><p>For the comparison with the QTLs detected in the recombinant inbred lines (RILs) grown under the same conditions and phenotyped for the same traits (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Albert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>), we projected the QTLs detected in both populations onto the tomato genome (SL2.50). In the comparison, we considered related traits as a single trait: pH, malic acid, and citric acid contents were grouped as &#x02018;acids&#x02019;, and SSC, glucose, and fructose contents as &#x02018;sugars&#x02019;. Besides, whatever the QTL type (&#x02018;interactive&#x02019;, &#x02018;constitutive&#x02019;, or &#x02018;specific&#x02019;) and the location of the trial, we considered that a single QTL was present when the intervals overlapped between RIL and GWA QTLs.</p><p content-type="indent">We then focused on the QTLs for vitamin C, sugar, and acid content including &#x0003c;100 genes to identify putative candidate genes with a reasonable confidence. Under those QTLs, we refined the set of candidates by selecting the genes expressed in tomato fruits according to gene expression data published by the <xref rid="CIT0099" ref-type="bibr">Tomato Genome Consortium (2012)</xref>. Then, we examined their functional annotations and focused on genes with annotations corresponding to related functions. Finally, we screened the polymorphism data obtained through the whole-genome resequencing of four accessions of our GWA population chosen to represent a large range of the molecular variability present in small fruit tomato (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Causse <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>): Cervil (13.3&#x000d7; sequence depth), Criollo (8.1&#x000d7;), LA1420 (12.5&#x000d7;), and Plovdiv (12.2&#x000d7;). First, we considered the nucleotide variants with moderate (non-synonymous polymorphisms in coding regions) to high (modification of splice sites or start/stop codons) effect on the protein sequence (detected using SnpEff; <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">Cingolani <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Then, the predicted impacts of the variants on the protein function were assessed using the web interfaces of PROVEAN (<uri xlink:href="http://provean.jcvi.org/seq_submit.php">http://provean.jcvi.org/seq_submit.php</uri>) (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Choi and Chan, 2015</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s12"><title>Results</title><sec id="s13"><title>Dissection of the phenotypic variations in the GWA population</title><p>In the variance analysis, the part of the total variation attributed to the genotype effect was predominant (35&#x02013;80%, all <italic>P</italic>-values &#x0003c;0.001) compared with the one attributed to the genetic group (0&#x02013;15%, all <italic>P</italic>-values &#x0003c;0.05) and the watering regime (0&#x02013;28%, significant for 17 traits), except for leaf length in Agadir and stem diameter in Avignon and Agadir (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S5</ext-link>). For those vigour traits, the watering regime represented 48&#x02013;61% of the total variation.</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Dissection of the total phenotypic variation. For each phenotypic trait, the top figure displays the proportion of each effect in the total sum of squares: green for watering regime (<italic>W</italic>); dark blue for genetic group (<italic>Gr</italic>); light blue for genotype nested in genetic group [<italic>Gr</italic>(<italic>G</italic>)]; black for the interaction genetic group by watering regime (<italic>Gr</italic>&#x000d7;<italic>W</italic>); gray for the interaction genotype by watering regime [<italic>Gr</italic>(<italic>G</italic>)&#x000d7;<italic>W</italic>], and yellow for the residual. The table shows the significance of the <italic>P</italic>-value for the different effects: ***<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001, **<italic>P</italic>=0.001&#x02013;0.01, *<italic>P</italic>=0.01&#x02013;0.05, and ns &#x0003e;0.05. &#x02018;H2 C&#x02019; and &#x02018;H2 D&#x02019; indicate the broad-sense heritabilities in control and drought conditions, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw411_f0001"/></fig><p content-type="indent">The genetic group by watering regime interactions represented &#x0003c;2% of the total sum of squares for all traits and was non-significant for 12 traits. The eight significant traits were Diam.Aga, Leaf.Avi, Leaf.Aga, Ht.Avi, FW.Avi, FW.Aga, FIR.Aga, and VitCFM.Avi. Tukey&#x02019;s post-hoc test indicated that these interactions were mainly driven by a singular behavior of the SP group in response to water deficit (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S2</ext-link>). In contrast, the genotype by watering regime interaction represented 1&#x02013;19% of the total variation and was significant for all traits, except Flw.Avi, DMW.Avi, pH.Avi, and MalicFM.Avi. Interaction partitioning according to method 1 from <xref rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr">Muir <italic>et al.</italic> (1992)</xref> indicated that the genotype by watering regime interactions were mainly due to accessions re-ranking across watering regimes (80&#x02013;100%) and in a minor way to scale changes (0&#x02013;20%, data not shown). The broad-sense heritabilities ranged from 30% for FructoseFM.Avi.D to 92% for FW.Avi.C. These values were correlated across watering regimes (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>H</sub>
<sup>2</sup>=0.80), as well as the genetic variances (<italic>r</italic>
<sub>&#x003c3;</sub>
<sup>2</sup>
<sub>G</sub>=0.99), confirming genotype re-ranking across watering regimes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1"> Supplementary Table S5</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s14"><title>Impact of the water deficit on fruit quality and yield components</title><p>The RIL and GWA populations were grown in Avignon and Agadir in separate greenhouse trials over the years 2013 and 2014, while ensuring similar watering conditions (control and drought) (see <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Albert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref> for details concerning the RILs). On average, in both locations, water deficit impacted plant and fruit traits in the same direction in the GWA and RIL populations, with a decline in plant vigor, a decrease in yield, and a higher concentration of the metabolites in fruits (as a percentage of FM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Table 1</xref>). However, when applying the drought treatment, FW.Avi was decreased 2-fold and Nbfruits.Avi 9-fold in the RILs (FW.Avi, &#x02013;37.7%; Nbfruits, &#x02013;21.7%) compared with the GWA accessions (FW.Avi, &#x02013;19.0%; Nbfruits, &#x02013;2.5%). It resulted in a yield decrease reaching the level of &#x02013;50% in the RILs against &#x02013;20% in the GWA accessions. On the other hand, SSC, DMW, and VitCFM were more strongly enhanced in the RILs (SSC, +26.3%; DMW, +30.7%; and VitCFM, +26.3%) than in the GWA accessions (SSC, +12.6%; DMW, +11.4%; and VitCFM, +12.7%).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Average relative difference between control and drought conditions for the fruit and plant traits measured in the GWA and RIL populations (%)</p><p>The average relative differences were computed as: (Mean <sub>Drought</sub>&#x02013;Mean <sub>Control</sub>)/Mean <sub>Control</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw411_t0001"/></fig><p content-type="indent">The correlation between fruit FW in control conditions (indicator of fruit size) and &#x02206;FW was strongly negative in the GWA accessions (Avi, <italic>r</italic>= &#x02013;0.55, <italic>P</italic>=2.70 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;12</sup>; Aga, <italic>r</italic>= &#x02013;0.52, <italic>P</italic>=2.65 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;10</sup>), as was previously noted in the RILs. This indicated greater FW loss in larger fruited accessions under drought and increased metabolite contents resulting mainly from the reduced amount of water in the fruits. Thus, the differences observed between the populations may mostly reflect differences in fruit size, with larger fruits among the RILs (8&#x02013;61 g, mean=20 g, SD=9 g) compared with the GWA accessions (2&#x02013;46 g, mean=13 g, SD=10 g). Nevertheless, a larger range of variation was observed among the GWA accessions for &#x02206;Yield.Avi and &#x02206;Nbfruits.Avi compared with the RILs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Figs S3</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">S4</ext-link>). In particular, 55 accessions exhibited an increased yield under drought in the GWA population against only two among the RILs. No noticeable geographic origin or genetic group was obvious among these 55 accessions of the GWA population (10 mixture, 43 SLC, and 2 SP).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Impact of water deficit on yield, fruit number, fruit FW, and soluble solid content (SSC) in fruit. (A) and (B) Histograms of yield plasticity (&#x02206;Yield) in the GWA and RIL populations, respectively. (C) and (D) Relationship between plasticity of fruit number (&#x02206;Nbfruits) and plasticity of SSC (&#x02206;SSC), in view of FW plasticity (&#x02206;FW), in the GWA and RIL populations, respectively. In the bottom figures, the color scale indicates the variation in FW plasticity: blue for values below &#x02013;0.5, purple for values between &#x02013;0.25 and 0, magenta for values between 0 and 0.25, and red for values &#x0003e;0.5. The size of the points is proportional to the FW in control watering conditions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw411_f0002"/></fig><p content-type="indent">When plotting &#x02206;Nbfruits against &#x02206;SSC in regard to fruit size and &#x02206;FW.Avi, the RIL and GWA plants presented different patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Among the RILs, only 18 accessions were present in the top right quarter of the plot corresponding to accessions with increased SSC and Nbfruits under water deficit. Besides, all the top right quarter RILs had a negative &#x02206;FW.Avi (blue and purple color) meaning a decreased FW under drought compared with the control condition for these accessions. On the other hand, 40% of the GWA accessions were present in the top right quarter of the plot and six of them had a positive &#x02206;FW.Avi (magenta and red color) and small to medium fruit size (FW in control from 2 g to 28 g). Similar figures were obtained when considering fruit ascorbate (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S5</ext-link>), malic acid, and citric acid contents (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S6</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="s15"><title>QTL and QTL by watering regime interactions identified by association mapping</title><p>The MTMM mapping approach detected 53 unique associations for 15 out of 27 phenotyped traits in the GWA population with <italic>P</italic>-values &#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup> and percentages of variation explained varying from 5.45% to 18.22% (individual PVE per marker) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S6</ext-link>). A total of 49 associations were &#x02018;constitutive&#x02019; irrespective of the watering regime. Among these associations, the most significant were observed for malic acid content, with <italic>P</italic>-values comprised between 2.40 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;6</sup> and 1.33 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;13</sup> in the global test (chromosomes 6 and 7) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S7</ext-link>). Four associations were declared &#x02018;interactive&#x02019; between the watering regimes, two for Flw.Avi (chromosomes 9 and 11) and two for GlucoseDM.Avi (chromosomes 4 and 5), with <italic>P</italic>-values ranging from 1.48 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup> to 7.04 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Focus on QTLs detected for fruit quality traits at the bottom of chromosome 4. (A) Manhattan plot displaying the &#x02013;log10(<italic>P</italic>-values) (<italic>y</italic>-axis) over genomic positions (<italic>x</italic>-axis) in a window of 1.46 Mbp corresponding to the common confidence interval of QTLs detected for VitCDM.Avi (MLMM control condition, blue), GlucoseDM.Avi (MTMM GxW test, purple), GlucoseFM.Avi (MLMM &#x02206;, red), and pH.Avi (MLMM control, green) on chromosome 4 in the GWA population. <italic>P</italic>-values &#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup> were considered as significant (4 in logit values). The pairwise LD heatmap was drawn using the R package &#x02018;snp.plotter&#x02019; (<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">Luna and Nicodemus, 2007</xref>). (B) Box-plot of the allelic effects for the four associated markers: S04_65828262 (VitCDM, &#x02018;control specific&#x02019;), S04_65907012 (GlucoseFM, &#x02018;antagonist&#x02019;), S04_65908608 (GlucoseDM, &#x02018;antagonist&#x02019;), and S04_6630772 (pH, &#x02018;control specific&#x02019;). Blue: allelic effects under control conditions. Red: allelic effects under drought conditions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw411_f0003"/></fig><p content-type="indent">The MLMM approach identified a total of 124 associations (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c;1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup>) for the 27 studied phenotypic traits. Among them, 94 associations were &#x02018;specific&#x02019; (39 and 55 to drought and control conditions, respectively), 23 &#x02018;interactive&#x02019; (detected on &#x02206; values) and seven &#x02018;constitutive&#x02019; (detected under both conditions; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Tables S7</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">S8</ext-link>). The explained percentages of phenotypic variation ranged from 8.16% (one SNP for Leaf.Aga.C) to 63.85% (six SNPs for SSC.Avi.D) (global PVE for all the significant markers for a trait). Constitutive and/or specific associations were observed for all the traits. The most significant <italic>P</italic>-values were associated ith MalicFM.Avi.D (S06_44955568: 1.88 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;19</sup>), MalicDM.Avi.D (S06_44955568: 1.27 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;17</sup>), pH.Avi (S04_66307772: 9.95 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;11</sup>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>), and SSC.Avi.C (S10_64149793: 5.96 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;10</sup>). The 23 interactive SNPs were associated with 11 out of 27 traits. Their <italic>P</italic>-values ranged from 7.59 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup> (&#x02206;Flw.Avi: S06_36868039) to 2.75 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;11</sup> (&#x02206;FW.Aga: S11_50391249, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S8</ext-link>).</p><p content-type="indent">When gathering the associations obtained with MLMM and MTMM, 20 associations were detected in common (same trait and same QTL type), resulting in a total of 157 associations for the 27 traits (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Tables S6&#x02013;S8</ext-link>). Sixteen associations were detected between twice and three times with related traits (&#x02018;acid&#x02019; and &#x02018;sugar&#x02019; traits) and/or for the same trait in the two locations. Thus, a total of 141 different associations were identified, spread unevenly over the genome (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>
<bold>).</bold> Chromosomes carried out six (chromosomes 7 and 8) to 23 associations (chromosome 2; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S7</ext-link>). Thirty percent of the associations were &#x02018;constitutive&#x02019; (44/141), 30% were &#x02018;control specific&#x02019; (41/141), 22% were &#x02018;drought specific&#x02019; (31/141), and 17% were &#x02018;interactive&#x02019; (25/141). Among the interactive associations, 16 showed &#x02018;differential&#x02019; effects (effect intensity changing according to watering regime) whereas nine presented &#x02018;antagonist&#x02019; effects (effect direction changing according to watering regime). Up to 14, 24, and 28 different associations were mapped for vitamin C, &#x02018;acid&#x02019;, and &#x02018;sugar&#x02019; content in fruit, respectively.</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Description of QTLs detected for plant and fruit traits in the GWA population through association mapping and comparison with those detected in the RIL population through linkage analysis</p><p>QTLs detected in the GWA population were classified according to their type. QTLs significant under both watering regimes are referred to as &#x02018;constitutive&#x02019;. QTLs significant under one watering regime only (&#x02018;control&#x02019; or &#x02018;drought&#x02019;) are designated as &#x02018;specific&#x02019;. QTLs detected with the plasticity data and/or with the interaction test are designated as &#x02018;interactive&#x02019;. For each phenotypic trait and each QTL type, the number of QTLs, minimum and maximum confidence interval (CI in Mbp on genome assembly v2.5) and minimum and maximum number of genes in the interval are displayed. We considered related traits as a single trait: pH, acid malic (DM and FM), and acid citric (DM and FM) were grouped in &#x02018;acids&#x02019;, as well as SSC, glucose (DM and FM), and fructose (DM and FM) in &#x02018;sugars&#x02019;. We gathered QTLs detected in both trial locations (Agadir and Avignon) for the same trait. For the comparison with the RIL population (results described in Albert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016), whatever the QTL type, we considered that a single QTL was present when the CI overlapped between RIL and GWA QTLs.</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trait</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Constitutive QTL</th><th align="left" colspan="10" rowspan="1">Specific QTL</th><th align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Interactive QTL</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">
</th><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Control</th><th align="left" colspan="5" rowspan="1">Drought</th><th align="left" colspan="6" rowspan="1">
</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nb QTL total</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Nb</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min&#x02013;Max CI (Mpb)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min&#x02013;Max no. of genes</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Com. RIL</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Nb</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min&#x02013;Max CI (Mpb)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min&#x02013;Max no. of genes</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Com. RIL</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Nb</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min&#x02013;Max CI (Mpb)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min&#x02013;Max No. of nes</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Com. RIL</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Nb</italic> ant.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Nb</italic> diff.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LG</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min&#x02013;Max CI (Mpb)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min&#x02013;Max no. of genes</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Com. RIL</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="23" rowspan="1">
<bold>Plant traits</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Flw</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#x02013;0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02013;117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4; 5; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00&#x02013;59.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;1653</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4<sup><italic>a</italic></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 6; 9; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06&#x02013;16.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x02013;94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diam</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">336</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2; 5; 6; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14&#x02013;3.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16&#x02013;500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2; 4; 9; 12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02&#x02013;36.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;600</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2; 5; 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02&#x02013;12.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;516</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 2; 3; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03&#x02013;45.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;1147</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2; 4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50&#x02013;4.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">232&#x02013;463</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#x02013;9.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;284</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ht</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 2; 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22&#x02013;32.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#x02013;720</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4<sup><italic>b</italic></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2; 3; 7; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10&#x02013;5.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#x02013;140</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nbfruits</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4;7;;11;12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34-50.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40-741</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9;10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28-7.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97-819</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="23" rowspan="1">
<bold>Fruit traits</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FW</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2<sup><italic>b</italic></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2; 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07&#x02013;1.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 - 250</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">677</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 10; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23&#x02013;56.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02013;1287</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FIR</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6<sup><italic>b</italic></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 2; 5; 6; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02&#x02013;32.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;858</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 2; 3; 5; 9; 12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04&#x02013;48.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02013;928</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4; 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04&#x02013;65.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;2573</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VitC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8; 9; 10; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15&#x02013;8.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02013;899</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4; 7; 9; 12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27&#x02013;41.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02013;796</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 2; 4; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#x02013;4.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x02013; 494</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DMW</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#x02013;0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;137</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sugars</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9<sup><italic>c</italic></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4; 5; 7; 8; 9; 10; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07&#x02013;59.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18&#x02013;1602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3; 9; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#x02013;3.34</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;417</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 4; 6; 10; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03&#x02013;2.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02013;327</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 2; 4; 5; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04&#x02013;59.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#x02013;1602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acids</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11<sup><italic>c</italic></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5; 6; 7; 8; 9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00&#x02013;2.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;289</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2; 3; 4; 6; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00-0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;137</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1; 4; 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04&#x02013;0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2; 4; 10; 11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09&#x02013;64.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#x02013;2427</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yield</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>141</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>44</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>41</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>31</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>16</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Com. RIL</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-05" fn-type="other"><p>
<sup>a</sup> Indication of interactive QTLs confirmed with both plasticity data and interaction test.</p></fn><fn id="fn-06" fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic>b</italic></sup> Indication of QTLs confirmed in both locations, Agadir and Avignon (with the same type: &#x02018;constitutive&#x02019;, &#x02018;specific&#x02019;, or &#x02018;interactive&#x02019;).</p></fn><fn id="fn-07" fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic>c</italic></sup> Indication of QTLs for acids and sugars confirmed with several measurement methods (pH and acid content, SSC and sugar content).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s16"><title>Confidence intervals and candidate gene selection under QTLs for fruit quality traits</title><p>We observed large differences in size and number of underlying genes when drawing confidence intervals around the association peaks. Eighteen QTLs mapped around the weakly recombinant centromeres covered &#x0003e;10 Mbp and included between 410 and 2573 genes, whereas 84 QTLs covered &#x0003c;5.5 Mbp and encompassed between one and 97 genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S9</ext-link>). In the RILs grown in the same conditions (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Albert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>), only four QTLs covered &#x0003c;100 genes on a total of 56 QTLs. The comparison of the QTL positions between the RIL and GWA populations resulted in a total of 11 QTLs common to both populations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>), whereas 45 were specific to the RILs and 130 to the GWA population (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S10</ext-link>).</p><p content-type="indent">To propose putative candidate genes, we focused on QTLs for vitamin C, sugar, and acid contents in fruit including &#x0003c;100 genes (42 among 66 QTLs) and selected in their intervals genes showing expression in the fruits according to the data from the <xref rid="CIT0099" ref-type="bibr">Tomato Genome Consortium (2012)</xref>. This reduced the gene list to screen for between one and 87 genes depending on the QTL intervals. Annotations were analyzed to identify genes with functions related to vitamin C, sugar, or acid metabolism under &#x02018;constitutive&#x02019; QTLs and functions related to primary metabolism and/or defense against abiotic stress under &#x02018;specific&#x02019; and &#x02018;interactive&#x02019; QTLs. A total of 41 putative candidates were proposed for three &#x02018;constitutive&#x02019; QTLs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>) and 15 &#x02018;interactive&#x02019; or &#x02018;specific&#x02019; QTLs (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>). Of those genes, 22 were reported to have DNA polymorphisms in the four accessions of our GWA population which were re-sequenced by <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Causse <italic>et al.</italic> (2013)</xref>. The polymorphisms in four of those genes were predicted to change the amino acids, affecting biological function of a protein.</p><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Putative candidate genes in the confidence interval around constitutive GWA QTLs for vitamin C, sugar. and acid content in fruit.We focused on QTLs encompassing &#x0003c;100 genes. Comparisons with the QTLs detected in Albert <italic>et al.</italic> (2016) (RIL under control and drought conditions) and Pascual <italic>et al.</italic> (2016) (MAGIC, RIL, and GWA populations under control conditions) for related traits are indicated. For each QTL, significant marker(s), confidence interval (CI), number of genes in the interval, and among them the number of genes which are expressed in the tomato fruits according to gene expression data published by the Tomato Genome Consortium (2012) are indicated. Putative candidate genes are proposed on the basis of their expression in the fruit, their functional annotation, and the scientific literature. &#x02018;Variants&#x02019; displays the number of moderate (non-synonymous polymorphisms in coding regions) to high (modification of splice sites or start/stop codons) effect polymorphisms identified from the resequencing of four accessions of the GWA population (Causse <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013). Variants which have a deleterious impact on the protein structure according to PROVEAN are indicated by &#x02018;#&#x02019;.</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QTL(s)<sup><italic>a</italic></sup>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QTL type</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Co-loc. Albert <italic>et al.</italic> (2016) and Pascual <italic>et al.</italic> (2016)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marker(s)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI (Mbp)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of genes</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of genes expressed in fruit</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative candidate genes and annotations</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Related functions</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-syn. variants</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>MalicDM.Avi_6.3</italic>; <italic>MalicFM.Avi_6.3</italic></bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>C and D</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>MAGIC+GWA</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>S06_44955568</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>44.92&#x02013;44.96</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>Solyc06g072910: aluminum-activated malate transporter-like</italic></bold>
<sup><bold><italic>b</italic></bold></sup>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Carbon metabolism and malate compartmentation</bold> (Martinoia and Rentsch, 1995; Sauvage <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>Solyc06g072920: aluminum-activated malate transporter-like</italic></bold>
<sup><bold><italic>b</italic></bold></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>GlucoseDM.Avi_7.1</italic>; <italic>MalicDM.Avi_7.2</italic>; <italic>MalicFM.Avi_7.2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">C and D</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">MAGIC+GWA</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">S07_64878195; S07_65079667</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">64.86&#x02013;65.60</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">97</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g062530: Phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malic and citric acid accumulation (Guillet <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1#</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g062650: malate dehydrogenase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carbon metabolism and malate compartmentation (Martinoia and Rentsch, 1995)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>FructoseDM.Avi_10.2</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>C and D</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>NO</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>S10_63163119</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>63.10&#x02013;63.24</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>18</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>16</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc10g083290: beta-fructofuranosidase insoluble isoenzyme 2 (Lin6</bold>)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Sugar metabolism</bold> (Fridman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004; Proels and Roitsch, 2009; Ruan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010; Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc10g083300: beta-fructofuranosidase insoluble isoenzyme 2 (Lin8</bold>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-08" fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic>a</italic></sup> QTL names make reference to the map representation in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S7</ext-link>. They are in underlined when they were identified with <italic>P</italic>-values &#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup>.</p></fn><fn id="fn-09" fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic>b</italic></sup> Genes poorly expressed in the fruit.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Putative candidate genes in the confidence interval around specific and interactive GWA QTLs for vitamin C, sugar and acid content in fruit</p><p>We focused on QTLs encompassing &#x0003c;100 genes. Comparisons with the QTLs detected in Albert <italic>et al.</italic> (2016) (RIL under control and drought conditions) and Pascual <italic>et al.</italic> (2016) (MAGIC, RIL, and GWA populations under control conditions) for related traits are indicated. For each QTL, significant marker(s), confidence interval (CI), number of genes in the interval, and among them number of genes which are expressed in the tomato fruits according to gene expression data published by the Tomato Genome Consortium (2012) are indicated. Putative candidate genes are proposed on the basis of their expression in the fruits, their functional annotation, and the scientific literature. &#x02018;Variants&#x02019; displays the number of moderate (non-synonymous polymorphisms in coding regions) to high (modification of splice sites or start/stop codons) effect polymorphisms identified from the resequencing of four accessions of the GWA population (Causse <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013). Variants which have a deleterious impact on the protein structure according to PROVEAN are indicated by &#x02018;#&#x02019;.</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QTL(s)*</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QTL type</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Co-loc. Albert <italic>et al.</italic> (2016) and Pascual <italic>et al.</italic> (2016)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Marker(s)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CI (Mbp)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of genes</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of genes expressed in fruit</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative candidate genes and annotations</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Related functions</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-syn. variants</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">CitricDM.Avi_1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RIL</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S01_86174739</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.15&#x02013;86.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g094720: vesicular glutamate transporter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen transporter (Rentsch <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>VitCDM.Avi_1.1</italic></bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>D</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>NO</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>S01_93702068</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>93.47&#x02013;93.76</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>42</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>36</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g105340: chaperone protein dnaJ</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Protein protection</bold> (Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g105540: 2-oxoglutarate/malate translocator</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Carbon metabolism and malate compartmentation</bold> (Martinoia and Rentsch, 1995)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g105630: calmodulin</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Osmotic adjustment and stress signaling in interaction with cellular calcium</bold> (Perruc <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004; Reddy <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSC_Avi_1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAGIC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S01_96226845</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.22&#x02013;96.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc01g109220: mitochondrial import receptor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxidative stress (Frank <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1#</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>FructoseDM.Avi_1.1</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>ant.</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MAGIC</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>S01_97877551</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>97.43&#x02013;97.99</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>79</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>61</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g111280: cold shock protein-1</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Protein protection under salt and drought stress</bold> (Kim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g111300: cold shock protein-1</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g111320: thaumatin-like protein</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Sweet-tasting protein, sugar accumulation and plant defense</bold> (Kim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002; Petre <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g111330: thaumatin-like protein</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g111510: Ascorbate peroxidase</bold>
<break/>
<bold>Solyc01g111510: Ascorbate peroxidase</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g111510: ascorbate peroxidase</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Oxidative stress</bold> (Pignocchi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g111630: glyoxylate/hydroxypyruvate reductase B</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Recycling fatty acids into glucose</bold> (Cornah <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g111680: ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme 22</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Osmotic adjustment and oxidative stress response</bold> (Zhou <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g111660: aquaporin-like protein</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Water and solute transport, osmotic adjustment</bold> (Reuscher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013; Ricardi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc01g111750: heat shock protein dnaJ</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Oxidative stress, fruit maturation</bold> (Banzet <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998; Neta-Sharir <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<italic>SSC.Avi_2.2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">dif.</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">MAGIC+RIL+GWA</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">S02_40059311</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">40.02&#x02013;40.11</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g070270: amino acid transporter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g070280: amino acid transporter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc02g070290: potassium/chloride transporter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>pH.Avi_2.3</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>dif.</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MAGIC+RIL+GWA</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>S02_49491595</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>49.40&#x02013;49.50</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc02g086820: carbonic anhydrase</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Enhanced photosynthesis under drought</bold> (Gu <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<italic>FructoseDM.Avi_4.1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">NO</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">S04_03214865</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">3.05&#x02013;3.22</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g009770: DNAJ chaperone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein protection (Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc04g009830: stress responsive gene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene regulation under abiotic stress (Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>MalicDM.Avi_4.1</italic></bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>D</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>NO</bold>
<break/>
<bold>NO</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>S04_03821452</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>3.64&#x02013;4.10</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>31</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>26</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc04g010330:auxin-regulated protein</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Abiotic stress signaling</bold> (Bianchi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002; Gong <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3#</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc04g011440: heat shock protein</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Oxidative stress, fruit maturation</bold> (Banzet <italic>et al.</italic>, 1998; Neta-Sharir <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc04g011450: heat shock cognate protein 2</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">GlucoseFM.Avi_6.1</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">NO</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">S06_38712034</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">38.34&#x02013;38.73</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">36</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g060360: universal stress protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gene regulation under abiotic stress (Chen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g060370: organic anion transporter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc06g060620: nitrate transporter</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrogen transport (Rentsch <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>FructoseFM.Avi_6.1</italic></bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>D</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>NO</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>S06_42161946</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>42.00&#x02013;42.20</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>28</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>19</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc06g066820: gibberellin 3-beta-hydroxylase</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Water status and reduced transpiration</bold> (Nir <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VitCFM.Avi_7.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NO<break/>-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S07_02439123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.29&#x02013;2.56</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc07g007790: sucrose phosphate synthase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sugar compartmentation, sink strength (Nguyen-Quoc and Foyer, 2001)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>SSC.Avi_9.1</italic></bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>C</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>MAGIC+RIL+GWA</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>S09_03477979</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>0.34&#x02013;0.35</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>2</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc09g010080: beta-fructofuranosidase, insoluble isoenzyme 1 (Lin5</bold>)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">
<bold>Sugar metabolism, heat and drought tolerance</bold> (Fridman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004; Zanor <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009<italic>a</italic>; Ruan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010; Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc09g010090: beta-fructofuranosidase insoluble isoenzyme 2 (Lin7</bold>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VitCFM.Avi_10.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">dif.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NO<break/>-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S10_00934508</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#x02013;0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc10g006130: ethylene responsive TrF</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abiotic stress signaling (Pan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>FructoseDM.Avi_10.1</italic></bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>D</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>NO</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>S10_60291460</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>60.12&#x02013;60.37</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>31</bold>
</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">
<bold>30</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc10g078370: auxin efflux carrier</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Abiotic stress signaling</bold> (Bianchi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002; Gong <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc10g078490: aquaporin</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Water and solute transport, osmotic adjustment</bold> (Reuscher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013; Ricardi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Solyc10g078560: chaperone protein dnaJ</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein protection (Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1#</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>FructoseFM.Avi_11.3</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAGIC</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">S11_52838456</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.80&#x02013;52.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Solyc11g067050: neutral invertase</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sugar metabolism, heat and drought tolerance (Ruan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010; Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-10" fn-type="other"><p>
<sup><italic>a</italic></sup> QTL names make reference to the map representation in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S7</ext-link>. They are in underlined when they were identified with <italic>P</italic>-values &#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p content-type="indent">From the 18 dissected QTLs, &#x02018;SSC.Avi_9.1&#x02019; (control specific) probably corresponded to the cloned QTL &#x02018;Brix9.2.5&#x02019; controlling SSC in fruit and associated with a polymorphism in a cell wall invertase gene (Solyc09g010080: Lin5) (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Fridman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>). A second QTL (&#x02018;Malic.Avi_6.3&#x02019;) co-localized with a previously mapped QTL for acid content in fruit in different tomato populations and for which two &#x02018;aluminum-activated malate transporter-like&#x02019; genes (Solyc06g072910 and Solyc06g072920) were pointed out as putative candidate genes by <xref rid="CIT0090" ref-type="bibr">Sauvage <italic>et al.</italic> (2014)</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). Although these two genes presented promising polymorphisms between our four re-sequenced accessions, they displayed a very low expression in fruit (<xref rid="CIT0099" ref-type="bibr">Tomato Genome Consortium, 2012</xref>; personal data) and will need further validation to be clearly associated with the phenotypes.</p><p content-type="indent">Ten QTLs co-localized with loci identified in the RILs (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Albert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>, control and drought conditions) and/or in the three tomato population analyzed by <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr">Pascual <italic>et al.</italic> (2016)</xref> (RIL, GWA, and MAGIC, control conditions) but for which no candidate gene was proposed until now, while six were present in genomic regions where, to the best of our knowledge, no QTLs for related traits were mapped thus far. In the intervals of four of them, controlling vitamin C and fructose content in a drought-specific manner (&#x02018;<italic>VitCDM.Avi_1.1</italic>&#x02019;, &#x02018;<italic>FructoseDM.Avi_4.1</italic>&#x02019;, and &#x02018;<italic>FructoseDM.Avi_10.1</italic>&#x02019;), three genes coding for &#x02018;<italic>chaperone proteins dnaJ</italic>&#x02019; were identified (Solyc01g105340, Solyc04g009770, and Solyc10g078560; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>). Five more genes coding for &#x02018;<italic>heat/cold shock proteins</italic>&#x02019; (Solyc01g111280, Solyc01g111300, Solyc01g111750, Solyc04g011440, and Solyc04g011450) were identified under antagonist and drought-specific QTLs for fructose and malic acid content (&#x02018;<italic>FructoseDM.Avi_1.1</italic>&#x02019; and &#x02018;<italic>MalicDM.Avi_4.1</italic>&#x02019;; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table 4</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Three constitutive QTLs, the first two on chromosome 7 controlling glucose and malic acid content and the third on chromosome 10 controlling fructose content, seemed particularly promising. The first two (&#x02018;<italic>GlucoseDM.Avi_7.2</italic>&#x02019; and &#x02018;<italic>Malic.Avi.7_2</italic>&#x02019; in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>) shared a common interval including a gene coding for a &#x02018;<italic>phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase</italic>&#x02019; (Solyc07g062530: PEPC) and a gene coding for a &#x02018;<italic>malate dehydrogenase</italic>&#x02019; (Solyc07g062650). The PEPC gene presented a non-synonymous polymorphism with a predicted impact on the protein function when comparing the four re-sequenced accessions. The third one (&#x02018;FructoseDM.Avi_10.2&#x02019; in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>) contained two genes coding for &#x02018;<italic>cell wall invertases</italic>&#x02019;, Lin6 (Solyc10g083290) and Lin8 (Solyc10g083300), presenting three non-synonymous polymorphisms between the re-sequenced accessions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s17"><title>Discussion</title><p>To assess the extent of natural variation in tomato responses to water deficit, we phenotyped a collection of 141 small fruit accessions for plant and fruit traits, under control and drought conditions. Using 6100 SNPs genotyped over the genome, we achieved association mapping using univariate and bivariate mixed models. QTLs, QTL by watering regime interactions, and putative candidate genes were identified. This study, in combination with the results reported in RILs grown under the same watering conditions, contributed to a first detailed characterization of the genetic variations and genomic determinants of response to water deficit in tomato.</p><sec id="s18"><title>Improving fruit quality while maintaining yield in tomato under water limitation</title><p>Deficit irrigation strategies aiming to reduce non-beneficial water consumption while maximizing fruit quality and minimizing yield losses are studied in horticultural production to address environmental issues and market expectations simultaneously. It seems particularly relevant for tomato since consumers complain about lack of taste in the new varieties (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Bruhn <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Causse <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). In our trials, after a decrease in 60% of the water supply throughout plant growth, we observed on average reduced plant vigor and yield, while fruit quality was improved or stable depending on whether metabolite concentrations were expressed relative to FM or DM. This antagonistic relationship between quality and yield performances confirmed the results obtained in RILs (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Albert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) and the tendencies reported by other authors in tomato (<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Guichard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Kirda <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0109" ref-type="bibr">Zheng <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), peach (<xref rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr">Mir&#x000e1;s-Avalos <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>), or grapevine (<xref rid="CIT0088" ref-type="bibr">Santesteban and Royo, 2006</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Nevertheless, 50 accessions (with small to medium fruit size) had both improved fruit quality and maintained yield (or even improved) under water deficit compared with the control watering regime, although their vigor (measured through leaf length and stem diameter) was decreased. These accessions emphasized the opportunity to increase metabolite content in tomato fruits using deficit irrigation without achieving parallel limitation of the yield. In contrast, no RIL presented such a response to the water deficit treatment, and the increased sugar and acid contents observed reflected mainly concentration effects due to a decreased amount of water in fruit (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Albert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">The large phenotypic variations observed mainly resulted from genotype effects (35&#x02013;80%) and less from genotype by watering regime interactions (1&#x02013;19%). The watering regime effect represented a significant part of the total phenotypic variability (up to 40%) only for stem diameter and leaf length. This suggests that tomato plants buffer the negative effect of water limitation by limiting their vegetative growth and reallocating the photo-assimilates to the fruits (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Lemoine <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr">Osorio <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s19"><title>Benefits and limits of GWA to dissect the genetic architecture of response to water deficit in tomato</title><p>Association studies aiming to identify alleles whose effects are modulated by environmental conditions are still few in plants. To date, such studies were only reported in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Li <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr">Morrison and Linder, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">El-Soda <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0089" ref-type="bibr">Sasaki <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), and maize (<xref rid="CIT0086" ref-type="bibr">Sa&#x000ef;dou <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Explicitly accounting for &#x02018;QTL by environment interactions&#x02019; in QTL studies can help to discover novel genes that act synergistically with the environment, potentially leading to the identification of superior genotypes according to the environments (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Des Marais <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">We identified a total of 141 QTLs with low to medium effects. The phenotyped traits were strongly polygenic and justified the use of a multilocus GWA mapping model (MLMM: <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Segura <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). In particular, up to 14, 24, and 28 different QTLs were identified for vitamin C, acid, and sugar content, respectively. Among the loci identified, 51% were specific to one watering condition, 31% were constitutive and detected whatever the condition, and 18% were interactive between the watering conditions. These proportions of QTL types are relatively similar to those reported in the RILs grown in the same conditions (<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Albert <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>) and in the study of <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Gur <italic>et al.</italic> (2011)</xref> on tomato introgression lines. However, while most of the interactive QTLs identified in the RILs presented antagonist effects, a majority of differential effects was observed in the GWA study. These discrepancies between both populations may reflect their different genetic basis: the RILs segregate between a small- and a large-fruited accession, whereas the GWA collection focuses on the polymorphisms between several diverse small-fruited accessions.</p><p content-type="indent">Because of the large number of markers to be used in GWA analysis, it is not straightforward to choose an appropriate significance threshold controlling for false positives while maintaining the statistical power. We thus opted for a lowered threshold of 10<sup>&#x02013;4</sup>. If we used Bonferroni correction usually applied to exclude false positives, we should have used a significance threshold of 10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup>. This would reduce the number of associations detected to 69 (nine &#x02018;interactive&#x02019;, 44 &#x02018;specific&#x02019;, and 16 &#x02018;constitutive&#x02019;). With this stringent threshold, we would not have recovered some well-described tomato QTLs, such as, for example, FW11.2 and FW11.3 on chromosome 11 (fruit FW QTLs: <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Huang and van der Knaap, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Illa-Berenguer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). The need for more permissive thresholds in GWASs is often claimed. Strategies based on enrichment tests using known candidate genes from the literature to evaluate the false-positive rate and choose the appropriate threshold values are proposed (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Atwell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0089" ref-type="bibr">Sasaki <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). However, these approaches are limited to well-annotated model genomes and simple traits with already well-described genetic architecture. Another solution to solve the multiple testing issues could be to use haplotypes instead of individual markers to minimize the number of tests, especially in species where the LD spans large genomic regions (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Bader, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr">McClurg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>). This has already been successfully applied in crops (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Gawenda <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) and would be worth testing in tomato, but may need more markers to identify haplotypes correctly.</p><p content-type="indent">The projection of the QTL intervals onto the physical map of tomato allowed the comparison of QTL positions between the RIL and GWA population even though they were genotyped with different markers. This projection resulted in a total of 11 QTLs conserved between both populations. On the other hand, 45 were specific to the RIL population and 130 to the GWA population. This may seem like a relatively small number of common QTLs between the populations, but the RIL parental accessions reflected only a limited fraction of the genetic variation present in the GWA population.</p></sec><sec id="s20"><title>Searching for candidate genes under QTLs for fruit quality traits</title><p>Our approach, combining linkage and association mapping, was powerful in recovering previously identified loci associated with fruit quality. As an example, we mapped a QTL associated with fruit fructose content on chromosome 9 which included in its interval the gene Lin5 (Solyc09g010080) known to encode a cell wall invertase affecting tomato fruit sugar content (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Fridman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). Apart from recovering previously described genes, we identified QTLs in genomic regions where QTLs associated with related traits were previously identified in other populations but for which no candidate gene was proposed until now (probably because of too large confidence intervals) or in genomic regions where, to the best of our knowledge, no QTL was reported for related traits thus far. The confidence intervals around the association peaks obtained using an LD-based approach were mostly shorter (1&#x02013;97 genes for 84 intervals) compared with the intervals obtained using the RILs or introgression lines (<xref rid="CIT0093" ref-type="bibr">Semel <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Gur <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Arms <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>).</p><p content-type="indent">Combining publicly available expression data (<xref rid="CIT0099" ref-type="bibr">Tomato Genome Consortium, 2012</xref>), exonic variants gained from re-sequencing of four accessions of the GWA collection (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Causse <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) and functional analysis of the gene annotations in the confidence intervals, we proposed 41 putative candidate genes under three constitutive QTLs and 15 interactive or specific QTLs. Under the interactive and specific QTLs, genes related to protein protection (chaperone and heat/cold shock proteins), water and solute transport (aquaporins and others transporters), sugar metabolism (sucrose phosphate synthase and invertases), and hormonal signaling (auxin, gibberellin, and ethylene) were identified and may play a crucial role in responses to water deficit (<xref rid="CIT0103" ref-type="bibr">Wang <italic>et al.</italic>, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="CIT0094" ref-type="bibr">Shinozaki and Yamaguchi-Shinozaki, 2007</xref>). Some of them presented polymorphisms with predicted impacts on the protein function when comparing the re-sequenced accessions and constitute promising targets for future functional validations.</p><p content-type="indent">On the bottom of chromosome 7, two QTLs, controlling glucose and malic acid content, shared a common interval including a gene coding for a &#x02018;phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase&#x02019; (PEPC) and a gene coding for a &#x02018;malate dehydrogenase&#x02019;. The PEPC gene presented a non-synonymous polymorphism with a predicted impact on the protein function in the four re-sequenced accessions. As the PEPC is catalyzing the carboxylation of the phosphoenolpyruvate arising from glycolysis into oxaloacetate which is then converted into malate by the malate dehydrogenase or enters the Krebs cycle (<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Guillet <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002</xref>), this gene constitutes a likely candidate. Nevertheless, although if the &#x02018;malate dehydrogenase&#x02019; gene did not present any exonic SNPs in our data, it remains an interesting candidate as our four re-sequenced accessions probably did not represent the full genetic diversity present in the GWA population, and the phenotypic variations observed may result from regulation change more than modifications of the protein. On the bottom of chromosome 10, a QTL interval controlling fructose content contained two genes coding for &#x02018;cell wall invertases&#x02019; (Lin6 and Lin8). Both genes presented non-synonymous polymorphisms between the re-sequenced accessions. In contrast to Lin5 on chromosome 9, Lin6 and Lin8 have not yet been associated with variation in sugar content in fruit. Cell wall invertases are extracellular hydrolases which cleave sucrose to glucose and fructose, which are then transported into the cell. They play a central role in regulating, amplifying, and integrating different signals that lead to the source&#x02013;sink transition in plants.</p><p content-type="indent">Subsequent analyses based on either fine mapping around the candidate genes using target re-sequencing approach or functional validation, for example by genome editing, could clarify the involvement of these genes in the phenotypic variations observed.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s21"><title>Supplementary data</title><p>Supplementary data are available at <italic>JXB</italic> online</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Fig. S1</ext-link>. Structuration observed in the GWA population ba<bold>s</bold>ed on principal co-ordinate analysis (PCoA) on data of 6100 SNPs.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Fig. S2</ext-link>. Box-plot of the mean distribution for the nine traits that showed a significant genetic group by watering regime interaction in the ANOVAs.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Fig. S3</ext-link>. Distribution of the accession means for plant traits in the GWA population grown under two watering regimes..</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Fig. S4</ext-link>. Distribution of the accession means for fruit traits in the GWA population grown under two watering regimes.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Fig. S5</ext-link>. Relationship between plasticity of fruit number and plasticity of vitamin C content in fruit, in view of the fruit FW plasticity, in the GWA and RIL populations, respectively.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Fig. S6</ext-link>. Relationship between plasticity of fruit number and plasticity of citric and malic acid content in fruit (relative to FW), in view of the fruit FW plasticity, in the GWA population.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Fig. S7</ext-link>. Physical map of the QTLs detected in the GWA and RIL populations.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Fig. S8</ext-link>. Example of co-localizations between GWA and RIL QTLs for soluble solid content and fruit FW on the bottom of chromosome 11.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Fig. S9</ext-link>. Confidence interval (CI) sizes and numbers of genes underlying the QTLs in the GWA and RIL populations.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Fig. S10</ext-link>. Venn diagram representing common QTLs between the RIL population (linkage mapping) and the GWA population (association mapping).</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Table S1</ext-link>. Genetic and phenotypic description of the accessions in the GWA population.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Table S2</ext-link>. Genotypic data in the GWA population.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Table S3</ext-link>. Principal co-ordinates analysis in the GWA population.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Table S4</ext-link>. Correlations between Avignon and Agadir trials.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Table S5</ext-link>. Effect of watering regime (<italic>W</italic>), genetic group (<italic>Gr</italic>), genotype nested in genetic group [<italic>Gr</italic>(<italic>G</italic>)] and the interactions [<italic>Gr</italic>&#x000d7;<italic>W</italic> and <italic>Gr</italic>(<italic>G</italic>)&#x000d7;<italic>W</italic>] on the plant and fruit traits measured in the GWA population.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Table S6</ext-link>. QTLs identified under both watering regimes (&#x02018;Control&#x02019; and &#x02018;Drought&#x02019;) using the bivariate multitrait mixed model (MTMM) genome-wide association mapping approach.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Table S7</ext-link>. QTLs identified under each watering regime (&#x02018;Control&#x02019; and &#x02018;Drought&#x02019;) using the univariate multilocus mixed model (MLMM) genome-wide association mapping approach.</p><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw411/-/DC1">Table S8</ext-link>. QTLs identified for plasticity data each [(Drought&#x02013;Control)/Control] using the univariate multilocus mixed model (MLMM) genome-wide association mapping approach.</p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Data</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_67_22_6413__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_erw411_Supplementary_Figures_S1_S6_S8_S10_Supplementary_Table_S4.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"
xlink:href="supp_erw411_Supplementary_figure_S7.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"
xlink:href="supp_erw411_Supplementary_Tables_S1_S3_S5_S8.xlsx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We acknowledge the experimental teams of UR-GAFL and Gautier SEMENCES for their collaboration in implementing the experimentations. We particularly thank Yolande Carretero, Esther Pelpoir, Romain Novaretti, Doriane Bancel, and the employees of &#x02018;Domaine Margau&#x02019; (Agadir) for their help in phenotyping. Thanks to Christopher Sauvage for proofreading and script sharing. The CTPS project TOMSEC supported this work. EA was supported by an INRA PhD fellowship. EA conducted experiments in France, analyzed data, and wrote the manuscript. VS developed scripts for the GWA mapping. JG sampled and collected phenotypic data in France. JB and LD supervised sample collection and phenotypic measurements in Morocco. MC supervised the project, built the experimental design, and revised the manuscript. All authors discussed the results and commented on the manuscript. The authors declare no conflict of interest in the authorship and publication of this document.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albacete</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-And&#x000fa;jar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Alfocea</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Hormonal and metabolic regulation of source&#x02013;sink relations under salinity and drought: from plant survival to crop yield stability</article-title>. <source>Biotechnology Advances</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>12</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24513173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gricourt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonnefoi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pateyron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamby</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bitton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Genotype by watering regime interaction in cultivated tomato: lessons from linkage mapping and gene expression</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>129</volume>, <fpage>395</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>418</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26582510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arms</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>St Clair</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>High-resolution mapping of a major effect QTL from wild tomato Solanum habrochaites that influences water relations under root chilling</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>1713</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1724</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26044122</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Atwell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilhj&#x000e1;lmsson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide association study of 107 phenotypes in a common set of Arabidopsis thaliana inbred lines</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>465</volume>, <fpage>627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>631</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20336072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aulchenko</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isaacs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Duijn</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>GenABEL: an R library for genome-wide association analysis</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1294</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17384015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bac-Molenaar</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Granier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Keurentjes</surname><given-names>JJB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vreugdenhil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide association mapping of time-dependent growth responses to moderate drought stress in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>88</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>The relative power of SNPs and haplotype as genetic markers for association tests</article-title>. <source>Pharmacogenomics</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11258193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Banzet</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richaud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deveaux</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kazmaier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Triantaphylid&#x000e8;s</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Accumulation of small heat shock proteins, including mitochondrial HSP22, induced by oxidative stress and adaptive response in tomato cells</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>527</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9680997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnabas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The effect of drought and heat stress on reproductive processes in cereals</article-title>. <source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Damerval</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vartanian</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Identification of proteins regulated by cross-talk between drought and hormone pathways in Arabidopsis wild-type and auxin-insensitive mutants, axr1 and axr2</article-title>. <source>Functional Plant Biology</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blanca</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Montero-Pau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauvage</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauchet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Illa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>D&#x000ed;ez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Knaap</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ca&#x000f1;izares</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Genomic variation in tomato, from wild ancestors to contemporary breeding accessions</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25880392</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brachi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Faure</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Flahauw</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vazquez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordborg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergelson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cuguen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Linkage and association mapping of Arabidopsis thaliana flowering time in nature</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genetics</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e1000940</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20463887</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruhn</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garlitz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ivans</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thurber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Consumer perceptions of quality: apricots, cantaloupes, peaches, pears, strawberries and tomatoes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Food Quality</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>195</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Capel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez del Carmen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Wide-genome QTL mapping of fruit quality traits in a tomato RIL population derived from the wild-relative species Solanum pimpinellifolium L</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>2019</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2035</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26163766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desplat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Whole genome resequencing in tomato reveals variation associated with introgression and breeding events</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>791</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24228636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Friguet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coiret</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>LePicier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Navez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Holthuysen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinesio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moneta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grandillo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Consumer preferences for fresh tomato at the European scale: a common segmentation on taste and firmness</article-title>. <source>Journal of Food Science</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>S531</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S541</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21535628</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saliba-Colombani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lesschaeve</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Genetic analysis of organoleptic quality in fresh market tomato. 2. Mapping QTLs for sensory attributes</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>283</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortu&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Maroco</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Deficit irrigation in grapevine improves water-use efficiency while controlling vigour and production quality</article-title>. <source>Annals of Applied Biology</source>
<volume>150</volume>, <fpage>237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>252</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>A nucleotide metabolite controls stress-responsive gene expression and plant development</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>e26661</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22028934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>PROVEAN web server: a tool to predict the functional effect of amino acid substitutions and indels</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>2745</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2747</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25851949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cingolani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Coon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Land</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruden</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>A program for annotating and predicting the effects of single nucleotide polymorphisms, SnpEff: SNPs in the genome of Drosophila melanogaster strain w 1118; iso-2; iso-3</article-title>. <source>Fly</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>80</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22728672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cormier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Gouis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubreuil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lafarge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Praud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>A genome-wide identification of chromosomal regions determining nitrogen use efficiency components in wheat (Triticum aestivum L.)</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>127</volume>, <fpage>2679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2693</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25326179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cornah</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Germain</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Beale</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Lipid utilization, gluconeogenesis, and seedling growth in Arabidopsis mutants lacking the glyoxylate cycle enzyme malate synthase</article-title>. <source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source>
<volume>279</volume>, <fpage>42916</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42923</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15272001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ortu&#x000f1;o</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chaves</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Deficit irrigation as a strategy to save water: physiology and potential application to horticulture</article-title>. <source>Journal of Integrative Plant Biology</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>1421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1434</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Des Marais</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juenger</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Genotype-by-environment interaction and plasticity: exploring genomic responses of plants to the abiotic environment</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution, and Systematics</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Des Marais</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wayne</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Juenger</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Physiological genomics of response to soil drying in diverse Arabidopsis accessions</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>893</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>914</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22408074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dur&#x000e1;n Zuazo</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pleguezuelo</surname><given-names>CRR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tarifa</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Impact of sustained-deficit irrigation on tree growth, mineral nutrition, fruit yield and quality of mango in Spain</article-title>. <source>Fruits</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Soda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boer</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagheri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanhart</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aarts</surname><given-names>MGM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<italic>a</italic>
<article-title>Genotype&#x02013;environment interactions affecting preflowering physiological and morphological traits of Brassica rapa grown in two watering regimes</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>708</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24474811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Soda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kruijer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malosetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aarts</surname><given-names>MGM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Quantitative trait loci and candidate genes underlying genotype by environment interaction in the response of Arabidopsis thaliana to drought</article-title>. <source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>585</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>599</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>El-Soda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Malosetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zwaan</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Koornneef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aarts</surname><given-names>MGM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<italic>b</italic>
<article-title>Genotype&#x000d7;environment interaction QTL mapping in plants: lessons from Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Trends in Plant Science</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>390</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>398</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24491827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab><bold>FAO Water</bold></collab></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<source>Crop WATER INFORMATION: SOybean</source>. <uri xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/nr/water/cropinfo_tomato.html">http://www.fao.org/nr/water/cropinfo_tomato.html</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fereres</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Deficit irrigation for reducing agricultural water use</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>147</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>159</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17088360</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baar</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qudeimat</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Woriedh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alawady</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ratnadewi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gremillon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Reski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>A mitochondrial protein homologous to the mammalian peripheral-type benzodiazepine receptor is essential for stress adaptation in plants</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>1004</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1018</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17651369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fridman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrari</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Zooming in on a quantitative trait for tomato yield using interspecific introgressions</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>305</volume>, <fpage>1786</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1789</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15375271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fridman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pleban</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>A recombination hotspot delimits a wild-species quantitative trait locus for tomato sugar content to 484 bp within an invertase gene</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
<volume>97</volume>, <fpage>4718</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4723</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gawenda</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorwarth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gunther</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ordon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide association studies in elite varieties of German winter barley using single-marker and haplotype-based methods</article-title>. <source>Plant Breeding</source>
<volume>134</volume>, <fpage>28</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bancel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vercambre</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The microplate reader: an efficient tool for the separate enzymatic analysis of sugars in plant tissues&#x02014;validation of a micro-method</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>1893</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1905</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Transcriptional profiles of drought-responsive genes in modulating transcription signal transduction, and biochemical pathways in tomato</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>3563</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3575</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20643807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Enhanced tolerance to drought in transgenic rice plants overexpressing C4 photosynthesis enzymes</article-title>. <source>Crop Journal</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>114</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guichard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gary</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Tomato fruit quality in relation to water and carbon fluxes</article-title>. <source>Agronomie</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>392</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Guillet</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Just</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Destrac-Irvine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Baldet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hernould</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rothan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>A fruit-specific phosphoenolpyruvate carboxylase is related to rapid growth of tomato fruit</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>
<volume>214</volume>, <fpage>717</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>726</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11882940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Semel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Yield quantitative trait loci from wild tomato are predominately expressed by the shoot</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>122</volume>, <fpage>405</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>420</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20872209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>S-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stoffel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Deynze</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buell</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Single nucleotide polymorphism discovery in cultivated tomato via sequencing by synthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Genome Journal</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>17</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Knaap</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Tomato fruit weight 11.3 maps close to fasciated on the bottom of chromosome 11</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>123</volume>, <fpage>465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>474</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21541852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Illa-Berenguer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Houten</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van der Knaap</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Rapid and reliable identification of tomato fruit weight and locule number loci by QTL-seq</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>1329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1342</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25893466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jury</surname><given-names>Wa</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaux</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>The role of science in solving the world&#x02019;s emerging water problems</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>15715</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15720</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>A thaumatin-like gene in nonclimacteric pepper fruits used as molecular marker in probing disease resistance, ripening, and sugar accumulation</article-title>. <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>135</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11999369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Saburi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>COLD SHOCK DOMAIN PROTEIN 3 is involved in salt and drought stress tolerance in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>FEBS Open Bio</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>438</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>442</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cetin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Dasgan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Topcu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kaman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ekici</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Derici</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ozguven</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Yield response of greenhouse grown tomato to partial root drying and conventional deficit irrigation</article-title>. <source>Agricultural Water Management</source>
<volume>69</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Korte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Farlow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The advantages and limitations of trait analysis with GWAS: a review</article-title>. <source>Plant Methods</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23876160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Korte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilhj&#x000e1;lmsson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordborg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>A mixed-model approach for genome-wide association studies of correlated traits in structured populations</article-title>. <source>Nature Genetics</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>1066</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1071</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22902788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langridge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Functional genomics of abiotic stress tolerance in cereals</article-title>. <source>Briefings in Functional Genomics and Proteomics</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>354</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17202125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leib</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Caspari</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Redulla</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jabro</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Partial rootzone drying and deficit irrigation of &#x02018;Fuji&#x02019; apples in a semi-arid climate</article-title>. <source>Irrigation Science</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lemoine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Camera</surname><given-names>S La</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atanassova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Source-to-sink transport of sugar and regulation by environmental factors</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>272</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23898339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bergelson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordborg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Borevitz</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Association mapping of local climate-sensitive quantitative trait loci in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA</source>
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>21199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21204</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rainsford</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>High invertase activity in tomato reproductive organs correlates with enhanced sucrose import into, and heat tolerance of, young fruit</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>63</volume>, <fpage>1155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1166</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22105847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicodemus</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>snp.plotter: an R-based SNP/haplotype association and linkage disequilibrium plotting package</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>774</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>776</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17234637</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malosetti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribaut</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Crossa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>van Eeuwijk</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>A multi-trait multi-environment QTL mixed model with an application to drought and nitrogen stress trials in maize (Zea mays L.)</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>
<volume>161</volume>, <fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>257</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martinoia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rentsch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Malate compartmentation&#x02014;responses to a complex metabolism</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>447</fpage> &#x02013; <lpage>467</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McClurg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pletcher</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wiltshire</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Su</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Comparative analysis of haplotype association mapping algorithms</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>61</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16466585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mir&#x000e1;s-Avalos</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alcobendas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alarc&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Valsesia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#x000e9;nard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicol&#x000e1;s</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Assessment of the water stress effects on peach fruit quality and size using a fruit tree model, QualiTree</article-title>. <source>Agricultural Water Management</source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Association mapping of germination traits in Arabidopsis thaliana under light and nutrient treatments: searching for G&#x000d7;E effects</article-title>. <source>G3 (Bethesda, Md.)</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1478</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0063"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nyquist</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Alternative partitioning of the genotype-by-environment interaction</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>84</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24203047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0064"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neta-Sharir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Isaacson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lurie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Dual role for tomato heat shock protein 21: protecting photosystem II from oxidative stress and promoting color changes during fruit maturation</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>1829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1838</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15879560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0065"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen-Quoc</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foyer</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>A role for &#x02018;futile cycles&#x02019; involving invertase and sucrose synthase in sucrose metabolism of tomato fruit</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>881</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>889</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11432905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0066"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nir</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Moshelion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The Arabidopsis GIBBERELLIN METHYL TRANSFERASE 1 suppresses gibberellin activity, reduces whole-plant transpiration and promotes drought tolerance in transgenic tomato</article-title>. <source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0067"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>Y-L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>An update on source-to-sink carbon partitioning in tomato</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>516</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25339963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0068"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>An ethylene response factor (ERF5) promoting adaptation to drought and salt tolerance in tomato</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Reports</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>360</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22038370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0069"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauvage</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Dissecting quantitative trait variation in the resequencing era: complementarity of bi-parental, multi-parental and association panels</article-title>. <source>Plant Science</source>
<volume>242</volume>, <fpage>120</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>130</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26566830</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0070"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perruc</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Charpenteau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jauneau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Galaud</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranjeva</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranty</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>A novel calmodulin-binding protein functions as a negative regulator of osmotic stress tolerance in Arabidopsis thaliana seedlings</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>410</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>420</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15086802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0071"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Major</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rouhier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Duplessis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide analysis of eukaryote thaumatin-like proteins (TLPs) with an emphasis on poplar</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biology</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>33</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21324123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0072"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pignocchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiddle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Asensi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taybi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Foyer</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Ascorbate oxidase-dependent changes in the redox state of the apoplast modulate gene transcript accumulation leading to modified hormone signaling and orchestration of defense processes in tobacco</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>141</volume>, <fpage>423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>435</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16603663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0073"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Proels</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roitsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Extracellular invertase LIN6 of tomato: a pivotal enzyme for integration of metabolic, hormonal, and stress signals is regulated by a diurnal rhythm</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>1555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1567</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19297549</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0074"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab><bold>R Development Core Team</bold></collab></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<source>R: a language and environment for statistical computing</source>. <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0075"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>ASN</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Celesnik</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Coping with stresses: roles of calcium- and calcium/calmodulin-regulated gene expression</article-title>. <source>The Plant Cell</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2010</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2032</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21642548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0076"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rentsch</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Tegeder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Transporters for uptake and allocation of organic nitrogen compounds in plants</article-title>. <source>FEBS Letters</source>
<volume>581</volume>, <fpage>2281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2289</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17466985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0077"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reuscher</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Shiratake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide identification and expression analysis of aquaporins in tomato</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>e79052</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24260152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0078"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ricardi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide data (ChIP-seq) enabled identification of cell wall-related and aquaporin genes as targets of tomato ASR1, a drought stress-responsive transcription factor</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biology</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24423251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0079"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripoll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<italic>a</italic>
<article-title>The potential of the MAGIC TOM parental accessions to explore the genetic variability in tomato acclimation to repeated cycles of water deficit and recovery</article-title>. <source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1172</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26779213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0080"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripoll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<italic>b</italic>
<article-title>Water deficit effects on tomato quality depend on fruit developmental stage and genotype</article-title>. <source>Journal of Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>190</volume>, <fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26629612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0081"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ripoll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Staudt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lopez-Lauri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bidel</surname><given-names>LPR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bertin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Water shortage and quality of fleshy fruits, making the most of the unavoidable</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>4097</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4117</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24821951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0082"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rost</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerten</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bondeau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lucht</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rohwer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schaphoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Agricultural green and blue water consumption and its influence on the global water system</article-title>. <source>Water Resources Research</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>W09405</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0083"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Sugar input, metabolism, and signaling mediated by invertase: roles in development, yield potential, and response to drought and heat</article-title>. <source>Molecular Plant</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>942</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>955</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20729475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0084"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruggieri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Francese</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Alessandro</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigano</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Milone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cardi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mennella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>An association mapping approach to identify favourable alleles for tomato fruit quality breeding</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biology</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24387633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0085"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruggieri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Festa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rigano</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Picarella</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazzucato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Barone</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Exploring a tomato landraces collection for fruit-related traits by the aid of a high-throughput genomic platform</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>e0137139</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26393929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0086"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sa&#x000ef;dou</surname><given-names>A-A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Thuillet</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Couderc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mariac</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vigouroux</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Association studies including genotype by environment interactions: prospects and limits</article-title>. <source>BMC Genetics</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24393630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0087"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saliba-Colombani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Langlois</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Philouze</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Genetic analysis of organoleptic quality in fresh market tomato. 1. Mapping QTLs for physical and chemical traits</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0088"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santesteban</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Royo</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Water status, leaf area and fruit load influence on berry weight and sugar accumulation of cv. &#x02018;Tempranillo&#x02019; under semiarid conditions</article-title>. <source>Scientia Horticulturae</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>60</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0089"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Atwell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordborg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>&#x02018;Missing&#x02019; G&#x000d7;E variation controls flowering time in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genetics</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e1005597</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26473359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0090"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sauvage</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bauchet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Do</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nikoloski</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Genome-wide association in tomato reveals 44 candidate loci for fruit metabolic traits</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>165</volume>, <fpage>1120</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1132</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24894148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0091"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilhj&#x000e1;lmsson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Platt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Korte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Seren</surname><given-names>&#x000dc;</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nordborg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>An efficient multi-locus mixed-model approach for genome-wide association studies in structured populations</article-title>. <source>Nature Genetics</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>825</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>830</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22706313</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0092"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Seki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Narusaka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Monitoring the expression profiles of 7000 Arabidopsis genes under drought, cold and high-salinity stresses using a full-length cDNA microarray</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>292</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12164808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0093"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Semel</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Roessner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Metabolite analysis for the comparison of irrigated and non-irrigated field grown tomato of varying genotype</article-title>. <source>Metabolomics</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>295</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0094"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Yamaguchi-Shinozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Gene networks involved in drought stress response and tolerance</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>221</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>227</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17075077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0095"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>S-C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Durstewitz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Plieske</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Development of a large SNP genotyping array and generation of high-density genetic maps in tomato</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e40563</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22802968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0096"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Buret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Garchery</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Carretero</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Technique for rapid, small-scale analysis of vitamin C levels in fruit and application to a tomato mutant collection</article-title>. <source>Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>6159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6165</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16910702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0097"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tardieu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Any trait or trait-related allele can confer drought tolerance: just design the right drought scenario</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>63</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21963615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0098"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tieman</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Zeigler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmelz</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bliss</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kirst</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Klee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Identification of loci affecting flavour volatile emissions in tomato fruits</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>896</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16473892</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0099"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab><bold>Tomato Genome Consortium</bold></collab></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>The tomato genome sequence provides insights into fleshy fruit evolution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>485</volume>, <fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>641</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22660326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Eeuwijk</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bink</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chenu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Detection and use of QTL for complex traits in multiple environments</article-title>. <source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>205</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20137999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Verbyla</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cavanagh</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Verbyla</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Whole-genome analysis of multienvironment or multitrait QTL in MAGIC</article-title>. <source>G3 Genes|Genomes|Genetics</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1569</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1584</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25237109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Overexpression of tomato chloroplast-targeted DnaJ protein enhances tolerance to drought stress and resistance to Pseudomonas solanacearum in transgenic tobacco</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24929777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0103"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinocur</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Plant responses to drought, salinity and extreme temperatures: towards genetic engineering for stress tolerance</article-title>. <source>Planta</source>
<volume>218</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14513379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0104"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Warnes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Leisch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<source>Package &#x02018;genetics&#x02019;</source>
<uri xlink:href="http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=genetics">http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=genetics</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0105"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B-H</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Genard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Lescourret</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Influence of assimilate and water supply on seasonal variation of acids in peach (cv Suncrest)</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Science of Food and Agriculture</source>
<volume>82</volume>, <fpage>1829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1836</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0106"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranc</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mu&#x000f1;os</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rolland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Bouchet</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Desplat</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Paslier</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Brunel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Phenotypic diversity and association mapping for fruit quality traits in cultivated tomato and related species</article-title>. <source>Theoretical and Applied Genetics</source>
<volume>126</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>581</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23124430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0107"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanor</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Nunes-Nesi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<italic>a</italic>
<article-title>RNA interference of LIN5 in tomato confirms its role in controlling brix content, uncovers the influence of sugars on the levels of fruit hormones, and demonstrates the importance of sucrose cleavage for normal fruit development and fertility</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiology</source>
<volume>150</volume>, <fpage>1204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1218</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19439574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0108"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanor</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Rambla</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Cha&#x000ef;b</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Steppa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Granell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<italic>b</italic>
<article-title>Metabolic characterization of loci affecting sensory attributes in tomato allows an assessment of the influence of the levels of primary metabolites and volatile organic contents</article-title>. <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>2139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2154</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19346240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0109"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Mota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Responses of drip irrigated tomato (Solanum lycopersicum L.) yield, quality and water productivity to various soil matric potential thresholds in an arid region of Northwest China</article-title>. <source>Agricultural Water Management</source>
<volume>129</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>193</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0110"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name name-style="western"><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Overexpression of soybean ubiquitin-conjugating enzyme gene GmUBC2 confers enhanced drought and salt tolerance through modulating abiotic stress-responsive gene expression in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Molecular Biology</source>
<volume>72</volume>, <fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>367</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19941154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>