<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Genet Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Genet. Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Genetics and Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1617-4615</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1617-4623</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5854731</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1387</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00438-017-1387-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Quantitative trait loci for tuber blackspot bruise and enzymatic discoloration susceptibility in diploid potato</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hara-Skrzypiec</surname><given-names>Agnieszka</given-names></name><address><phone>22 729 90 87</phone><email>a.hara@ihar.edu.pl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0015a;liwka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jakuczun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zimnoch-Guzowska</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2180 5359</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.460599.7</institution-id><institution>Plant Breeding and Acclimatization Institute, </institution><institution>National Research Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>M&#x00142;och&#x000f3;w, Platanowa 19, 05-831 M&#x00142;och&#x000f3;w, Poland </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p>Communicated by S. Hohmann.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>293</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>342</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p>Tuber tissue discolorations caused by impact (blackspot bruising) and enzymatic discoloration (ED) after tuber cutting are crucial quality traits of the cultivated potato. To understand the complex genetics of the traits, quantitative trait locus (QTL) analysis using diploid mapping population and diversity array technology (DArT) markers was performed. The phenotypic assessment included the complex evaluation of blackspot bruising susceptibility through two methods: rotating drum (<italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>) and falling bolt (<italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>) in combination with the evaluation of enzymatic discoloration. Because of observed in-practice relationship between bruising susceptibility and tuber starch content (TSC), analysis of starch content-corrected bruising susceptibility (SCB) was performed. QTLs for bruising were detected on chromosomes I, V with both test methods. The rotating drum method enabled the detection of additional QTLs on chromosomes VIII and XII. Analysis of SCB enabled the identification of the major QTL on chromosome V and two weaker QTLs on chromosomes VIII and XII, independently of starch content. The QTL for bruising detected on chromosome I overlapped with the most significant QTL for tuber starch content. This QTL was not significant for starch content-corrected bruising susceptibility, and the effect of the QTL on chromosome V was enhanced for this trait. The QTL analysis of ED revealed the contribution of seven QTLs for the trait, located on six chromosomes, including these detected for the first time: a major locus on chromosome V and minor QTLs on chromosomes VII and X, which were specific for the trait. The QTL for ED on chromosome VIII was co-localized with the marker for polyphenol oxidase (<italic>POT32</italic>). The phenotypic correlation between bruising and ED was confirmed in QTL analyses of both traits, and the QTLs detected for these traits overlapped on chromosomes I, V, and VIII. Our results should provide a basis for further studies on candidate genes affecting blackspot bruise susceptibility and enzymatic discoloration.</p><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s00438-017-1387-0) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Bruising</kwd><kwd>Enzymatic discoloration</kwd><kwd>QTL analysis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>The National Science Centre in Poland</institution></funding-source><award-id>UMO-2012/05/N/NZ9/01295</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Hara-Skrzypiec</surname><given-names>Agnieszka</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p>Enzymatic discoloration (ED) and blackspot bruising affect potato tuber quality via the formation of dark pigments from phenolic compounds and the action of polyphenol oxidase (PPO) (Cobb <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1999</xref>). The ED that appears after peeling and cutting the tuber leads to not only undesirable colours but also flavour changes and loss of nutritional quality (Vitti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2011</xref>). ED occurs not only in potato tubers but also in fruits, vegetables, and seafood. Blackspot bruising of potatoes is an internal defect of tubers caused by mechanical impact and is observed only after peeling of the tuber skin and short exposure to the air. Bruising leads to rejection of the crop by consumers and the processing industry, thus resulting in considerable economic losses (Storey <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2007</xref>). Potato bruising is estimated to cost the U.S. potato industry at least $298&#x000a0;million each year, as deduced from a total potato production worth $2&#x000a0;billion (Thorton and Bohl <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">1995</xref>). The British Potato Marketing Board has estimated losses caused by the potato damage to be &#x000a3;30&#x000a0;million per year, corresponding to approximately &#x000a3;200 per hectare (Anon. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">1994</xref>). To decrease losses due to mechanical damages formed during harvest and at all stages of postharvest handling, the breeding of new potato cultivars with enhanced resistance to mechanical damage and blackspot bruising is an appropriate approach. The primary difficulty in the phenotypic selection of cultivars resistant to bruising in potato breeding programs is the limited number of tubers at an early stage of the breeding cycle. Potato breeding starts with a cross from which each true seed gives rise to a clonal, tuber-propagated line. The rate of vegetative propagation of such line is rather slow: eightfold per season (Bradshaw and Mackay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1994</xref>), while the methods of scoring tuber bruising are destructive for the assessed tubers. Diagnostic molecular tools for the trait would provide an advantage for breeding programs aimed at selection of cultivars resistant for bruising.</p><p>Blackspot bruising of potato tubers is a complex trait resulting from the interactions of both genetic and environmental factors (McGarry et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">1996</xref>), with heritability values varying from 0.45 to 0.93 (Zg&#x000f3;rska <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">1989</xref>; Pavek et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1993</xref>; Hara-Skrzypiec and Jakuczun <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2013</xref>; Urbany et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2011a</xref>). The biochemical components of the blackspot bruise reaction, PPO, and its substrates are expected to be essential for melanin synthesis in both ED and blackspot bruising. The importance of PPO in the ED process has been confirmed by the absence of discoloration in tubers with silenced expression of the PPO gene (Bachem et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1994</xref>; Coetzer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2001</xref>). Commercial companies have applied the PPO-silencing approach to create non-browning potatoes and apples (Walz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">2015</xref>). Moreover, the low rate of discoloration in the wild species <italic>Solanum hjertingii</italic> is due to low PPO activity (Brown et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1999</xref>). Culley et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2002</xref>) have demonstrated that <italic>S. hjertingii</italic> has a truncated version of <italic>POT32</italic> (one of the isoforms of polyphenol oxidase), which is a major form of <italic>PPO</italic> expressed in tubers (Thygesen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">1995</xref>). Werij et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2007</xref>) have dissected the genetic factors responsible for the variation observed in ED using a diploid potato family as a mapping population. The authors have identified three QTLs for ED on potato chromosomes I, III, and VIII, and the QTL on chromosome VIII co-localizes with molecular markers for <italic>POT32</italic>. The authors have discriminated three different alleles of the <italic>POT32</italic> gene (<italic>POT32PS1, POT32PS2</italic>, and <italic>POT32PS3</italic>), and genotypes with two copies of allele <italic>POT32PS1</italic> have the highest levels of both <italic>POT32</italic> gene expression and discoloration. The complexity of the genetic control of bruising and the various PPO alleles segregating in the studied genetic material may be primary reasons for the weak correlation between the trait and PPO activity demonstrated in many studies (Stark et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">1985</xref>; Stevens and Davelaar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">1997</xref>; L&#x000e6;rke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2000</xref>).</p><p>Tyrosine, a primary substrate of the discoloration reaction, is expected to be an important factor in bruising. The previous studies have demonstrated that the tyrosine level is correlated with bruising, as assessed as discoloration after tissue homogenization and in abrasive peeling tests (Corsini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1992</xref>; Dean et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1993</xref>), although the results of these tests are more correlated with the level of ED than to level of bruising. However, weak or non-significant correlations between blackspot formation and tyrosine levels have been reported in studies using the impact method for bruising evaluation (Stevens and Davelaar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">1997</xref>; Strehmel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2010</xref>; Hara-Skrzypiec and Jakuczun <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2013</xref>). The content of chlorogenic and caffeic acids, potential monophenolic substrates of PPO in tubers, is not correlated with ED levels and blackspot formation (Friedman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1997</xref>; L&#x000e6;rke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2002a</xref>). In addition, as demonstrated by Werij et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2007</xref>), QTLs for chlorogenic acid and tyrosine content do not overlap with the QTLs for ED.</p><p>In addition to the biochemical aspects of blackspot bruise formation, structural factors, such as cellular stability, cell number and volume, cell wall thickness, and tuber turgidity, also influence tuber bruising (Aeppli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1981</xref>; McGarry et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">1996</xref>; L&#x000e6;rke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2002b</xref>).</p><p>A close relationship between bruising susceptibility and tuber-specific gravity has been described in many reports (Scudder et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">1950</xref>; Massey et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1952</xref>; Ophuis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">1958</xref>; Rogers-Lewis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1980</xref>; Corsini et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1999</xref>; Urbany et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2011a</xref>). However, most of these studies have also demonstrated that some of the tested cultivars do not follow this tendency. An explanation for the correlation between bruising and specific gravity/dry matter content may be the interaction of starch grains with cell membranes; cells full of starch grains are more vulnerable to impact damage, because starch granules may rupture the membranes during the impact (Hughes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1980</xref>).</p><p>Urbany et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2011a</xref>) have reported the first attempts to dissect the genetic factors underlying bruising susceptibility and have associated DNA polymorphisms at multiple functional candidate loci with phenotypic variations in tetraploid cultivars and breeding clones. This strategy has led to the identification of significant associations among markers for <italic>PPO</italic> isoforms, <italic>hydroxycinnamoyl CoA quinate transferase (HCT), starch phosphorylase L-type (PHO1A)</italic>, and <italic>4-coumarate CoA ligase (4CL)</italic> genes and tuber bruising susceptibility. By comparing the tuber proteomes of bruising-resistant and susceptible cultivars, Urbany et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2011b</xref>) have discovered a novel candidate gene for bruising: <italic>triacylglycerol lipase III (LipIII27)</italic>. Markers derived from this gene are significantly associated with bruising susceptibility.</p><p>The goal of our study was to perform mapping of QTLs for blackspot bruise susceptibility in diploid potatoes. This study is the first to use a full-sib linkage mapping and QTL analyses of the bruising susceptibility and enzymatic discoloration susceptibility. Our approach, based on a dense genetic map constructed of DArT markers, complements the previous approaches by including new data on bruising susceptibility inheritance. Two different test methods were applied to determine bruising susceptibility. To clarify relationships between the bruising susceptibility and tuber starch content observed in breeding practice, QTL analysis of tuber starch content-corrected bruising susceptibility (SCB<sub>RD,</sub> SCB<sub>FB</sub>) was conducted and compared with the results of independent mapping the QTLs for bruising susceptibility and tuber starch content.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant materials</title><p>Diploid potato clones DG 06-5 (susceptible to bruising) and DG 03-226 (resistant to bruising) were crossed to obtain the <italic>F</italic>
<sub>1</sub> mapping population 11&#x02013;36 (<italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;149). The parental forms resulted from a long-term recombinant breeding program at Plant Breeding and Acclimatization Institute&#x02014;National Research Institute and were complex interspecific <italic>Solanum</italic> hybrids with <italic>S. tuberosum, S. acaule, S. chacoense, S. demissum, S. gourlayi, S. microdontum, S. phureja, S. verrucosum</italic>, and <italic>S. yungasense</italic> in their pedigree. In addition, DG 03-226 had a contribution from <italic>S. stenotomum</italic>. The theoretical contributions of <italic>S. tuberosum</italic> in the forms DG 06-5 and DG 03-226 were 70 and 69%, respectively. The corresponding values were 11 and 5% for <italic>S. chacoense</italic> and 6 and 14% for <italic>S. phureja</italic>. The mapping population, its parental forms and standard cultivars, table cv. Vineta and starch cv. Hinga, were planted at the end of April and harvested at the end of September in 3 consecutive years (2012, 2013, and 2014). The field experiments were fertilized with 90, 90, and 170&#x000a0;kg&#x000a0;ha<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of N, P, and K, respectively, and potatoes were chemically protected against pests and pathogens.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Phenotypic and statistical analyses</title><p>Blackspot bruise susceptibility was determined with two methods. In the first method, blackspot bruises were induced in a rotating drum (<italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>) according to Doma&#x00144;ski et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2007</xref>). Experiments were conducted in mid-February in 2013, 2014, and 2015 with two (2013, 2015) or three replicates (2014). To assess the resistance to blackspot bruising, each replicate included 14&#x02013;20 tubers per genotype. The selected tubers were undamaged, non-greening, and, as much as possible, uniform in size within each genotype. Sample tubers were stored for 5&#x000a0;months at 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C to simulate a storage period common in the potato industry. Before the test, tubers were incubated for 12&#x000a0;h at 11&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Tubers were placed in a hexagonal drum that was rotated ten times to stimulate the formation of blackspots (Douches et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2003</xref>). Then, the bruised tubers were stored at 20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 72&#x000a0;h. After peeling, blackspot bruises were visually evaluated and then divided into four quality groups: <italic>A</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0&#x02013;25% of tuber surface covered by bruises, lack of or weak bruising; <italic>B</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;25&#x02013;50% of tuber surface covered by bruises, moderate bruising; <italic>C</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;50&#x02013;75% of tuber surface covered by bruises, strong bruising; and <italic>D</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;75&#x02013;100% of tuber surface covered by bruises, very strong bruising. A bruising index was calculated with the formula <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;[(0.25<italic>A</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.5<italic>B</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;0.75<italic>C</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>D</italic>)/number of tested tubers]&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;100. The <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> ranged from 0 (resistant to blackspot bruising) to 100 (the most susceptible to bruising) (a modified method according to Urbany et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2011a</xref>). The second method, the falling bolt method (<italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>), was modified as described by Johnson et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2003</xref>). Experiments were conducted in mid-February in 2014 and 2015. The evaluations of <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub> were performed on two (2015) or three replicates (2014). Incubation conditions before and after impact were the same as those in the <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> method. Five tubers from each genotype were tested per replicate. The tubers were subjected to mechanical impact involving a metal bolt imparting 0.76&#x000a0;J of energy. After incubation at 20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 72&#x000a0;h, each tuber was transected through the site of mechanical impact. The spot sizes (diameter and depth in mm) and colour intensity of the bruises were rated according to the scale of Hironaka et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">1996</xref>): 0&#x02009;=&#x02009;no discoloration; 1&#x02009;=&#x02009;very small spots or vaguely defined; 2&#x02009;=&#x02009;spot diameter 3&#x02013;5&#x000a0;mm, depth less than 5&#x000a0;mm, grey or brownish; 3&#x02009;=&#x02009;spot diameter 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;mm, depth less than 5&#x000a0;mm, grey or black; 4&#x02009;=&#x02009;spot diameter 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;mm, depth greater than 5&#x000a0;mm, grey or black; and 5&#x02009;=&#x02009;spot diameter greater than 10&#x000a0;mm, depth greater than 5&#x000a0;mm, black.</p><p>Tuber starch content (TSC, %) was estimated with the underwater weight method, on the basis of the ratio of tuber weight in air to tuber weight in water, according to Lunden (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1956</xref>).</p><p>Starch-corrected blackspot bruise susceptibility estimated by the rotating drum (SCB<sub>RD</sub>) and falling bolt (SCB<sub>FB</sub>) methods was calculated using regression analysis according to Urbany et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2011a</xref>).</p><p>Enzymatic discoloration was evaluated in December 2012, 2013, and 2014. Five tubers from each genotype were tested in two (2012, 2014) or three replicates (2013). The degree of discoloration was evaluated 4&#x000a0;h after the tuber was cut in half. The level of ED was scored according to the colour chart for determining the discoloration of potato (Dansk G&#x000e6;rings-Industri, Ltd., Copenhagen, Denmark) on a scale of 1&#x02013;9 (where 1&#x02009;=&#x02009;the strongest discoloration, and 9&#x02009;=&#x02009;lack of discoloration).</p><p>The normality of the distribution of phenotypic data was tested with the Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk test. The reproducibility of analysed traits between years was estimated by calculating linear Pearson&#x02019;s correlation coefficients. The determination coefficients (<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>) for blackspot bruising were estimated from an analysis of variance. The broad-sense heritability was estimated according Doma&#x00144;ski et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2007</xref>) according to the formula: <italic>H</italic>
<sub>b</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>&#x003c3;</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
<sub>g</sub>/<italic>&#x003c3;</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
<sub>g</sub>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>&#x003c3;</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
<sub>ge</sub>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>&#x003c3;</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
<sub>e</sub>. All statistical analyses were performed using STATISTICA for Windows (StatSoft Polska, Krak&#x000f3;w, Polska).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Genetic mapping and QTL analysis</title><p>Genomic DNA was isolated from freeze-dried leaf tissue using a GeneElute Plant Genomic DNA Miniprep kit (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, Missouri, USA). Markers derived from the candidate genes listed in Supplementary Table S1 were amplified in 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of PCR mixture containing 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of 10&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;PCR buffer (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, Missouri, USA), 6&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M MgCl<sub>2</sub> (25&#x000a0;mM), 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M dNTPs (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, Missouri, USA), 0.4&#x000a0;&#x000b5;M each primer, 1 U DreamTaq polymerase (Fermentas Life Sciences, Thermo Fischer Scientific, Inc.), and 10&#x02013;30&#x000a0;ng of the template DNA. The PCR parameters were as follows: 94&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 60&#x000a0;s and 40 cycles of 93&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 25&#x000a0;s, 50&#x02013;65&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 35&#x000a0;s, 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 90&#x000a0;s, and 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 300&#x000a0;s (Supplementary Table S1). Restriction digestions were performed in 20&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of reaction mixture containing 10&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of PCR product, 1&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of enzyme (listed in Table S1), 2&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of buffer provided by the enzyme supplier, and 7&#x000a0;&#x000b5;l of H<sub>2</sub>O for 3&#x000a0;h at the temperature recommended by the enzyme supplier (37 or 65&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C). DNA polymorphisms in amplicons with or without restriction endonuclease digestion&#x000a0;site were detected by electrophoresis in 1.5% agarose gels with ethidium bromide staining. Diversity Array Technology (DArT) analysis was performed by Diversity Array Pty Ltd., Canberra, Australia, as described in &#x0015a;liwka et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">b</xref>), using protocols developed for other plant species (Jaccoud et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2001</xref>; Wenzl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">2004</xref>; Akbari et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2006</xref>). Parental linkage maps and a common map were constructed using the JoinMap<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>4 software with the following settings: CP (cross pollinator) population type, independence LOD (logarithm of odds) as a grouping parameter (linkages with LOD&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3 were considered significant), regression mapping algorithm, and Haldane&#x02019;s mapping function (&#x0015a;liwka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2012a</xref>). Identification and orientation of particular potato chromosomes were performed by comparing the maps with those from the previous DArT mapping studies in <italic>Solanum</italic> (&#x0015a;liwka et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2012a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">b</xref>; Sharma et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2013</xref>). Separate linkage maps for both parents were constructed using the function Create Maternal and Paternal Population Nodes, which analysed only markers descending from the given parent, whereas the ones descending from the other parent or from both parents were ignored. Then, a common map based on all markers was constructed using the function Create Population Node. QTL analysis was performed using interval mapping with the MapQTL<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>6 software (Van Ooijen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">2009</xref>). QTLs were detected using an LOD threshold&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;3.1.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Phenotyping evaluation</title><p>The mean values of <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>, SCB<sub>RD</sub>, SCB<sub>FB</sub>, ED and TSC of the parents and individuals from the mapping population 11&#x02013;36 and standard cultivars are presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The paternal clone DG 03-226 was highly resistant to bruising and enzymatic discoloration with a low value of TSC. The maternal clone DG 06-5 was highly susceptible to bruising with high TSC.</p><p>
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Mean values of <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>, SCB<sub>RD</sub>, SCB<sub>FB</sub>, ED and TSC (%) of the parents and individuals from the mapping population 11&#x02013;36 and standard cultivars, ranges of the traits and standard deviations</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Trait<sup>a</sup>
</th><th align="left">DG 03-226 &#x02642;</th><th align="left">DG 06-5 &#x02640;</th><th align="left">Standard cv.Vineta</th><th align="left">Standard cv.Hinga</th><th align="left">
<italic>F</italic>
<sub>1</sub>, <italic>N</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;149 population mean</th><th align="left">Range of <italic>F</italic>
<sub>1</sub> variation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>
</td><td char="(" align="char">9.3 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.9)</td><td char="(" align="char">87.3 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">1.2 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9)</td><td char="(" align="char">61.7 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.3)</td><td char="(" align="char">46.9 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;17.6)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">5.0&#x02013;91.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>
</td><td char="(" align="char">1.4 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3)</td><td char="(" align="char">4.8 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.0 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">1.9 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">2.0 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">0.1&#x02013;4.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SCB<sub>RD</sub>
</td><td char="(" align="char">&#x02212; 34.9 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">29.5 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">&#x02212; 35.5 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">9.9 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.1 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;16.3)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;40.5&#x02013;39.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SCB<sub>FB</sub>
</td><td char="(" align="char">&#x02212; 0.8 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">2.1 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">&#x02212; 1.4 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.02)</td><td char="(" align="char">&#x02212; 0.5 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.04)</td><td char="(" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.008 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.9&#x02013;2.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ED</td><td char="(" align="char">8.2 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">5.3 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">8.5 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">6.7 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">7.4 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.9)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">5.3&#x02013;9.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TSC</td><td char="(" align="char">16.4 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">24.8 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">12.4 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">21.1 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">18.7 (&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.3)</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">11.6&#x02013;23.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>a</sup>Mean values are calculated from all years and replications; <italic>N</italic> number of analysed <italic>F</italic>
<sub>1</sub> individuals</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>Pearson&#x02019;s <italic>r</italic> values for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> between results from specific years ranged from 0.65 to 0.77 and for SCB<sub>RD</sub> from 0.63 to 0.75. Pearson&#x02019;s correlation coefficient for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub> between tested years was <italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.56 and for SCB<sub>FB</sub>
<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.52. Pearson&#x02019;s correlation coefficients for ED and TSC between tested years ranged from 0.54 to 0.72 and from 0.78 to 0.81, respectively. Pearson&#x02019;s correlation coefficients between tested years for all traits were significant at <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0001.</p><p>Values of <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FD,</sub> SCB<sub>RD</sub>, SCB<sub>FD</sub>, and TSC were normally distributed in the mapping population 11&#x02013;36, whereas ED values deviated significantly from normality, with a distribution skewed towards low discoloration (Supplementary Fig. S1).</p><p>Analysis of variance in the mapping population demonstrated significant effects of genotype, year, and interaction genotype&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;year on <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>, SCB<sub>RD</sub>, SCB<sub>FD,</sub> ED, and TSC (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Genotype had the largest influence on all six assessed traits, explaining from 53.2% for SCB<sub>FB</sub> up to 63.5% of the variance for B<sub>RD</sub>. For four of six traits, the effects of the genotype&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;year interactions were stronger than the year effects, which was not the case for SCB<sub>RD</sub> and TSC.</p><p>
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Analysis of variance in <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>, SCB<sub>RD</sub>, SCB<sub>FB</sub>, ED and TSC in the mapping population 11&#x02013;36</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Factor/interaction</th><th char="." align="left" colspan="2">
<italic>Df</italic> effect<sup>a</sup>
</th><th char="." align="left" colspan="2">Mean sum of squares effect</th><th char="." align="left">
<italic>Df</italic> error<sup>a</sup>
</th><th char="." align="left" colspan="2">Mean sum of squares error</th><th char="." align="left">
<italic>F</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>P</italic>
</th><th char="." align="left">
<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup> (%)<sup>b</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Genotype {1}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">148.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">2037.0</td><td char="." align="char">543.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">102.3</td><td char="." align="char">19.9</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">63.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Year {2}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">2.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">24231.0</td><td char="." align="char">543.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">102.3</td><td char="." align="char">236.9</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">10.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">283.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">243.7</td><td char="." align="char">543.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">102.3</td><td char="." align="char">2.4</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">14.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Genotype {1}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">146.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">4.4</td><td char="." align="char">433.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.7</td><td char="." align="char">6.2</td><td align="left">0.0000</td><td char="." align="char">56.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Year {2}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">1.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">9.1</td><td char="." align="char">433.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.7</td><td char="." align="char">12.8</td><td align="left">0.0004</td><td char="." align="char">0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">143.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">1.2</td><td char="." align="char">433.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.7</td><td char="." align="char">1.7</td><td align="left">0.0000</td><td char="." align="char">15.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">SCB<sub>RD</sub>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Genotype {1}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">148.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">1767.6</td><td char="." align="char">543.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">95.4</td><td char="." align="char">18.5</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">58.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Year {2}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">2.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">34725.5</td><td char="." align="char">543.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">95.4</td><td char="." align="char">364.1</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">15.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">283.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">233.1</td><td char="." align="char">543.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">95.4</td><td char="." align="char">2.4</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">14.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">SCB<sub>FB</sub>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Genotype {1}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">146.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">4.4</td><td char="." align="char">432.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.7</td><td char="." align="char">6.2</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">53.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Year {2}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">1.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">9.0</td><td char="." align="char">432.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.7</td><td char="." align="char">12.6</td><td align="left">0.000418</td><td char="." align="char">1.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">143.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">1.2</td><td char="." align="char">432.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.7</td><td char="." align="char">1.7</td><td align="left">0.000015</td><td char="." align="char">16.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">ED</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Genotype {1}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">148.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">5.5</td><td char="." align="char">585.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.5</td><td char="." align="char">10.1</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">53.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Year {2}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">2.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">54.2</td><td char="." align="char">585.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.5</td><td char="." align="char">99.4</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">7.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">289.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.9</td><td char="." align="char">585.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">0.5</td><td char="." align="char">1.7</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">17.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">TSC</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Genotype {1}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">148.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">35.6</td><td char="." align="char">588.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">1.6</td><td char="." align="char">22.1</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">54.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Year {2}</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">2.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">1369.6</td><td char="." align="char">588.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">1.6</td><td char="." align="char">849.9</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">28.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;2</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">292.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">2.7</td><td char="." align="char">588.0</td><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">1.6</td><td char="." align="char">1.7</td><td align="left">0.00000</td><td char="." align="char">8.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>a</sup>Number of degrees of freedom</p><p>
<sup>b</sup>Percent of variance explained</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>The broad-sense heritabilities of blackspot bruise susceptibility evaluated via the rotating drum and falling bolt methods were <italic>H</italic>
<sub>b</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.71 and <italic>H</italic>
<sub>b</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.68, respectively. The broad-sense heritabilities of starch-corrected <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> and starch-corrected <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub> were <italic>H</italic>
<sub>b</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.67 and <italic>H</italic>
<sub>b</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.57, respectively. The broad-sense heritabilities of ED and TSC were <italic>H</italic>
<sub>b</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.62 and <italic>H</italic>
<sub>b</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.80, respectively.</p><p>The evaluations of blackspot bruising susceptibility with the two methods were highly correlated (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The correlation analyses of the phenotypic data demonstrated that genotypes with higher TSC were more susceptible to blackspot bruise formation than those with low TSC. Genotypes with high susceptibility to bruising also demonstrated strong ED. However, the correlation between TSC and ED was not significant.</p><p>
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Correlation coefficients (Pearson&#x02019;s <italic>r</italic> values) <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>, SCB<sub>RD</sub>, SCB<sub>FB</sub>, ED and TSC in mapping population 11&#x02013;36</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>
</th><th align="left">SCB<sub>RD</sub>
</th><th align="left">SCB<sub>FB</sub>
</th><th align="left">ED</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>
</td><td align="left">0.70**</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">SCB<sub>RD</sub>
</td><td align="left">0.97**</td><td align="left">0.67**</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">SCB<sub>FB</sub>
</td><td align="left">0.64***</td><td align="left">0.96**</td><td align="left">0.66**</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">ED</td><td align="left">0.51<sup>a</sup>***</td><td align="left">0.63<sup>a</sup>***</td><td align="left">0.53<sup>a</sup>***</td><td align="left">0.64<sup>a</sup>***</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">TSC</td><td align="left">0.42***</td><td align="left">0.32***</td><td align="left">0.21*</td><td align="left">n.s</td><td align="left">n.s</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>n.s</italic>. not significant</p><p>
<sup>a</sup>Scale for ED evaluation was reversed (9&#x02009;=&#x02009;the strongest discoloration) for the purpose of correlation coefficients calculations</p><p>
<sup>*</sup>Significant at <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01</p><p>
<sup>**</sup>Significant at <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.001</p><p>
<sup>***</sup>Significant at <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0001</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Linkage map</title><p>Of the 5363 DArT markers scored in mapping population 11&#x02013;36, 2564 DArT markers segregated. After exclusion of markers with more than 10% missing data (192 markers), those with missing parental data (91 markers), and those with quality parameters below thresholds of <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;60 (288 markers) and call rate&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;85 (112 markers), 1881 DArT markers were used to construct a genetic map. Markers with identical patterns of segregation were excluded with the JoinMap&#x000ae;4 program. An initial grouping in the population node (markers from both parents analysed simultaneously) yielded 19 groups with the average LOD for grouping 10.7 (range 9&#x02013;15). On the basis of the strongest cross-link (SCL) parameter and the presence of markers with known chromosomal positions, 12 groups corresponding to potato chromosomes were formed. The LOD for mapping varied from 13.6 to 42.8 in particular groups, with the average LOD 25.6. The final genetic map common for parents consisted of 1359 DArT markers and nine sequence-characterized amplified region (SCAR) and cleavage-amplified polymorphic sequence (CAPS) markers. Of these 1368 markers, 390 originated from parent DG 03-226, 452 originated from parent DG 06-5, and 526 originated from both parents. The total length of the genetic map reached 972&#x000a0;cM. The lengths of the chromosomes ranged from 54 (chromosome IV) to 109&#x000a0;cM (chromosome I). The numbers of markers located on particular chromosomes varied from 48 on chromosome IV to 167 on chromosome II (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, Supplementary Table S2).</p><p>
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>QTL map of population 11&#x02013;36 for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, SCB<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>, SCB<sub>FB</sub>, ED and TSC. In addition, map position of the candidate genes is shown</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="438_2017_1387_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1966"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>QTL analysis</title><p>QTLs detected using the mean data sets are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, whereas QTLs detected in data sets from particular years of phenotyping are presented in supplementary table S3. QTLs significant only in some years appear only in supplementary table S3.</p><p>
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>QTL detected for mean <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>, SCB<sub>RD</sub>, SCB<sub>FB</sub>, ED,&#x000a0;TSC in the mapping population 11&#x02013;36. Only QTL with LOD&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;3.1 are presented</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Chromosome</th><th align="left">Trait</th><th align="left">Marker at peak or markers flanking virtual interval</th><th align="left">Marker origin<sup>a</sup>
</th><th align="left">Peak position (cM)</th><th align="left">LOD</th><th align="left">
<italic>R</italic>
<sup><italic>2</italic></sup>(%)</th><th align="left">Interval (cM)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">I</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>
</td><td align="left">toPt-437458</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">75.4</td><td char="." align="char">5.00</td><td char="." align="char">14.3</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">51.5&#x02013;86.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4"/><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>
</td><td align="left">pPt-538190</td><td align="left">P2</td><td char="." align="char">72.9</td><td char="." align="char">6.76</td><td char="." align="char">19.1</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">54.1&#x02013;94.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ED</td><td align="left">pPt-538519</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">13.7</td><td char="." align="char">3.17</td><td char="." align="char">9.3</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">13.6&#x02013;14.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">toPt-437458</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">75.4</td><td char="." align="char">6.66</td><td char="." align="char">18.3</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">57.4&#x02013;108.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TSC</td><td align="left">pPt-538418</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">75.7</td><td char="." align="char">8.49</td><td char="." align="char">23.1</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">43.1&#x02013;108.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">III</td><td align="left">TSC</td><td align="left">pPt-456904</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td char="." align="char">4.85</td><td char="." align="char">13.9</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">0.0&#x02013;7.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">pPt-472721-<break/>pPt-536347</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">14.1</td><td char="." align="char">3.56</td><td char="." align="char">10.4</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">13.0&#x02013;15.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">pPt-458741</td><td align="left">P2</td><td char="." align="char">32.4</td><td char="." align="char">3.84</td><td char="." align="char">11.2</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">25.4&#x02013;32.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ED</td><td align="left">pPt-473371-<break/>pPt-540060</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">29.7</td><td char="." align="char">3.96</td><td char="." align="char">11.5</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">28.7&#x02013;30.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">V</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>
</td><td align="left">pPt-539905</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">24.5</td><td char="." align="char">4.94</td><td char="." align="char">14.2</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">22.2&#x02013;45.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3"/><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>
</td><td align="left">pPt-539905</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">24.5</td><td char="." align="char">5.41</td><td char="." align="char">15.6</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">13.6&#x02013;43.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SCB<sub>RD</sub>
</td><td align="left">pPt-655798</td><td align="left">P2</td><td char="." align="char">31.6</td><td char="." align="char">7.77</td><td char="." align="char">21.4</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">13.6&#x02013;60.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SCB<sub>FB</sub>
</td><td align="left">pPt-540393</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">32.5</td><td char="." align="char">8.92</td><td char="." align="char">24.4</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">11.6&#x02013;47.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">ED</td><td align="left">pPt-650647</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">26.0</td><td char="." align="char">7.57</td><td char="." align="char">20.9</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">11.6&#x02013;44.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">TSC</td><td align="left">pPt-652324</td><td align="left">P1</td><td char="." align="char">25.3</td><td char="." align="char">3.48</td><td char="." align="char">10.2</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">25.3&#x02013;25.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">pPt-559550</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">40.7</td><td char="." align="char">3.81</td><td char="." align="char">11.1</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">35.9&#x02013;41.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">VII</td><td align="left">ED</td><td align="left">pPt-654764-<break/>pPt-653593</td><td align="left">H,P2</td><td char="." align="char">47.3</td><td char="." align="char">3.78</td><td char="." align="char">11.0</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">37.4&#x02013;54.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">VIII</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>
</td><td align="left">pPt-535666</td><td align="left">P1</td><td char="." align="char">65.2</td><td char="." align="char">3.24</td><td char="." align="char">9.5</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">61.7&#x02013;65.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SCB<sub>RD</sub>
</td><td align="left">pPt-535666</td><td align="left">P1</td><td char="." align="char">65.2</td><td char="." align="char">3.11</td><td char="." align="char">9.2</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">61.7&#x02013;65.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ED</td><td align="left">pPt-535666</td><td align="left">P1</td><td char="." align="char">65.2</td><td char="." align="char">4.84</td><td char="." align="char">13.9</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">35.3&#x02013;65.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">IX</td><td align="left">TSC</td><td align="left">pPt-657529-<break/>pPt-656452</td><td align="left">H,P2</td><td char="." align="char">1.0</td><td char="." align="char">4.54</td><td char="." align="char">13.1</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">0.0&#x02013;5.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">pPt-473072</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">13.5</td><td char="." align="char">4.62</td><td char="." align="char">13.3</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">11.3&#x02013;15.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">pPt-471870</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">33.6</td><td char="." align="char">3.77</td><td char="." align="char">11.0</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">29.6&#x02013;34.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">X</td><td align="left">ED</td><td align="left">pPt-456962</td><td align="left">P2</td><td char="." align="char">15.6</td><td char="." align="char">4.00</td><td char="." align="char">11.6</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">15.6&#x02013;23.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TSC</td><td align="left">pPt-652232</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">72.2</td><td char="." align="char">3.43</td><td char="." align="char">10.1</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">71.7&#x02013;72.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">XII</td><td align="left">
<italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>
</td><td align="left">pPt-651718</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">49.2</td><td char="." align="char">4.88</td><td char="." align="char">14.0</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">42.0&#x02013;69.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">SCB<sub>RD</sub>
</td><td align="left">pPt-651718</td><td align="left">H</td><td char="." align="char">49.2</td><td char="." align="char">4.81</td><td char="." align="char">13.8</td><td char="&#x02013;" align="char">43.7&#x02013;72.6</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The most significant QTL for each trait is marked in bold</p><p>
<italic>H</italic> descending from both parents</p><p>
<sup>a</sup>P1-inherited from DG 03-226. P2-inherited from DG 06-5</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>In mapping population 11&#x02013;36, QTLs on chromosome V were significant for all six tested traits (mean data sets and most data sets from specific years, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> and Supplementary Table S3, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><p>QTLs for mean <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> were detected on chromosomes I, V, VIII, and XII (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The most significant QTL for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> was detected on chromosome I and was significant in three of four data sets, whereas the QTLs for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> on chromosomes V and XII were significant in all data sets.</p><p>The QTLs for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub> were significant in all three data sets on chromosomes I and V. The QTL peaks for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> and <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub> on chromosome V were in the same position (24.5&#x000a0;cM).</p><p>QTLs for SCB<sub>RD</sub> were detected on chromosomes V, VIII, and XII. The most significant QTL was on chromosome V, and the QTLs on chromosome XII were significant in all four data sets (SCB<sub>RD</sub> and SCB<sub>RD</sub>12&#x02013;14). QTL peaks for B<sub>RD</sub> and SCB<sub>RD</sub> on chromosomes VIII and XII were in the same positions, and the effects of these QTLs were similar. The QTL for SCB<sub>FB</sub> was detected on chromosome V and was significant for all data sets.</p><p>QTLs for ED were detected on chromosomes I, III, V, VII, VIII, and X. Three QTLs for ED, which were significant in all four data sets (ED and ED12&#x02013;ED14), were detected on chromosomes I, V and VIII. The most important QTL for ED was on chromosome V. The QTL localizations for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> and ED overlapped on chromosomes I and VIII. The QTL peaks for these traits were localized in the same positions.</p><p>The most important QTL for tuber starch content was detected on chromosome I, spanning a wide region of the chromosome, from 43.1 to 108.8&#x000a0;cM, with the peak at 75.7&#x000a0;cM. Another QTL for TSC, which was significant in all four data sets (TSC and TSC12-TSC14), was localized on chromosome IX. Two other QTLs for TSC also on chromosome IX were significant for mean TSC, TSC12, and TSC14. Three QTLs on chromosome III and the QTL on chromosome X were significant for mean TSC and 2&#x000a0;years of testing. Two QTLs on chromosome V were detected only in 1&#x000a0;year of testing.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>The candidate gene approach</title><p>The genetic positions of nine markers derived from candidate genes and their physical positions in the potato DM 1&#x02013;3 516 R44 (DM1-3) genome (v4.03) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://solanaceae.plantbiology.msu.edu/integrated_searches.shtml">http://solanaceae.plantbiology.msu.edu/integrated_searches.shtml</ext-link>) are presented in supplementary table S1. In our study, <italic>LipIII27</italic> was mapped to chromosome XII, which is a location different from the published location on chromosome II of the sequence used to design <italic>LipIII27</italic>. Only two of nine tested sequence-specific markers were significant for the analysed traits. The marker AGPaseS mapped within the QTLs for ED and TSC on chromosome I. AGPaseS explained 12.7% (LOD&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.40) of the variation for ED and 12% (LOD&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.14) of the variation for TSC. The marker for the <italic>POT32</italic> gene, located on chromosome VIII, was significant for ED and explained 11.8% (LOD&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.07) of the variation for this trait. None of the chosen markers were significantly related to blackspot bruising susceptibility evaluated with the two methods.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Both blackspot bruise susceptibility and ED depend on multiple factors. According to the analysis of variance in our study, genetic factors were the most important in their determination (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Simultaneously, the genotype&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;year interaction effects were larger than year effects for bruising susceptibility and enzymatic discoloration, but this trend was not found for starch content. Heritability in a broad sense was high for all tested traits but was the highest for TSC, followed by <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>, SCB<sub>RD</sub>, ED. and SCB<sub>FB</sub>.</p><p>Blackspot bruise susceptibility is a complex trait that cannot be ascribed to any single physiological parameter. The relationships among various physiological parameters and bruising susceptibility change depending on the impact method (L&#x000e6;rke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2000</xref>). Hence, determination of the overall mechanism of blackspot bruise susceptibility in our study included evaluation of the trait with two impact methods, rotating drum and falling bolt, in combination with evaluation of discoloration potential after tuber cutting (ED). The applied impact procedures affect both the physical and the biochemical properties of tubers. While the falling bolt method provided precise and standardized information on the tissue reaction to the impact of controlled strength, the rotating drum method, which was meant to mimic packing plant conditions, resulted in scoring the final bruising extent as an effect of many factors including the tissue reaction, tuber size, and shape.</p><p>Despite the comparisons that indicate considerable differences among test methods (Aeppli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1981</xref>; L&#x000e6;rke et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2002b</xref>), in our study, a highly significant correlation was detected between the falling bolt and the rotating drum methods. The most significant QTLs for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> and <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub> overlapped on chromosome I. Other important QTLs for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> and <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FD</sub> were detected for all data sets on chromosome V, with the same peak position (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). However, the rotating drum method detected an additional QTL for the trait on chromosome XII, which was significant in all tested years. The most important QTLs for blackspot bruise susceptibility were significant in three or four data sets, thus indicating that the trait was relatively stable across different vegetation seasons.</p><p>
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>QTL on chromosome I (<bold>a</bold>) and chromosome V (<bold>b</bold>) for mean&#x000a0;<italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>, SCB<sub>RD</sub>, SCB<sub>FB</sub>, ED and TSC. The threshold LOD score (LOD&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.1) is indicated by horizontal line</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="438_2017_1387_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e2940"/></fig>
</p><p>To clarify relationships between bruising susceptibility and tuber starch content, observed in breeding practice and confirmed in correlation analysis in our study, QTL mapping of starch content-corrected bruising susceptibility was conducted. The major effect QTL for bruising detected on chromosome I overlapped with the most significant QTL for tuber starch content and was not detected for starch-corrected bruising. The most significant QTLs for SCB<sub>RD</sub> and SCB<sub>FB</sub> were detected on chromosome V, and their effects were enhanced in comparison with those of the QTLs for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> and <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>. Partial overlap of QTLs for SCB<sub>RD</sub> and SCB<sub>FB</sub> and for TSC on chromosome V may result from linked genes that control both traits independently. The major QTL for bruising not related to starch content on chromosome V, and the two weaker QTLs on chromosomes VIII and XII provide information on the genetics of bruising susceptibility, rather than providing information to guide the selection of resistant clones independently of their starch content.</p><p>In our study, the QTL analysis of ED revealed the contribution of seven QTLs to the trait. These QTLs were located on six chromosomes: I, III, V, VII, VIII, and X. The QTL on chromosome VIII co-localized with the marker for <italic>POT32</italic>, thus confirming the results of Werij et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2007</xref>). Werij et al., in their first report of genetic factors underlying ED, detected QTLs for ED on chromosomes VIII (explaining 21% of total variance), I, and III. In our study, the major QTL for ED (explaining 20.9% of variance) was localized on chromosome V and co-localized with QTLs for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB,</sub> SCB<sub>RD</sub>, SCB<sub>FB</sub>, and TSC. The QTLs on chromosomes VII and X were specific for the trait and did not co-localize with QTLs for other analysed traits. The region on chromosome V, together with the QTL on chromosome VIII, is apparently essential for bruising and enzymatic discoloration formation, and may include genes affecting pigment synthesis both after bruising and after tissue cutting.</p><p>Possible candidate genes located on the DM1-3 physical map within a region corresponding to the QTLs for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub>, <italic>B</italic>
<sub>FB</sub>, SCB<sub>RD</sub>, SCB<sub>FB</sub>, and ED on chromosome V on genetic map 11&#x02013;36 were <italic>phenylalanine ammonia-lyase</italic> (PGSC000DMG400005492; chr05:36342746..36347409) and <italic>peroxidase</italic> (PGSC0003DMG400005279; chr05:42523943..42525912). The two genes encode proteins involved in the production and the oxidative reactions of phenolic compounds, respectively (Supplementary Table S4). However, the QTL region spans a large portion of the chromosome V with many other putative candidates including other peroxidases as well.</p><p>We identified ten QTLs for starch content on five chromosomes: I, III, V, IX, and X. The most important QTL for TSC was detected on chromosome I, spanning a wide region of the chromosome, from 43.1 to 108.8&#x000a0;cM. The effect of this QTL on the mean TSC explained 23.1% of the variance. The marker AGPaseS was located within this QTL and explained 12% of the TSC variation. <italic>AGPaseS</italic> is one of the three expressed genes encoding the large subunit of the <italic>AGPaseS</italic> gene, which converts G1P and ATP into PPi and ADP-glucose (Sonnewald and Kossmann <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2013</xref>). The location of <italic>AGPaseS</italic> has previously been reported on chromosome I and was associated with tuber starch content and starch yield (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2001</xref>). Some allele-specific sequences of this gene have been characterized in tetraploid potatoes and used as diagnostic markers for TSC (Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2013</xref>). The <italic>AGPaseS</italic> gene has also been mapped by &#x0015a;liwka and co-workers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2016</xref>) in a diploid mapping population in the major QTL for TSC on chromosome I. Several authors have detected similar QTLs for TSC/specific gravity, as in our study, on chromosome V in diploid (Freyre and Douches <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1994</xref>; Werij et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2012</xref>; Sch&#x000e4;fer-Pregl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1998</xref>; Manrique-Carpintero et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2015</xref>) and tetraploid potatoes (Bradshaw et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2008</xref>; McCord et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2011</xref>). Sch&#x000e4;fer-Pregl et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1998</xref>), Werij et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">2012</xref>) and Manrique-Carpintero et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2015</xref>) have also detected QTLs for TSC in positions similar to those observed in this study on chromosome IX.</p><p>None of the nine tested sequence-specific markers derived from genes chosen on the basis of published results (Werij et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">2007</xref>; Urbany et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">b</xref>; &#x0015a;liwka <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2016</xref>) were significant for blackspot bruise susceptibility in our study. Urbany et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">b</xref>) have combined a proteomics approach using genotype groups with high and low bruising susceptibility with association mapping. With this strategy, the coincidence between differentially expressed proteins and bruising-associated DNA-based markers specific for protein-coding genes was tested. The authors have suggest that, among others, <italic>polyphenol oxidase</italic> isoforms <italic>POT32</italic> and <italic>PHO1A</italic> are strong candidate genes for susceptibility to bruising. The lack of linkage in our study between QTLs for bruising susceptibility and the candidate genes identified by Urbany et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">b</xref>) might have resulted from use of different materials. The diploid parental forms used in our study were interspecific <italic>Solanum</italic> hybrids with several <italic>Solanum</italic> species in their pedigrees. The occurrence of gene alleles in diploid parents that are different from the alleles detected in tetraploid potato genotypes used by Urbany et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2011a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">b</xref>) may be a reason for the identification of different genomic regions that were important for bruising susceptibility.</p><p>Marker LipIII27, derived from <italic>triacylglycerol lipase III</italic> (SGN-U269327), was mapped in our study to chromosome XII, which was a different location from that of the published sequence on chromosome II. Urbany et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2011b</xref>), through comparison of the tuber proteomes of bruising-resistant and susceptible cultivars, have identified this gene as a candidate gene for bruising susceptibility. In our study, marker LipIII27 did not co-segregate with the QTL for <italic>B</italic>
<sub><italic>R</italic>D</sub> on chromosome XII. Another gene encoding triacylglycerol lipase III (PGSC0003DMG400028858; chr12:53245891..53249383) was located within the DM1-3 region corresponding to the QTL for <italic>B</italic>
<sub>RD</sub> (chr12:7849989..7850206&#x02014;Unknown) and might contribute to its effect.</p><p>Novel regions within the potato genome influencing bruising not related to starch content were identified on chromosomes V, VIII, and XII. They represent a substantial contribution to the understanding this complex and important potato quality trait. Our work also provides new information about regions on chromosomes V, VII, and X not previously identified as important for enzymatic discoloration formation. The results may provide a basis for further investigations to identify new candidate genes responsible for the analysed traits.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec12"><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="438_2017_1387_MOESM1_ESM.tif"><caption><p>
<bold>Fig. S1</bold>. Distribution of blackspot bruise susceptibility estimated by rotating drum (B<sub>RD</sub>, in scale from 0&#x02014;resistant to 100&#x02014;the most susceptible to bruising), blackspot bruise susceptibility estimated by falling bolt (B<sub>FB,</sub> in scale 1-5, where 1 = resistant to bruising, 5 = susceptible to bruising), starch-corrected blackspot bruise susceptibility estimated by rotating drum (SCB<sub>RD</sub>, obtained from B<sub>RD</sub> and TSC according Material and Methods), starch-corrected blackspot bruise susceptibility estimated by falling bolt (SCB<sub>FB</sub>, obtained from B<sub>FB</sub> and TSC according Material and Methods), enzymatic discoloration (ED, in scale 1-9, where 1 = the strongest discoloration, 9 = lack of discoloration), and tuber starch content (TSC, % FW) in population 11&#x02013;36. Histograms and the normal distribution curves were generated using STATISTICA for Windows (Stat Soft, Inc. and StatSoft Polska Ltd., Polska). The normality of distribution of phenotypic data was tested by the Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk test. &#x02642;- DG 03-226, &#x02640; DG06-5. (TIF 193 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="438_2017_1387_MOESM2_ESM.tif"><caption><p>
<bold>Fig. S2</bold>. Number of markers and length of chromosomes (cM) of genetic map constructed for population 11-36 (N = 149) (JoinMap<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>4. Van Ooijen 2006) (TIF 39 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="438_2017_1387_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary material 3 (XLSX 13 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="438_2017_1387_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary material 4 (XLSX 53 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="438_2017_1387_MOESM5_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary material 5 (DOCX 20 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="438_2017_1387_MOESM6_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary material 6 (DOCX 16 KB)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s00438-017-1387-0) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This research was supported by The National Science Centre in Poland, Grant UMO-2012/05/N/NZ9/01295. The authors thank Professor W. Marczewski for the critical reading of the manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>AHS participated in the design of the study, performed the crossing, conducted the phenotyping, detected the CAPS/SCAR markers, and drafted the manuscript. J&#x0015a; participated in the design of the study, constructed the genetic map, conducted the QTL analysis, and participated in the writing of the manuscript. HJ oversaw development of the mapping population and phenotyping experiments. EZG participated in the design of the study and participated in the writing of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aeppli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwendimann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Einfluss des Erntetermins auf die Blauempfindlichkeit von Kartoffelknollen. Zeitschrift fiir Acker- und Pflanzenbau</article-title><source>J Agro Crop Sci</source><year>1981</year><volume>150</volume><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>381</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akbari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenzl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Caig</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Carling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Uszynski</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohler</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmensiek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuchel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Howes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathmell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Huttner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity arrays technology (DArT) for high-throughput profiling of the hexaploid wheat genome</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>1409</fpage><lpage>1420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-006-0365-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17033786?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17033786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Anonymous</collab></person-group><source>Factsheet 1</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>Cowley</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Bruising and Damage Potato Marketing Board</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bachem</surname><given-names>CWB</given-names></name><name><surname>Speckmann</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Linde</surname><given-names>PCG</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhaggen</surname><given-names>FTM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zabeau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antisense expression of polyphenol-oxidase genes inhibits enzymatic browning of potato tubers</article-title><source>Biotechnology</source><year>1994</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1101</fpage><lpage>1127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt1194-1101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breeding strategies for clonally propagated potatoes</article-title><source>Potato genetics</source><year>1994</year><publisher-loc>Wallingford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CAB International</publisher-name><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>497</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pande</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Waugh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QTL mapping of yield, agronomic and quality traits in tetraploid potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> subsp.)</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2008</year><volume>1116</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-007-0659-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>McNabnay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic characterization of reduced melanin formation in tuber tissue of <italic>Solanum hjertingii</italic> and hybrids with cultivated diploids</article-title><source>Am J Potato Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02853556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A potato molecular-function map for carbohydrate metabolism and transport</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220051645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cobb AH (1999) A review of the physiology of bruising in potatoes. The 14th Triennial Conference of the European Association for Potato Research, Sorrento: pp&#x000a0;198&#x02013;199</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coetzer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Corsini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of enzymatic browning in potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.) by sense and antisense RNA from tomato polyphenol oxidase</article-title><source>J Agro Food Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>652</fpage><lpage>657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf001217f</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corsini</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavek</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in free and protein-bound tyrosine among potato genotypes and the relationship to internal blackspot resistance</article-title><source>Am Potato J</source><year>1992</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02852293</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corsini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors contributing to the blackspot bruise potential of Idaho potato fields</article-title><source>Am J Potato Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02854225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Culley</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introgression of the low browning trait from the wild Mexican species <italic>Solanum hjertingii</italic> into cultivated potato (<italic>S. tuberosum</italic> L.)</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2002</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1016099923261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackowiak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Corsini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blackspot pigment development of resistant and susceptible <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L. genotypes at harvest and during storage measured by three methods of evaluation</article-title><source>Am Potato J</source><year>1993</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02849309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doma&#x00144;ski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Michalak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimnoch-Guzowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation of blackspot susceptibility of the selected potato cultivars</article-title><source>Biuletyn IHAR</source><year>2007</year><volume>246</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>149</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Douches DD, Chase RW, Coombs J, Flecher K, Frank L, Driscoll J, Estellee E, Hammerschmidt R, Kirk W (2003) Seventy-second annual report by Michigan State University In: National Germplasm evaluation and enhancement report, 2001. In: Haynes KG (ed) seventy second annual report by cooperators. US Department of Agriculture Agricultural Research Service, ARS-162: 171&#x02013;199</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freyre</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Douches</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isoenzymatic identification of quantitative traits in crosses between heterozygous parents: mapping tuber traits in diploid potato (<italic>Solanum</italic> spp.)</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1994</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>764</fpage><lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00221127</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24190461?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24190461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemistry, biochemistry, and dietary role of potato polyphenols</article-title><source>A review. J Agric Food Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>45</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1523</fpage><lpage>1540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf960900s</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hara-Skrzypiec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakuczun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diploid potato hybrids as sources of resistance to blackspot bruising</article-title><source>Am J Potato Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12230-013-9319-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hironaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishibashi</surname><given-names>K-I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Change in bruise susceptibility of potatoes during storage</article-title><source>Res Bull Obihiro Univ</source><year>1996</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>39</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potatoes 1: factors affecting susceptibility to damage</article-title><source>Span</source><year>1980</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaccoud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Feinstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity arrays: a solid state technology for sequence information independent genotyping</article-title><source>Nucl Acids Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>E25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/29.4.e25</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11160945?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11160945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Croy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biphasic superoxide generation in potato tubers. A self-amplifying response to stress</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>131</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1440</fpage><lpage>1449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.013300</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12644693?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12644693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kloosterman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Oortwijn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Willigen</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><name><surname>America</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>RGF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachem</surname><given-names>CWB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From QTL to candidate gene: genetical genomics of simple and complex traits in potato using a pooling strategy</article-title><source>BMC Genom</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>158</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-11-158</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e6;rke</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brierley</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact&#x02014;induced blackspots and membrane deterioration in potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.) tubers</article-title><source>J Sci Food Agric</source><year>2000</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1332</fpage><lpage>1338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-0010(200007)80:9&#x0003c;1332::AID-JSFA645&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-T</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e6;rke</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Veierskov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blackspot bruise susceptibility of potato tubers during growth and storage determined by two different test methods</article-title><source>Potato Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02736114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e6;rke</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Veierskov</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colour of blackspot bruises in potato tubers during growth and storage compared to their discoloration potential</article-title><source>Postharvest Biol Technol</source><year>2002</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0925-5214(02)00008-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tacke</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofferbert</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;beck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Strahwald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Draffehn</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walkemeier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of candidate gene markers for marker-assisted selection of potato cultivars with improved tuber quality</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>126</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-012-2035-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23299900?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23299900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lunden</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Underldokerd over forholder mellom popetens spesifikka vekt og deres torvstoff og Stivelsesinhold Forhl</article-title><source>Forsok Landbruket</source><year>1956</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>107</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manrique-Carpintero</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Coombs</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Veilleux</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Buell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Douches</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic map and QTL analysis of agronomic traits in a diploid potato population using single nucleotide polymorphism markers</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>2566</fpage><lpage>2579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2014.10.0745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massey</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Varietal susceptibility of potatoes to internal blackspot</article-title><source>Am Potato J</source><year>1952</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02881660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCord</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosinski</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Clough</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Yencho</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Linkage mapping and QTL analysis of agronomic traits in tetraploid potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> subsp. <italic>tuberosum</italic>)</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci2010.02.0108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGarry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hole</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>RKL</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Internal damage in potato tubers: critical review</article-title><source>Postharvest Biol Technol</source><year>1996</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0925-5214(96)00006-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ophuis</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hesen</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroesbergen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of the temperature during handling on the occurrence of blue discolorations inside potato tubers</article-title><source>Europ Potato J</source><year>1958</year><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02364335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pavek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Corsini</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inheritance of blackspot bruise resistance in potato</article-title><source>Am Potato J</source><year>1993</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02848646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rigal</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauillard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Richard-Forget</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in the carotenoid content of apricot (<italic>Prunus armeniaca</italic>, var Bergeron) during enzymatic browning: &#x003b2;-carotene inhibition of chlorogenic acid degradation</article-title><source>J Sci Food Agric</source><year>2003</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>763</fpage><lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0010(20000501)80:6&#x0003c;763::AID-JSFA623&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-U</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers-Lewis</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods of reducing damage in main crop potatoes</article-title><source>Ann Appl Biol</source><year>1980</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>349</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;fer-Pregl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Concilio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hesselbach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovatti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Walkemeier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Thelen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of quantitative trait loci (QTLs) and quantitative trait alleles (QTAs) for potato tuber yield and starch content</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>834</fpage><lpage>846</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220050963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scudder</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Varietal susceptibility and the effect of potash on the incidence of blackspot in potatoes</article-title><source>Proc Am Soc Hortic Sci</source><year>1950</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>348</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000f8;nderk&#x000e6;r</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amoros</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Carboni</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Ambrosio</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>de la Cruz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Genova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Douches</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguiluz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Guzman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackett</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Maass</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mej&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Munive</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponce</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Waugh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachem</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagredo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Feingold</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Orjeda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Veilleux</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonierbale</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Milbourne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Construction of reference chromosome-scale pseudomolecules for potato: integrating the potato genome with genetic and physical maps</article-title><source>G3 Genes Genomes Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>2031</fpage><lpage>2047</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0015a;liwka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakuczun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chmielarz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara-Skrzypiec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomczy&#x00144;ska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimnoch-Guzowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new resistance gene against potato late blight originating from <italic>Solanum</italic> &#x000d7; <italic>michoacanum</italic> maps to potato chromosome VII</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-011-1715-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21987281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21987281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0015a;liwka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakuczun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chmielarz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara-Skrzypiec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomczy&#x00144;ska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimnoch-Guzowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Late blight resistance gene from <italic>Solanum ruiz</italic>-<italic>ceballosii</italic> is located on potato chromosome X and linked to violet flower colour</article-title><source>BMC Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>11</fpage><?supplied-pmid 22369123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22369123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0015a;liwka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>So&#x00142;tys-Kalina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Szajko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasilewicz-Flis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Strzelczyk-&#x0017b;yta</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimnoch-Guzowska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jakuczun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Marczewski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping of quantitative trait loci for tuber starch and leaf sucrose contents in diploid potato</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2016</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-015-2615-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26467474?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26467474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonnewald</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kossmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Starches-from current models to genetic engineering</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbi.12029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23190212?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23190212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Corsini</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurley</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwelle</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical differences of potato clones differing in blackspot susceptibility</article-title><source>Am Potato J</source><year>1985</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02853475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Davelaar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical potential of potato tubers to synthesize blackspot pigments in relation to their actual blackspot susceptibility</article-title><source>J Agro Food Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>4221</fpage><lpage>4226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf9608837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storey</surname><given-names>RMJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Vreugdenhil</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The harvested crop</article-title><source>Potato biology and biotechnology: advances and perspectives</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>468</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strehmel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Praeger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Konig</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fehrle</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Erban</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Geyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dongen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Time course effects on primary metabolism of potato (<italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L.) tuber tissue after mechanical impact</article-title><source>Postharvest Biol Technol</source><year>2010</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2009.12.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Thorton M, Bohl W (1995) Preventing potato bruise damage. University of Idaho Extension System. Agricultural Experiment Station. BUL 725 (Revised). pp&#x000a0;1&#x02013;16</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thygesen</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dry</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polyphenol oxidase in potato. A multigene family that exhibits differential expression patterns</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.2.525</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7480344?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7480344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urbany</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Berding</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Junghans</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Niehoff</surname><given-names>K-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckhard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofferbert</surname><given-names>H-R</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;beck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Strahwald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association genetics in <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> provides new insights into potato tuber bruising and enzymatic tissue discoloration</article-title><source>BMC Genom</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-12-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urbany</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Colby</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of natural variation of the potato tuber proteome reveals novel candidate genes for tuber bruising</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr2006186</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22047174?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22047174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Ooijen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><source>JoinMap &#x000ae; 4, Software for the calculation of the genetic linkage maps in experimental populations</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Wageningen</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kyazma BV</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vitti</surname><given-names>MCD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Miguel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kluge</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morretti</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Activity of enzymes associated with the enzymatic browning of minimally processed potatoes</article-title><source>Braz Arch Biol Technol</source><year>2011</year><volume>54/5</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1516-89132011000500016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>USDA approves next-generation GM potato</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2015</year><volume>33/1</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt0115-12</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wenzl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudrna</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaccoud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Huttner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kleinhofs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity arrays technology (DArT) for whole genome profiling of barley</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>9915</fpage><lpage>9920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0401076101</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15192146?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15192146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Werij</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kloosterman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Celis-Gambola</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ric de Vos</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>America</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>RGF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachem</surname><given-names>CWB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unravelling enzymatic discoloration in potato through a combined approach of candidate genes, QTL, and expression analysis</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-007-0560-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17492422?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17492422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Werij</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Furrer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Eck</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Visser</surname><given-names>RGF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachem</surname><given-names>CWB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A limited set of starch related genes explain several interrelated traits in potato</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2012</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-012-0651-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zg&#x000f3;rska K (1989) Biologiczne i ekologiczne czynniki warunkuj&#x00105;ce podatno&#x0015b;&#x00107; bulw ziemniaka na powstanie ciemnej plamisto&#x0015b;ci pouderzeniowej. Rozprawa habilitacyjna. 1&#x02013;91. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://solanaceae.plantbiology.msu.edu/integrated_searches.html">http://solanaceae.plantbiology.msu.edu/integrated_searches.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>