<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?origin publisher?><?properties no_embargo?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Theor Appl Genet</journal-id><journal-title>TAG. Theoretical and Applied Genetics. Theoretische Und Angewandte Genetik</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0040-5752</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-2242</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">1913174</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17273845</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">500</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-006-0500-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The construction of a <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic> LYC4 introgression line population and the identification of QTLs for resistance to <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finkers</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><address><phone>+31-317-484164</phone><fax>+31-317-483457</fax><email>Richard.Finkers@wur.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Heusden</surname><given-names>Adriaan W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Meijer-Dekens</surname><given-names>Fien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Kan</surname><given-names>Jan A. L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Maris</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>Pim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Graduate School Experimental Plant Sciences, Laboratory of Plant Breeding, Wageningen University, P.O. Box 386, 6700 AJ Wageningen, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Laboratory of Phytopathology, Wageningen University, P.O. Box 8025, 6700 EE Wageningen, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>De Ruiter Seeds, P.O. Box 1050, 2660 BB Bergschenhoek, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p>Communicated by R. Waugh.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>2</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>114</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1071</fpage><lpage>1080</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>12</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag 2007</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>Tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) is susceptible to grey mold (<italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic>). Partial resistance to this fungus has been identified in accessions of wild relatives of tomato such as <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic> LYC4. In a previous F<sub>2</sub> mapping study, three QTLs conferring resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> (<italic>Rbcq</italic>1, <italic>Rbcq</italic>2 and <italic>Rbcq</italic>4a) were identified. As it was probable that this study had not identified all QTLs involved in resistance we developed an introgression line (IL) population (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;30), each containing a <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> introgression in the <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. Moneymaker genetic background. On average each IL contained 5.2% of the <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> genome and together the lines provide an estimated coverage of 95%. The level of susceptibility to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> for each of the ILs was assessed in a greenhouse trial and compared to the susceptible parent <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. Moneymaker. The effect of the three previously identified loci could be confirmed and seven additional loci were detected. Some ILs contains multiple QTLs and the increased resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> in these ILs is in line with a completely additive model. We conclude that this set of QTLs offers good perspectives for breeding of <italic>B. cinerea</italic> resistant cultivars and that screening an IL population is more sensitive for detection of QTLs conferring resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> than the analysis in an F<sub>2</sub> population.</p><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s00122-006-0500-2) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag 2007</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p>Cultivated tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) displays only a limited amount of genotypic and phenotypic variation. Wild relatives of tomato are a useful source of variation for improving tomato (Rick <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1982</xref>). Several wild <italic>Solanum</italic> accessions are crossable with tomato but barriers like unilateral incompatibility, hybrid inviability and sterility sometimes have to be overcome to obtain viable progeny. After successful hybridization, the introgression of specific traits from wild <italic>Solanum</italic> is often laborious and time consuming. The practical feasibility of introgressing specific chromosomal regions can be hampered by reduced recombination and/or linkage drag. Despite these difficulties, many favorable traits such as disease resistances (Bai et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2003</xref>; Haanstra et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2000</xref>; Kabelka et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2002</xref>), tolerance to abiotic stresses (Foolad et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2003</xref>) and agronomic traits (Bernacchi et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1998</xref>; Eshed and Zamir <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1995</xref>; Lecomte et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2004</xref>) have been successfully introduced into tomato.</p><p>The focus of our research was the identification of quantitative trait loci (QTL) for increased disease resistance to <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> Pers:Fr [teleomorph <italic>Botryotinia fuckeliana</italic> (de Bary) Whetzel], a necrotrophic pathogenic fungus with a wide host range (Elad et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2004</xref>; Jarvis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1977</xref>). To date, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> is the principal model to study the interaction with <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. Glazebrook (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2005</xref>) reviewed the complex interactions between <italic>B. cinerea</italic> and mutants of <italic>A. thaliana</italic>. Denby et&#x000a0;al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2004</xref>) performed QTL mapping to elucidate the genetics of the interactions between <italic>B. cinerea</italic> and <italic>A. thaliana</italic> and reported the presence of multiple QTLs controlling resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>.</p><p>Heirloom and modern hybrid tomato cultivars are susceptible to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> although a number of cultivars show quantitative resistance. A high level of resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> has been identified in the wild accession <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic> LYC4 (ten Have et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2007</xref>; Urbasch <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">1986</xref>). To study the genetics of this resistance, an F<sub>2</sub> mapping population (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;174) of the cross between <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. Moneymaker and <italic>S.&#x000a0;habrochaites</italic> LYC4 has been developed (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>). Initially, two QTLs for resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> were identified in this F<sub>2</sub> mapping study (denominated <italic>Rbcq</italic>1 and <italic>Rbcq</italic>2, located on Chromosomes 1 and 2, respectively). A third QTL (<italic>Rbcq</italic>4 on Chromosome 4) that showed an interaction with <italic>Rbcq</italic>2 was detected in segregating BC<sub>2</sub>S<sub>1</sub> progenies (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>).</p><p>A limitation of QTL-mapping in interspecific segregating F<sub>2</sub> populations is the wide variation in plant growth rate, morphology and physiology but also the presence of major QTLs that potentially disguise QTLs with minor effects. Furthermore, it is difficult to do repeated tests as each F<sub>2</sub> plant is a unique genotype. Alternatively, a genetic library consisting of a set of introgression lines (IL) can be used for mapping purposes. Each IL ideally harbors a single, defined chromosome segment that originates from the donor species in an otherwise uniform genetic background (Zamir <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">2001</xref>). Such lines facilitate the identification of QTLs because phenotypic variation between the line and the control cultivar is directly associated with the introgressed segment. Each line typically contains more than 95% of the recurrent cultivated parent genome and minor quantitative effects can easily be identified by comparison with the recurrent parent. Minimizing negative epistatic effects caused by other regions of the wild genome may lead to identification of novel QTLs (Eshed and Zamir <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1995</xref>). Each line is homozygous and immortal and thus allows multiple testing (in multiple environments). Finally, sterility problems are less prominent due to the fact that the genetic constitution of each line is largely identical to the cultivated variety, which is usually very fit and fertile.</p><p>The first IL population was developed in wheat (Wehrhahn and Allard <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1965</xref>), but the majority of IL populations have been developed during the last decade by means of marker-assisted selection (MAS) using different marker systems and breeding approaches. In tomato, ILs have been developed from <italic>Solanum pennellii</italic> LA716 (Eshed and Zamir <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1994</xref>), <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> LA1777 (Monforte and Tanksley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2000a</xref>), <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> LA407 (Francis et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2001</xref>) and <italic>S. lycopersicoides</italic> LA2951 (Canady et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2005</xref>). ILs in tomato has proved to be extremely helpful in the identification of QTLs (Eshed and Zamir <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1995</xref>; Rousseaux et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2005</xref>), fine mapping of QTLs (Eshed and Zamir <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1996</xref>; Ku et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2001</xref>; Monforte et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2001</xref>; Monforte and Tanksley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2000b</xref>) and cloning of QTLs (Frary et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2000</xref>; Fridman et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2000</xref>; Liu et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2002</xref>). Besides tomato, IL populations have been developed for barley (von Korff et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">2004</xref>), cabbage (Ramsay et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">1996</xref>), lettuce (Jeuken and Lindhout <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2004</xref>), melon (Eduardo et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2005</xref>), rice (Lin et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">1998</xref>) and wheat (Pestova et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2001</xref>).</p><p>In general, IL populations have been developed by MAS using co-dominant SSR and RFLP markers but this is labor intensive and results in a lower marker density (ranging from 62 to 350 markers) compared to using AFLP markers (757 markers for lettuce). The advantage of SSR and RFLP markers, however, is that their positions are usually known, allowing the selection of a core set of markers covering the complete genome. AFLPs are high throughput markers but often with an unknown position and unequal coverage of the genome. Clustering of AFLP markers is a potential pitfall for certain enzyme combinations (Haanstra et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1999</xref>), however, in other cases AFLP markers identified introgressions that remained undetected using RFLP markers (Bonnema et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2002</xref>).</p><p>Our research aimed at verification of the QTLs for resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> that have previously been identified in an interspecific F<sub>2</sub> population (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>) and the identification of additional QTLs. This paper describes the development of an IL population (BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub>) of <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> LYC4 in the genetic background of an indeterminate growing tomato by using AFLP as the platform for MAS. Each of the developed ILs was screened for its level of susceptibility to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant material and development of the ILs</title><p>The parents of the present study were the <italic>B. cinerea</italic> susceptible, indeterminate growing <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. Moneymaker (hereafter referred to as <italic>SL</italic>) and the resistant <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> LYC4 (ten Have et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2007</xref>; Urbasch <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">1986</xref>; hereafter referred to as <italic>SH</italic>, syn. <italic>Lycopersicon</italic><italic>hirsutum</italic>). Seeds of <italic>SL</italic> were in stock of Wageningen University and seeds of <italic>SH</italic> were obtained from the Institute for Plant Genetics and Crop Plant Research, Gatersleben, Germany. One F<sub>1</sub> plant was self pollinated to obtain F<sub>2</sub> seeds and also backcrossed to <italic>SL</italic> to obtain BC<sub>1</sub> seeds. The F<sub>2</sub> seeds were sown to grow an F<sub>2</sub> population (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;174), which has previously been used for the construction of a genetic linkage map (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>). The BC<sub>1 </sub>was used to develop the IL population (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Backcross and selection strategy used to obtain the <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> LYC4 IL population introgressed in the <italic>S.  lycopersicum</italic> cv. Moneymaker genetic background. Starting from BC<sub>2</sub>, marker assisted selection (MAS) was applied by using AFLP markers. The BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub> population was screened with a combination of AFLP and CAPS markers</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2006_500_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Marker analysis</title><p>Genomic DNA was isolated from two young (rolled up) leaves using a CTAB based protocol according to Steward and Via (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">1993</xref>), adjusted for high throughput DNA isolation using 1&#x000a0;ml micronic tubes (Micronic BV, Lelystad, The Netherlands) and ground using a Retsch 300&#x000a0;mm shaker at maximum speed (Retsch BV, Ochten, The Netherlands).</p><p>AFLP&#x02122; analysis was done according to Vos et&#x000a0;al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">1995</xref>). AFLP fragments were resolved on a LI-COR 4200&#x000a0;DNA sequencer, essentially following the method published by Myburg et&#x000a0;al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2001</xref>). The selective <italic>Pst</italic> primer was labeled with an IRD700 or IRD 800 fluorescent label. AFLP gel images were scored using AFLP-Quantar&#x02122; Pro software (Keygene, Wageningen, The Netherlands). Primer and adapter sequences have been described by Bai et&#x000a0;al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2003</xref>).</p><p>CAPS primers were obtained from the &#x0201c;Solanaceae Genomics Website&#x0201d; (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sgn.cornell.edu">http://www.sgn.cornell.edu</ext-link>) or designed on sequences of genomic or cDNA clones available from the same source. Polymorphisms between <italic>SL</italic> and <italic>SH</italic> were determined using the CAPS digestion approach described by Bai et&#x000a0;al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2004</xref>). Marker sequences, PCR conditions, and specific restriction endonucleases used for genotyping are presented in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. PCR products were separated using a 2.5% agarose gel.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Estimated mean disease incidence (DI), lesion size (LS) and lesion growth (LG) in the introgression lines (IL) and control lines. Means of each trait for each IL were compared to the mean of <italic>S. lycopersicum </italic>cv. Moneymaker (<italic>SL</italic>) using a Dunnett test and significant differences are marked with *&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 or **&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">IL</th><th align="left">QTL</th><th align="left"><italic>N</italic><sup>a</sup></th><th align="left">Disease incidence (%)</th><th align="left">Lesion size (mm)</th><th align="left">Lesion growth rate (mm/day)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1&#x02013;1</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">41</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">65&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.7</td><td char="." align="char">56</td><td char="." align="char">5.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1&#x02013;2</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>1?</td><td char="." align="char">40</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.7</td><td char="." align="char">33</td><td char="." align="char">3.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1&#x02013;3 / 3&#x02013;3</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>9b</td><td char="." align="char">29</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.1**</td><td char="." align="char">30**</td><td char="." align="char">1.7**</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1&#x02013;4</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>9b</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">37&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.4**</td><td char="." align="char">34</td><td char="." align="char">2.4*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2&#x02013;1</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>2</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">41&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.4**</td><td char="." align="char">30*</td><td char="." align="char">3.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2&#x02013;2</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>2</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">37&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.5**</td><td char="." align="char">26*</td><td char="." align="char">2.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2&#x02013;3</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">58&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.5</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="." align="char">3.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3&#x02013;1</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>3</td><td char="." align="char">43</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.6</td><td char="." align="char">41</td><td char="." align="char">2.8*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3&#x02013;2</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>3</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">46&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.5*</td><td char="." align="char">35</td><td char="." align="char">4.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4&#x02013;1</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>4a</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">41&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.4**</td><td char="." align="char">26**</td><td char="." align="char">2.5*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4&#x02013;2</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>4a</td><td char="." align="char">42</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.7*</td><td char="." align="char">33</td><td char="." align="char">3.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4&#x02013;3</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>4b, <italic>Rbcq</italic>9a</td><td char="." align="char">20</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">51&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.6</td><td char="." align="char">29</td><td char="." align="char">2.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5&#x02013;1</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">61&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.6</td><td char="." align="char">53</td><td char="." align="char">4.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5&#x02013;2</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">43</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">69&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.6</td><td char="." align="char">64</td><td char="." align="char">5.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6&#x02013;1</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>6</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">49&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.5*</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="." align="char">3.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6&#x02013;2 / 7&#x02013;2</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">55&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.3</td><td char="." align="char">39</td><td char="." align="char">3.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6&#x02013;3</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">79&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.5</td><td char="." align="char">49</td><td char="." align="char">4.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7&#x02013;1</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">50&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.4</td><td char="." align="char">35</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8&#x02013;3</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">59&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.5</td><td char="." align="char">43</td><td char="." align="char">3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9&#x02013;1</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>9a</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">69&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.5</td><td char="." align="char">34*</td><td char="." align="char">3.0*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9&#x02013;2</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>9b</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">49&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.4*</td><td char="." align="char">33</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10&#x02013;1</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">43</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">60&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.6</td><td char="." align="char">47</td><td char="." align="char">4.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10&#x02013;2</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">62&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.5</td><td char="." align="char">49</td><td char="." align="char">4.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10&#x02013;3</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">70&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.4</td><td char="." align="char">53</td><td char="." align="char">4.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">10&#x02013;4</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">76&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.6</td><td char="." align="char">47</td><td char="." align="char">4.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11&#x02013;1 / 9&#x02013;3</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>9b</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">48&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.5*</td><td char="." align="char">36</td><td char="." align="char">4.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11&#x02013;2</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>11</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">34&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.4**</td><td char="." align="char">33*</td><td char="." align="char">3.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12&#x02013;1</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>12</td><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">51&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.4</td><td char="." align="char">35</td><td char="." align="char">4.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12&#x02013;2</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>12</td><td char="." align="char">43</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">52&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.4</td><td char="." align="char">37</td><td char="." align="char">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12&#x02013;3</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>9b,  <italic>Rbcq</italic>12</td><td char="." align="char">24</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">24&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.6**</td><td char="." align="char">21**</td><td char="." align="char">2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>SL</italic></td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">156</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">73&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.0</td><td char="." align="char">46</td><td char="." align="char">4.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>SH</italic></td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">44</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">3&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.4**</td><td char="." align="char">ND<sup>b</sup></td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">BRC-5</td><td align="left"><italic>Rbcq</italic>1 <italic>and</italic><italic>Rbcq</italic>4b</td><td char="." align="char">39</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">15&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.9**</td><td char="." align="char">20*</td><td char="." align="char">ND<sup>c</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Durinta</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char">68</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.5**</td><td char="." align="char">29**</td><td char="." align="char">2.3**</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup><italic>N </italic>Number of inoculation sites</p><p><sup>b</sup>Only one outgrowing lesion, observation excluded from the statistical analysis</p><p><sup>c</sup>First observation of outgrowing lesions was after 12&#x000a0;days, therefore lesion growth could not be determined</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Graphical genotyping</title><p>Graphical representation of the genotypes for each backcross population and the ILs were obtained using the software program GGT (van Berloo <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">1999</xref>). For the calculation of introgression size and genome percentages, the half-intervals flanking a marker locus were considered to be of the same introgression as implemented by the software. Missing marker data were estimated from the flanking markers; if these had identical genotypes then the missing marker was assumed to have the same genotype as the two flanking makers. If the two flanking makers had contrasting genotypes, the missing data were recorded as truly missing.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Experimental design and disease evaluations</title><p>To assess susceptibility, 16 incomplete randomized blocks were used in which in total 11 replications for each IL were tested. Each block contained at least two <italic>SL</italic> plants and one plant of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. Durinta, a commercial cultivar producing truss tomatoes with a fair level of resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. Six weeks after sowing, plants were transplanted into the soil of two greenhouse compartments with a set day/night regime of 19/15&#x000b0;C and a photo period of 16&#x000a0;h light. After 11&#x000a0;weeks, two incisions of 15&#x000a0;mm were made into the stem of each plant at approximately 1.5 and 1.7&#x000a0;m height using a knife. Each wound was inoculated with a 1&#x000a0;cm<sup>2</sup> agar plug containing a culture of <italic>B.&#x000a0;cinerea</italic> B05.10 (Benito et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1998</xref>) and subsequently covered with tape. Two weeks later a third and fourth inoculation were performed on the same plants below the initial inoculation sites. Plants were watered at the beginning of the evening to maintain a humid climate during the night. Disease parameters were measured nine and 12&#x000a0;days after inoculation. The parameters were: disease incidence as percentage of growing lesions (DI), lesion size (using a caliper) after 12&#x000a0;days minus the size of the inoculation wound (15&#x000a0;mm, LS), and lesion growth rate expressed as the difference in lesion size between nine and 12&#x000a0;days post inoculation expressed in mm/day (LG).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS 12.0 software (SPSS Inc., Chicago, USA). Using a general linearized model (GLM) procedure, means for each IL/trait were estimated according to the following models: DI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;constant&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;IL&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;block&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;inoculation position, LS&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;constant&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;IL&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;block&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;inoculation position and LG&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;constant&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;IL&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;block&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;inoculation position</p><p>Mean values of each trait were compared to the mean of the susceptible control genotype <italic>SL</italic> using a Dunnett test (Dunnett <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1955</xref>) and probabilities smaller then 0.05 were considered as significant. To analyze LS and LG, a square root transformation was applied to normalize the data of both traits. Correlations between traits were calculated using the Pearson correlation coefficient.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>IL population</title><p>An introgression line (IL) population of <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> LYC4 (<italic>SH</italic>) in the genetic background of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. Moneymaker (<italic>SL</italic>) was generated according to the procedure illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. One F<sub>1</sub> plant from the cross between <italic>SL</italic> and <italic>SH</italic> was backcrossed to <italic>SL</italic>. Subsequently a random set of 14 BC<sub>1</sub> plants was backcrossed to <italic>SL</italic> to obtain a BC<sub>2</sub> progeny (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;59). All BC<sub>2</sub> plants were genotyped and a selected set was backcrossed to <italic>SL</italic>. This set was chosen in such a way that the combined introgressions covered as much of the <italic>SH</italic> genome as possible and that each alien chromosome was represented by three ILs. The backcrossing and selection procedure was repeated until BC<sub>5</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Eventually, 31 BC<sub>5</sub> plants were selected, mainly containing one or two heterozygous introgressions. These 31 plants were self pollinated. Up to 12 plants of each of the 31 BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>1</sub> families were screened with AFLP markers to obtain a selected BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub> progeny (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;44) homozygous for the (single) <italic>SH</italic> introgressions. The selected BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub> progeny was grown once more to allow a more detailed marker screen in which 457 AFLP markers (result of 10 AFLP enzyme/primer combinations) and 34 CAPS markers were analyzed. The total of 457 AFLP markers reported here is a twofold increase in marker density compared to the F<sub>2</sub> population (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>). The marker screen resulted in the selection of a core set of 30&#x000a0;ILs with the highest possible coverage of the <italic>SH</italic> genome (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) in as few lines as possible. Each selected line was self pollinated to obtain BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>3</sub> seeds.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Graphical representation of the genotypes of the <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. Moneymaker&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>S.&#x000a0;habrochaites</italic> LYC4 introgression line population. All chromosomes are drawn to scale in 20&#x000a0;cM segments according to the F<sub>2</sub> genetic linkage map (Finkers et al.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18"> 2007</xref>) or estimated using the <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>S. pennellii</italic> linkage map (Tanksley et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">1992</xref>; http://www.sgn.cornell.edu). Genetic length of the chromosome 9 introgressions was estimated from recombination frequencies of BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub> marker data. Homozygous introgressions from <italic>S.&#x000a0;habrochaites</italic> are in black and heterozygous introgressions in <italic>gray</italic></p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2006_500_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p>The IL library consists of 15 lines with a single introgression, ten lines with two introgressions, four lines with three introgressions while one IL contained four introgressions. The proportion of <italic>SH</italic> genome ranged from 20 (1.7%) to 122&#x000a0;cM (10.6%) with an average of 60&#x000a0;cM (5.2%). The IL library covers 95% of the F<sub>2</sub> AFLP linkage map (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>), which however, does not cover the entire <italic>SH</italic> genome. Additional CAPS analysis on Chromosomes 3 (top of the short arm), 4 (top of the short arm), 5 (long arm) and 9 (top of the short arm) provided markers that were nearer to the telomeres than the most distal AFLP marker. The sizes of the latter introgressions were estimated, using the high density RFLP map (Tanksley et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">1992</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sgn.cornell.edu">http://www.sgn.cornell.edu</ext-link>) and were estimated to be 20, 50 and 32&#x000a0;cM for Chromosome 4, 5 and 9, respectively. The size of the introgression at the top arm of Chromosome 3 could not be estimated.</p><p>No ILs homozygous <italic>SH</italic> for the top of Chromosome 3 (IL3-1) was obtained. Plants homozygous <italic>SH</italic> for IL5-1 and 5-2 failed to set seeds and these lines could only be maintained as heterozygotes for these introgressions. No ILs were obtained containing an introgression of Chromosome 1 harboring CAPS marker TG460, the distal end of the long arm of Chromosome 2 and the top of the short arm of Chromosome 8. Introgressions with the top of the short arm of Chromosome 7 and 9 were present in multiple ILs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Selection against introgression on Chromosome 7 was hampered by an excess of <italic>SH</italic> alleles. Introgressions for the top of Chromosome 9 could only be detected during the more detailed CAPS marker screen of the BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub> ILs, as mentioned above. Introgressions homozygous <italic>SH</italic> in this region were present in 30% of the ILs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Susceptibility of introgression lines to <italic>B. cinerea</italic></title><p>The population of 30 ILs was grown in the greenhouse to the adult stage, inoculated with <italic>B. cinerea</italic> and evaluated for disease symptoms. On 9 and 12&#x000a0;days after inoculation the quantitative susceptibility to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> was quantified by determining the parameters disease incidence (DI), lesion size (LS) and lesion growth rate (LG), the results of which are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The resistant parent <italic>SH</italic> hardly showed symptoms while 73% of the inoculation sites on the susceptible control <italic>SL</italic> developed into an expanding lesion with a mean LS of 46&#x000a0;mm and a LG of 4.6&#x000a0;mm/day. In total 14 ILs showed reduced susceptibility compared to <italic>SL</italic> and thus contain QTLs increasing resistance. Overall, 12 of these 14&#x000a0;ILs showed a significantly lower DI (24&#x02013;49%), seven a significantly reduced LS (21&#x02013;33&#x000a0;mm) and five a significantly lower LG (1.7&#x02013;3.0&#x000a0;mm/day). Two lines, IL4-1 and IL1-3/3&#x02013;3, showed a significant reduction of all three parameters (DI, LS and LG). The commercial cultivar <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. Durinta, with a fair level of resistance, also showed lower disease parameters compared to the susceptible control, <italic>SL</italic>.</p><p>Pearson correlation coefficients were calculated to asses the correlations between DI, LS and LG. Significant correlations (<italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) were present between DI and LS (<italic>r</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.82); DI and LG (<italic>r</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.65) and LG and LS (<italic>r</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.82) and are in agreement with the presence of lines significantly reduced for more than one disease parameter. The high correlations show that most of the QTLs alleles of <italic>SH</italic> result in the reduction of all three parameters (DI, LS and LG). We designated the identified QTLs as resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> QTL (<italic>Rbcq</italic>; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) followed by the number of the chromosome on which they are located, an analogous to the designation used for describing the QTLs in the F<sub>2</sub> population (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>).</p><p>Three QTLs, <italic>Rbcq</italic>2, <italic>Rbcq</italic>4a (previously named <italic>Rbcq</italic>4; Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>) and <italic>Rbcq</italic>6, unambiguously conferred increased resistance. The lower levels of susceptibility in IL3-1 and IL3-2, containing overlapping introgressions, are most probably the effect of one QTL, i.e., <italic>Rbcq</italic>3.</p><p>Others ILs those are less susceptible to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> than the reference <italic>SL</italic> contain multiple introgressions, thus complicating the allocation of resistance loci to specific chromosomes. In some cases, the most likely location can be deduced. For instance, IL9-2 contains introgressions of Chromosome 6 and 9. The introgression on Chromosome 6 is also present in IL6-3, which is equally susceptible to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> as <italic>SL</italic>. Thus, the increased resistance of IL9-2 is likely caused by a QTL on Chromosome 9 and there is no contribution from Chromosome 6. Furthermore, IL9-1 is partly overlapping with IL9-2 and has a similar LS as IL9-2, but a DI similar to <italic>SL</italic>. Therefore, we propose that two QTLs are present in IL9-2, <italic>Rbcq</italic>9a causing reduced LS in both IL9-1 and IL9-2 and <italic>Rbcq</italic>9b causing reduced DI only in IL9-2. By analogous deductions, the reduced disease symptoms in IL1-3/3-3, 1-4, 11&#x02013;2 and 12&#x02013;3 are likely to be caused by their Chromosome 9 introgressions which partly overlap the introgressions of IL9-1 and IL9-2. However, IL12-3 is significantly more resistant then IL9-2 suggesting an additional effect on Chromosome 12 (<italic>Rbcq</italic>12). The reduced susceptibility in IL12-1 and IL12-2, although statistically not significant, suggest that <italic>Rbcq</italic>12 might be located in the region overlapping between IL12-1, 12&#x02013;2 and 12&#x02013;3. IL11-2 has a significantly lower DI than IL9-1 and the introgression on Chromosome 9 is smaller then in IL9-1. Therefore the lower DI is probably conferred by another QTL: <italic>Rbcq</italic>11. IL1-3/3-3 and 1&#x02013;4 are not significantly less susceptible then IL9-2 therefore the resistance in these lines is probably conferred by the presence of <italic>Rbcq</italic>9b.</p><p>Due to the absence of <italic>SH</italic> alleles for the CAPS marker TG460, which is linked to <italic>Rbcq</italic>1, it is unclear whether this locus is represented within the IL population. However, from previous experiments (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>) a highly resistant BC<sub>2</sub>S<sub>2</sub> genotype was selected, denominated BRC-5, containing three homozygous introgressions on Chromosomes 1 (including <italic>Rbcq</italic>1 and homozygous <italic>SH</italic> for TG460), 4 and 10, representing in total 18% of the <italic>SH</italic> genome (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). BRC-5 was the least susceptible line showing a DI of only 15%. No decreased susceptibility has been identified in any of the four Chromosome 10&#x000a0;ILs even though these ILs cover the entire length of Chromosome 10. It is therefore unlikely that the Chromosome 10 introgression contributes to the resistance of BRC-5. The Chromosome 4 introgression of BRC-5 does not overlap with the previously mapped position of <italic>Rbcq</italic>4a. IL4-3 showed a decreased susceptibility, although statistically not significant, suggesting the presence of a second QTL <italic>Rbcq</italic>4b. The combined effect of <italic>Rbcq</italic>1 and <italic>Rbcq</italic>4b is likely responsible for the increased resistance of BRC-5, however, this needs to be confirmed by experimental evidence.</p><p>In summary, ten QTLs were identified all increasing resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. The evidence for QTLs <italic>Rbcq</italic>4b, <italic>Rbcq</italic>11 and <italic>Rbcq</italic>12 is only circumstantial due to the presence of <italic>Rbcq</italic>9a/b, and their effects should be confirmed in the absence of the introgression on Chromosome 9.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>IL population</title><p>An IL population (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;30) was developed of <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> in the genetic background of the cultivated tomato <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>. During generation of the IL population, 239 additional AFLP markers were used which were not identified during analysis of the initial F<sub>2</sub> population (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>) providing a nearly two-fold increase in marker density in spite of the use of the same AFLP primer combinations. A similar increase in marker density was observed during the development of a lettuce IL population (Jeuken and Lindhout <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2004</xref>), mainly due to the reduced complexity of the AFLP-patterns of the ILs, thereby enabling the scoring of closely migrating or faint amplification products.</p><p>Although <italic>Pst</italic>I/<italic>Mse</italic>I markers are more equally distributed over the tomato chromosomes compared to <italic>Eco</italic>RI/<italic>Mse</italic>I markers (Haanstra et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1999</xref>), ten randomly chosen primer combinations did not provide complete genome coverage. Compared to the high density RFLP reference map (Tanksley et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">1992</xref>) about 32% of the genetic length of Chromosome 9 was not detected during the AFLP screenings. In an IL population of <italic>S. pennellii</italic> that was developed using 350 RFLP markers (Eshed and Zamir <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1994</xref>), Chromosome 10 introgressions remained unnoticed using RFLP markers but could be detected using AFLP markers (Bonnema et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2002</xref>). A combination of AFLP with CAPS or SSR markers is a good strategy to develop introgression lines with a full genome coverage.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Reproductive behavior of the IL population</title><p>IL populations are generally believed to be less prone to reproductive problems, yet the development of some specific ILs has proven to be cumbersome. No ILs containing the top of Chromosome 8 were obtained. ILs generated with <italic>S. pennellii</italic> LA716 (Eshed and Zamir <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1995</xref>) and <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> LA1777 (Monforte and Tanksley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2000a</xref>), as progenitors appeared to lack lines with introgressions for a small region on the short arm of Chromosome 8. Attempts to fixate this region of the wild relative remained unsuccessful, presumably due to the presence of a male sterility locus. Compared to both previously mentioned studies, a larger portion of Chromosome 8 is lacking in our population. Developing additional ILs covering at least part of this region should be feasible.</p><p>Plants those were homozygous <italic>SH</italic> for introgressions on the long arm of Chromosome 5 failed to set seeds. The <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> LA1777 IL population (Monforte and Tanksley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2000a</xref>) contains a QTL for reduced self seed set on Chromosome 5, possibly causing zygotic incompatibility resulting in early seed abortion (Moyle and Graham <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2005</xref>). The occurrence of homozygous introgressions of Chromosome 7 and 9 was skewed towards homozygous <italic>SH</italic> resulting in the presence of these introgressions in multiple ILs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Similar observations were made in other advanced interspecific tomato populations involving wild relatives such as <italic>S. galapagense</italic> (Paran et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">1995</xref>), <italic>L. peruvianum</italic> (Fulton et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1997</xref>) and <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> (Monforte and Tanksley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2000a</xref>).</p><p>One of the advantages of an IL population is that each line has a high resemblance to <italic>SL</italic> and therefore sterility problems are expected to be minimal. For the development of a full set of homozygous ILs, however, extra effort must be undertaken to select lines containing introgressions flanking deleterious genes (e.g., on Chromosomes 5 and 8) or select against overrepresentation of introgressions on which an advantageous gene is located (e.g., on Chromosomes 7 and 9).</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Confirmation of previously identified loci for resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic></title><p>Two different disease assays were applied to quantify resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic>. Initially, QTLs were detected in an F<sub>2</sub> population and confirmed in BC<sub>2</sub>S<sub>1</sub> families (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>) using a bioassay on stem segments (ten Have et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2007</xref>) leading to the identification of three QTLs: <italic>Rbcq</italic>1 reducing LG, <italic>Rbcq</italic>2 and <italic>Rbcq</italic>4a both reducing DI (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>). Stem resistance in the IL population was quantified in whole adult plants; wound inoculated with a <italic>B. cinerea</italic> containing agar plug and disease progress was recorded during a longer period. In all tests, <italic>Rbcq</italic>2 and <italic>Rbcq</italic>4a conferred resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> showing the robustness of each QTL. <italic>Rbcq</italic>1 could not be confirmed in the IL population, but it remains uncertain whether <italic>Rbcq</italic>1 was represented in the ILs tested. Marker analysis showed that the introgression in lines IL1-2 and IL1-3/3-3 do not overlap. A small <italic>SH</italic> introgression for Chromosome 1 is therefore not represented within the ILs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). <italic>Rbcq</italic>1 is however, certainly present in BRC-5, the most resistant introgression line tested. Thus, all three previously identified loci for increased resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> were detected using both bioassays.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Identification of additional resistance loci using an IL population</title><p>The main purpose of developing an IL population and assessing its resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> was to identify additional QTLs to the ones previously identified in the F<sub>2</sub> population (Finkers et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2007</xref>). As resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> is polygenic, multiple minor quantitative effects can easily be overlooked in an interspecific F<sub>2</sub> population. Seven additional QTLs were detected in the IL population: <italic>Rbcq</italic>3, <italic>Rbcq</italic>4b, <italic>Rbcq</italic>6, <italic>Rbcq</italic>9a, <italic>Rbcq</italic>9b, <italic>Rbcq</italic>11 and <italic>Rbcq</italic>12. No indications for any of the seven new QTLs were found in the analysis of the F<sub>2</sub> population, even when reexamining these data (data not shown). Most newly identified loci were less efficient in reducing symptoms compared to <italic>Rbcq</italic>2. These &#x0201c;minor loci&#x0201d; might have been identified in a larger F<sub>2</sub> population, but they were readily detected in an IL population. Also in an <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RIL population, a larger number of QTLs for resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> were reported, some of which were considered to be specific for distinct pathogen isolates (Denby et&#x000a0;al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2004</xref>). This IL population provides an excellent tool to study the possible existence of isolate-specific QTLs in tomato and study resistance levels in different environments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Potential of pyramiding QTLs</title><p>None of the QTLs was sufficient to confer the full level of resistance of the <italic>SH</italic> parent. To reach such a level QTLs have to be combined. Pyramiding of ten QTLs is practically impossible and probably not necessary. An example of an additive effect is illustrated by <italic>Rbcq9b</italic> and <italic>Rbcq</italic>12. IL12-1 and IL12-2 with only <italic>Rbcq</italic>12 had on average a 22% lower DI (although not significant) while IL9-2 with <italic>Rbcq</italic>9b had a DI significantly decreased by 24%, compared to <italic>SL</italic>. Assuming an additive model, the combination of <italic>Rbcq</italic>9b and <italic>Rbcq</italic>12 would lead to a decrease in DI by 46%. The observation that IL12-3, combining both <italic>Rbcq</italic>9b and <italic>Rbcq</italic>12, had a DI that was 49% lower is in agreement with this additive model. These results show the potential of pyramiding multiple QTLs in order to get an elevated resistance to <italic>B. cinerea</italic> but redundancy of QTLs for resistance is expected. The IL population is an excellent tool to combine multiple QTLs and study their interaction in order to select the best set of QTLs for exploitation in a commercial breeding program. More detailed metabolome, proteome and transcriptome analysis of each of the ILs may provide insight in the resistance mechanism conferred by each QTL.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="N0x1cf7af0N0x2d247f0" content-type="local-data"><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.
</p><media xlink:href="122_2006_500_MOESM1_ESM.doc" id="MOESM1" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p><bold>Table S1</bold>: Primer sequences, lengths of PCR products and enzymes revealing a polymorphism for CAPS/SCAR markers. (DOC 227 kb)
</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This project is sponsored by grants of the Dutch Technology Foundation (STW, grant no. WBI.4172) and De Ruiter Seeds R&#x00026;D BV, The Netherlands. The authors would like to thank Petra van den Berg, Pham Thi Thu Huong and Roeland Voorrips for their contribution and valuable suggestions.</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulst</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer Dekens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnema</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QTLs for tomato powdery mildew resistance (<italic>Oidium lycopersici</italic>) in <italic>Lycopersicon parviflorum</italic> G1.1601 co-localize with two qualitative powdery mildew resistance genes</article-title><source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source><year>2003</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>176</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bai Y, Huang CC, van der Hulst R, Meijer Dekens F, Bonnema G, Lindhout P (2003) QTLs for tomato powdery mildew resistance (Oidium lycopersici) in Lycopersicon parviflorum G1.1601 co-localize with two qualitative powdery mildew resistance genes. Mol Plant Microbe Interact 16:169&#x02013;176 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12575751</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulst</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A set of simple PCR markers converted from sequence specific RFLP markers on tomato Chromosomes 9 to 12</article-title><source>Mol Breed</source><year>2004</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:MOLB.0000022535.82602.79</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bai Y, Feng XH, van der Hulst R, Lindhout P (2004) A set of simple PCR markers converted from sequence specific RFLP markers on tomato Chromosomes 9 to 12. Mol Breed 13:281&#x02013;287 </citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benito</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>ten Have</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x02018;t Klooster</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>JAL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal and plant gene expression during synchronized infection of tomato leaves by <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic></article-title><source>Eur J Plant Pathol</source><year>1998</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1008698116106</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Benito EP, ten Have A, van &#x02018;t Klooster JW, van Kan JAL (1998) Fungal and plant gene expression during synchronized infection of tomato leaves by Botrytis cinerea. Eur J Plant Pathol 104:207&#x02013;220 </citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernacchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck Bunn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Petiard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhlig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advanced backcross QTL analysis in tomato. I. Identification of QTLs for traits of agronomic importance from <italic>Lycopersicon hirsutum</italic></article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220050908</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bernacchi D, Beck Bunn T, Eshed Y, Lopez J, Petiard V, Uhlig J, Zamir D, Tanksley S (1998) Advanced backcross QTL analysis in tomato. I. Identification of QTLs for traits of agronomic importance from Lycopersicon hirsutum. Theor Appl Genet 97:381&#x02013;397 </citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonnema</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AFLPs mark different genomic regions compared with RFLPs: a case study in tomato</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2002</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g01-145</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bonnema G, Berg P, Lindhout P (2002) AFLPs mark different genomic regions compared with RFLPs: a case study in tomato. Genome 45:217&#x02013;221 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11962617</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Canady</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meglic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chetelat</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A library of <italic>Solanum lycopersicoides</italic> introgression lines in cultivated tomato</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2005</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g05-032</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Canady MA, Meglic V, Chetelat RT (2005) A library of Solanum lycopersicoides introgression lines in cultivated tomato. Genome 48:685&#x02013;697 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16094436</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denby</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kliebenstein</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> susceptibility loci in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2004</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0960-7412.2004.02059.x</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Denby KJ, Kumar P, Kliebenstein DJ (2004) Identification of Botrytis cinerea susceptibility loci in Arabidopsis thaliana. Plant J 38:473&#x02013;486 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15086796</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunnett</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A multiple comparison procedure for comparing several treatments with a control</article-title><source>J Am Stat Assoc</source><year>1955</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1096</fpage><lpage>1121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2281208</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Dunnett CW (1955) A multiple comparison procedure for comparing several treatments with a control. J Am Stat Assoc 50:1096&#x02013;1121 </citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eduardo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Arus</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Monforte</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a genomic library of near isogenic lines (NILs) in melon (<italic>Cucumis melo </italic>L.) from the exotic accession PI161375</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2005</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-005-0116-y</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Eduardo I, Arus P, Monforte AJ (2005) Development of a genomic library of near isogenic lines (NILs) in melon (Cucumis melo L.) from the exotic accession PI161375. Theor Appl Genet 112:139&#x02013;148 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16208502</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elad</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tudzynski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Delen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic>Botrytis</italic>: biology, pathology and control</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kluwer</publisher-name></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Elad Y, Williamson B, Tudzynski P, Delen N (2004) Botrytis: biology, pathology and control. Kluwer, Dordrecht </citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genomic library of <italic>Lycopersicon pennellii</italic> in <italic>L. e</italic>sculentum: a tool for fine mapping of genes</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>1994</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00022516</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Eshed Y, Zamir D (1994) A genomic library of Lycopersicon pennellii in L. esculentum: a tool for fine mapping of genes. Euphytica 79:175&#x02013;179 </citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An introgression line population of <italic>Lycopersicon pennellii</italic> in the cultivated tomato enables the identification and fine mapping of yield-associated QTL</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1995</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>1147</fpage><lpage>1162</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Eshed Y, Zamir D (1995) An introgression line population of Lycopersicon pennellii in the cultivated tomato enables the identification and fine mapping of yield-associated QTL. Genetics 141:1147&#x02013;1162 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8582620</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Less-than-additive epistatic interactions of quantitative trait loci in tomato</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1996</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>1807</fpage><lpage>1817</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Eshed Y, Zamir D (1996) Less-than-additive epistatic interactions of quantitative trait loci in tomato. Genetics 143:1807&#x02013;1817 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8844166</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><citation citation-type="other">Finkers R, van den Berg P, van Berloo R, ten Have A, van Heusden AW, van Kan JAL, Lindhout P (2007) Three QTLs for <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> resistance in tomato. Theor Appl Genet.  org/10.1007/s00122-006-0458-0</citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foolad</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Subbiah</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of drought tolerance during seed germination in tomato: inheritance and QTL mapping</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2003</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g03-035</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Foolad MR, Zhang LP, Subbiah P (2003) Genetics of drought tolerance during seed germination in tomato: inheritance and QTL mapping. Genome 46:536&#x02013;545 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12897861</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabelka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Franchino</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>St. Clair</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance to bacterial canker in tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon hirsutum</italic> LA407) and its progeny derived from crosses to <italic>L. esculentum</italic></article-title><source>Plant Dis</source><year>2001</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>1171</fpage><lpage>1176</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Francis DM, Kabelka E, Bell J, Franchino B, St. Clair D (2001) Resistance to bacterial canker in tomato (Lycopersicon hirsutum LA407) and its progeny derived from crosses to L. esculentum. Plant Dis 85:1171&#x02013;1176 </citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesbitt</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandillo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Knaap Evd</surname></name><name><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Elber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Alpert</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>fw2.2</italic>: a quantitative trait locus key to the evolution of tomato fruit size</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.289.5476.85</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Frary A, Nesbitt TC, Grandillo S, Knaap Evd, Cong B, Liu J, Meller J, Elber R, Alpert KB, Tanksley SD (2000) fw2.2: a quantitative trait locus key to the evolution of tomato fruit size. Science 289:85&#x02013;88 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10884229</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fridman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pleban</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A recombination hotspot delimits a wild-species quantitative trait locus for tomato sugar content to 484&#x000a0;bp within an invertase gene</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>4718</fpage><lpage>4723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.9.4718</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Fridman E, Pleban T, Zamir D (2000) A recombination hotspot delimits a wild-species quantitative trait locus for tomato sugar content to 484&#x000a0;bp within an invertase gene. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 97:4718&#x02013;4723 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10781077</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck Bunn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Emmatty</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Eshed</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Petiard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhlig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QTL analysis of an advanced backcross of <italic>Lycopersicon peruvianum</italic> to the cultivated tomato and comparisons with QTLs found in other wild species</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1997</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>881</fpage><lpage>894</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220050639</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Fulton TM, Beck Bunn T, Emmatty D, Eshed Y, Lopez J, Petiard V, Uhlig J, Zamir D, Tanksley SD (1997) QTL analysis of an advanced backcross of Lycopersicon peruvianum to the cultivated tomato and comparisons with QTLs found in other wild species. Theor Appl Genet 95:881&#x02013;894 </citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glazebrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contrasting mechanisms of defense against biotrophic and necrotrophic pathogens</article-title><source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source><year>2005</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.43.040204.135923</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Glazebrook J (2005) Contrasting mechanisms of defense against biotrophic and necrotrophic pathogens. Annu Rev Phytopathol 43:205&#x02013;227 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16078883</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haanstra</surname><given-names>JPW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbakel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer Dekens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Odinot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heusden</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Peleman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An integrated high density RFLP-AFLP map of tomato based on two <italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic> &#x000d7; <italic>L. pennellii</italic> F<sub>2</sub> populations</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220051231</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Haanstra JPW, Wye C, Verbakel H, Meijer Dekens F, van den Berg P, Odinot P, van Heusden AW, Tanksley S, Lindhout P, Peleman J (1999) An integrated high density RFLP-AFLP map of tomato based on two Lycopersicon esculentum &#x000d7; L. pennellii F2 populations. Theor Appl Genet 99:254&#x02013;271 </citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haanstra</surname><given-names>JPW</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer Dekens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauge</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Seetanah</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Joosten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wit</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping strategy for resistance genes against <italic>Cladosporium fulvum</italic> on the short arm of chromosome 1 of tomato: <italic>Cf-ECP5</italic> near the <italic>Hcr9</italic> Milky Way cluster</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220051528</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Haanstra JPW, Meijer Dekens F, Lauge R, Seetanah DC, Joosten M, de Wit P, Lindhout P (2000) Mapping strategy for resistance genes against Cladosporium fulvum on the short arm of chromosome 1 of tomato: Cf-ECP5 near the Hcr9 Milky Way cluster. Theor Appl Genet 101:661&#x02013;668 </citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><citation citation-type="other">Jarvis WR (1977) <italic>Botryotinia</italic> and <italic>Botrytis</italic> species: taxonomy, physiology, and pathogenicity; a guide to the literature. Monograph 15</citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeuken</surname><given-names>MJW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The development of lettuce backcross inbred lines (BILs) for exploitation of the <italic>Lactuca saligna</italic> (wild lettuce) germplasm</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>394</fpage><lpage>401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-004-1643-7</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Jeuken MJW, Lindhout P (2004) The development of lettuce backcross inbred lines (BILs) for exploitation of the Lactuca saligna (wild lettuce) germplasm. Theor Appl Genet 109:394&#x02013;401 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15103409</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabelka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Franchino</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two loci from <italic>Lycopersicon hirsutum</italic> LA407 confer resistance to strains of <italic>Clavibacter michiganensis</italic> subsp. <italic>michiganensis</italic></article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2002</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>510</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kabelka E, Franchino B, Francis DM (2002) Two loci from Lycopersicon hirsutum LA407 confer resistance to strains of Clavibacter michiganensis subsp. michiganensis. Phytopathology 92:504&#x02013;510 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18943024</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Doganlar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploitation of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>-tomato synteny to construct a high-resolution map of the ovate-containing region in tomato chromosome 2</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2001</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/gen-44-3-470</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ku HM, Liu J, Doganlar S, Tanksley SD (2001) Exploitation of Arabidopsis-tomato synteny to construct a high-resolution map of the ovate-containing region in tomato chromosome 2. Genome 44:470&#x02013;475 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11444707</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lecomte</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Saliba Colombani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez Jimenez</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Buret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine mapping of QTLs of chromosome 2 affecting the fruit architecture and composition of tomato</article-title><source>Mol Breed</source><year>2004</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:MOLB.0000012325.77844.0c</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lecomte L, Saliba Colombani V, Gautier A, Gomez Jimenez MC, Duffe P, Buret M, Causse M (2004) Fine mapping of QTLs of chromosome 2 affecting the fruit architecture and composition of tomato. Mol Breed 13:1&#x02013;14 </citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping quantitative trait loci controlling seed dormancy and heading date in rice, <italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L., using backcross inbred lines</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1998</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220050831</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lin SY, Sasaki T, Yano M (1998) Mapping quantitative trait loci controlling seed dormancy and heading date in rice, Oryza sativa L., using backcross inbred lines. Theor Appl Genet 96:997&#x02013;1003 </citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Eck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new class of regulatory genes underlying the cause of pear-shaped tomato fruit</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>13302</fpage><lpage>13306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.162485999</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Liu JP, Van Eck J, Cong B, Tanksley SD (2002) A new class of regulatory genes underlying the cause of pear-shaped tomato fruit. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 99:13302&#x02013;13306 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12242331</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monforte</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a set of near isogenic and backcross recombinant inbred lines containing most of the <italic>Lycopersicon hirsutum</italic> genome in a <italic>L. esculentum</italic> genetic background: a tool for gene mapping and gene discovery</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2000a</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/gen-43-5-803</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Monforte AJ, Tanksley SD (2000a) Development of a set of near isogenic and backcross recombinant inbred lines containing most of the Lycopersicon hirsutum genome in a L. esculentum genetic background: a tool for gene mapping and gene discovery. Genome 43:803&#x02013;813 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11081970</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monforte</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine mapping of a quantitative trait locus (QTL) from <italic>Lycopersicon hirsutum</italic> chromosome 1 affecting fruit characteristics and agronomic traits: breaking linkage among QTLs affecting different traits and dissection of heterosis for yield</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2000b</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220050061</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Monforte AJ, Tanksley SD (2000b) Fine mapping of a quantitative trait locus (QTL) from Lycopersicon hirsutum chromosome 1 affecting fruit characteristics and agronomic traits: breaking linkage among QTLs affecting different traits and dissection of heterosis for yield. Theor Appl Genet 100:471&#x02013;479 </citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monforte</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of a set of allelic QTL-NILs for chromosome 4 of tomato: deductions about natural variation and implications for germplasm utilization</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>572</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220051684</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Monforte AJ, Friedman E, Zamir D, Tanksley SD (2001) Comparison of a set of allelic QTL-NILs for chromosome 4 of tomato: deductions about natural variation and implications for germplasm utilization. Theor Appl Genet 102:572&#x02013;590 </citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moyle</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of hybrid incompatibility between <italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic> and <italic>L. hirsutum</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2005</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.104.029546</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Moyle LC, Graham EB (2005) Genetics of hybrid incompatibility between Lycopersicon esculentum and L. hirsutum. Genetics 169:355&#x02013;373 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466436</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Myburg</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Remington</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Malley</surname><given-names>O&#x02019; DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sederoff</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Whetten</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-throughput AFLP analysis using infrared dye-labeled primers and an automated DNA sequencer</article-title><source>Biotechniques</source><year>2001</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>357</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Myburg AA, Remington DL, O&#x02019; Malley DM, Sederoff RR, Whetten RW (2001) High-throughput AFLP analysis using infrared dye-labeled primers and an automated DNA sequencer. Biotechniques 30:348&#x02013;357 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11233604</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paran</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recombinant inbred lines for genetic mapping in tomato</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1995</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00222001</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Paran I, Goldman I, Tanksley SD, Zamir D (1995) Recombinant inbred lines for genetic mapping in tomato. Theor Appl Genet 90:542&#x02013;548 </citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pestsova</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Borner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a set of <italic>Triticum aestivum&#x02013;Aegilops tauschii</italic> introgression lines</article-title><source>Hereditas</source><year>2001</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1601-5223.2001.00139.x</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pestsova EG, Borner A, Roder MS (2001) Development of a set of Triticum aestivum&#x02013;Aegilops tauschii introgression lines. Hereditas 135:139&#x02013;143 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12152326</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohuon</surname><given-names>EJR</given-names></name><name><surname>Arthur</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lydiate</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kearsey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The construction of a substitution library of recombinant backcross lines in <italic>Brassica oleracea</italic> for the precision mapping of quantitative trait loci</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>1996</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>558</fpage><lpage>567</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ramsay LD, Jennings DE, Bohuon EJR, Arthur AE, Lydiate DJ, Kearsey MJ, Marshall DF (1996) The construction of a substitution library of recombinant backcross lines in Brassica oleracea for the precision mapping of quantitative trait loci. Genome 39:558&#x02013;567 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18469917</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Vasil</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scowcroft</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Frey</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The potential of exotic germplasm for tomato improvement</article-title><source>Plant improvement and somatic cell genetics</source><year>1982</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rick CM (1982) The potential of exotic germplasm for tomato improvement. In: Vasil IK, Scowcroft WR, Frey KJ (eds) Plant improvement and somatic cell genetics. Academic, New York 1982:1&#x02013;28 </citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rousseaux</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chetelat</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QTL analysis of fruit antioxidants in tomato using <italic>Lycopersicon pennellii</italic> introgression lines</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2005</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>1396</fpage><lpage>1408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-005-0071-7</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rousseaux MC, Jones CM, Adams D, Chetelat R, Bennett A, Powell A (2005) QTL analysis of fruit antioxidants in tomato using Lycopersicon pennellii introgression lines. Theor Appl Genet 111:1396&#x02013;1408 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16177901</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steward</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Via</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid CTAB DNA isolation technique useful for RAPD fingerprinting and other PCR applications</article-title><source>Biotechniques</source><year>1993</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>748</fpage><lpage>750</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Steward CN, Via LE (1993) A rapid CTAB DNA isolation technique useful for RAPD fingerprinting and other PCR applications. Biotechniques 14:748&#x02013;750 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8512694</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganal</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonierbale</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Broun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandillo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High density molecular linkage maps of the tomato and potato genomes</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1992</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>1160</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tanksley SD, Ganal MW, Prince JP, de Vicente MC, Bonierbale MW, Broun P, Fulton TM, Giovannoni JJ, Grandillo S, Martin GB (1992) High density molecular linkage maps of the tomato and potato genomes. Genetics 132:1141&#x02013;1160 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1360934</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>ten Have</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van Berloo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>van Kan</surname><given-names>JAL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Partial stem and leaf resistance against the fungal pathogen <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> in wild relatives of tomato</article-title><source>Eur J Plant Pathol</source><year>2007</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10658-006-9081-9</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">ten Have A, van Berloo R, Lindhout P, van Kan JAL (2007) Partial stem and leaf resistance against the fungal pathogen Botrytis cinerea in wild relatives of tomato. Eur J Plant Pathol 117:153&#x02013;166  </citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urbasch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistenz verschiedener Kultur- und Wildtomatenpflanzen (<italic>Lycopersicon spp</italic>.) gegen&#x000fc;ber <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> Pers</article-title><source>J Phytopathol</source><year>1986</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>344</fpage><lpage>351</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Urbasch I (1986) Resistenz verschiedener Kultur- und Wildtomatenpflanzen (Lycopersicon spp.) gegen&#x000fc;ber Botrytis cinerea Pers. J Phytopathol 116:344&#x02013;351 </citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berloo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GGT: software for the display of graphical genotypes</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>1999</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jhered/90.2.328</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">van Berloo R (1999) GGT: software for the display of graphical genotypes. J Hered 90:328&#x02013;329 </citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of candidate introgression lines using an exotic barley accession (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> ssp. spontaneum) as donor</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>1736</fpage><lpage>1745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-004-1818-2</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">von Korff M, Wang H, Leon J, Pillen K (2004) Development of candidate introgression lines using an exotic barley accession (Hordeum vulgare ssp. spontaneum) as donor. Theor Appl Genet 109:1736&#x02013;1745 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15502912</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleeker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reijans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frijters</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peleman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuiper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AFLP: a new technique for DNA fingerprinting</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1995</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>4407</fpage><lpage>4414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/23.21.4407</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vos P, Hogers R, Bleeker M, Reijans M, van de Lee T, Hornes M, Frijters A, Pot J, Peleman J, Kuiper M (1995) AFLP: a new technique for DNA fingerprinting. Nucleic Acids Res 23:4407&#x02013;4414 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7501463</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wehrhahn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The detection and measurement of the effects of individual genes involved in inheritance of a quantitative character in wheat</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1965</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>119</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wehrhahn C, Allard RW (1965) The detection and measurement of the effects of individual genes involved in inheritance of a quantitative character in wheat. Genetics 51:109&#x02013;119 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17248230</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving plant breeding with exotic genetic libraries</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35103589</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Zamir D (2001) Improving plant breeding with exotic genetic libraries. Nat Rev Genet 2:983&#x02013;989 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11733751</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s00122-006-0500-2) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>