<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?origin publisher?><?properties no_embargo?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Theor Appl Genet</journal-id><journal-title>TAG. Theoretical and Applied Genetics. Theoretische Und Angewandte Genetik</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0040-5752</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-2242</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2271080</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18231773</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">708</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-007-0708-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mapping and characterization of novel parthenocarpy QTLs in tomato</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gorguet</surname><given-names>Benoit</given-names></name><address><email>benoit.gorguet@wur.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eggink</surname><given-names>Pieter Martijn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oca&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>Aparna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schipper</surname><given-names>Danny</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Finkers</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>Richard G. F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Heusden</surname><given-names>Adriaan W.</given-names></name><address><phone>+31-317-487284</phone><fax>+31-317-483457</fax><email>sjaak.vanheusden@wur.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1">Graduate School of Experimental Plant Sciences, Wageningen UR Plant Breeding, PO Box 386, 6700AJ Wageningen, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="com"><p>Communicated by I. Paran.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>116</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>755</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2007</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2008</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>Parthenocarpy is the development of the fruit in absence of pollination and/or fertilization. In tomato, parthenocarpy is considered as an attractive trait to solve the problems of fruit setting under unfavorable conditions. We studied the genetics of parthenocarpy in two different lines, IL5-1 and IVT-line 1, both carrying <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic> chromosome segments. Parthenocarpy in IL5-1 is under the control of two QTLs, one on chromosome 4 (<italic>pat4.1</italic>) and one on chromosome 5 (<italic>pat5.1</italic>). IVT-line 1 also contains two parthenocarpy QTLs, one on chromosome 4 (<italic>pat4.2</italic>) and one on chromosome 9 (<italic>pat9.1</italic>). In addition, we identified one stigma exsertion locus in IL5-1, located on the long arm of chromosome 5 (<italic>se5.1</italic>). It is likely that <italic>pat4.1</italic>, from IL5-1 and <italic>pat4.2</italic>, from IVT-line 1, both located near the centromere of chromosome 4 are allelic. By making use of the microsynteny between tomato and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> in this genetic region, we identified <italic>ARF8</italic> as a potential candidate gene for these two QTLs. ARF8 is known to act as an inhibitor for further carpel development in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, in absence of pollination/fertilization. Expression of an aberrant form of the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>ARF8</italic> gene, in tomato, has been found to cause parthenocarpy. This candidate gene approach may lead to the first isolation of a parthenocarpy gene in tomato and will allow further use in several crop species.</p></abstract><custom-meta-wrap><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag 2008</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-wrap></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p>In normal fruit development, the initiation of fruit set depends on the successful completion of pollination and fertilization. However, these processes depend on narrow environmental constrains (Picken <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">1984</xref>). Normal pollen production is restricted to a specific temperature range, and mechanical vibration of the flowers, either manually or by bees is necessary to ensure pollen shedding. In tomato, failure to set fruit is therefore a common phenomenon under certain field conditions (high humidity combined with low or high temperatures) and in unheated greenhouses or tunnels during Winter or early Spring cultivation (George et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">1984</xref>). Parthenocarpic fruit development, which is the growth of the ovary into a seedless fruit in the absence of pollination and/or fertilization, offers an opportunity to overcome this problem of poor fruit set under unfavorable conditions. In tomato three sources (distinct varieties) of natural parthenocarpy have been widely studied because of their perspectives for practical application to produce seedless fruits (reviewed by Gorguet et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2005</xref>): <italic>Soressi</italic> or <italic>Montfavet 191</italic> (<italic>pat</italic>), <italic>Severianin</italic> (<italic>pat</italic>-<italic>2</italic>) and <italic>RP75/59</italic> (<italic>pat</italic>-<italic>3/pat</italic>-<italic>4</italic>). In addition, two other sources of parthenocarpy in tomato, IVT-line 1 and 2 (Zijlstra <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1985</xref>) were found to give a higher and more stable level of parthenocarpy than <italic>Soressi</italic> and <italic>Severianin</italic>. IVT-line 1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) was developed in the early 1980s from an interspecific cross between <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic> (accession unknown) and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>, followed by several generations of backcrosses and by at least one selfing (Zijlstra <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1985</xref>). This line was developed specifically for parthenocarpy and it was thought to be controlled by one single gene. Parthenocarpy in IVT-line 2 originated from <italic>S. peruvianum</italic> and was assumed to be polygenic (Zijlstra <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1985</xref>). To date, the only mapped gene for parthenocarpy in tomato is <italic>pat</italic>, localized on the long arm of chromosome 3 (Beraldi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2004</xref>). However, even in conditions favorable for seed production, <italic>pat</italic> genotypes give a very low seed set (Mazzucato et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>), which makes it less attractive for practical breeding.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Seedless fruits observed on IL5-1 (<italic>left picture</italic>) and IVT-line 1 (<italic>right picture</italic>). Stigma exsertion observed on IL5-1 (<italic>middle picture</italic>)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2007_708_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p>Recently Finkers et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2007b</xref>) have developed a set of introgression lines (ILs) for <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> accession LYC4 in the <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. Moneymaker genetic background. Parthenocarpic fruit development and stigma exsertion were observed in one of the ILs (IL5-1; R. Finkers, personal communication).</p><p>In this study we characterized and mapped four novel parthenocarpy QTLs responsible for the seedless fruit development in IL5-1 and IVT-line 1. In addition the position of the stigma exsertion locus, in IL5-1, was also identified. The syntenic relationship between two parthenocarpy QTLs and the <italic>ARF8 Arabidopsis</italic> parthenocarpy gene (Goetz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>) was investigated. <italic>ARF8</italic> was determined as a likely candidate for these two parthenocarpy QTLs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant materials</title><p>For the mapping procedure in <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> LYC4, we originally used two BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>1</sub> populations that were part of the IL development program of Finkers et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2007b</xref>). These ILs contain chromosome fragment(s) of <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> LYC4, hereafter referred to as <italic>SH</italic>, in a <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. Moneymaker genetic background, hereafter referred to as <italic>SL</italic>. IL5-1 carries an <italic>SH</italic> introgression on the short arm of chromosome 4 and the complete chromosome 5 from <italic>SH</italic>. IL5-2 carries the long arm of chromosome 5 from <italic>SH</italic>. The two BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>1</sub> populations had previously been used for the selection of IL5-1 and IL5-2 (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2007b</xref>) and will be hereafter denoted as populations 5-1 and 5-2. Population 5-1, segregating for the short arm of chromosome 4 and the entire chromosome 5, consisted of 174 plants. Population 5-2, segregating for the long arm of chromosome 5, was composed of 183 plants. Plants were grown in Summer/Autumn 2005 in a heated glasshouse in Wageningen, The Netherlands, under controlled conditions (temperature always superior to 15&#x000b0;C). The average length of days during fruit set was &#x0223c;12&#x000a0;h. Subsequently a set of relevant BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub> recombinant plants were selected and further studied in Spring/Summer 2006, with an average length of days during fruit set of &#x0223c;14&#x000a0;h, and in Winter 2006/2007, with an average length of days during fruit set of &#x0223c;9&#x000a0;h and lower light intensity than in Summer.</p><p>For the mapping of parthenocarpy genes in IVT-line 1, we used an F<sub>2</sub> population coming from a single cross between the parthenocarpic IVT-line 1, and the nonparthenocarpic <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. Moneymaker. The F<sub>2</sub> population of this cross was composed of 160 plants and grown under controlled conditions, as above, in Spring 2006, with an average length of days during fruit set of &#x0223c;13&#x000a0;h.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Flower morphology</title><p>Fresh flowers were collected and analyzed at pre-anthesis on the third flower truss of BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>1</sub> plants. In this experiment pre-anthesis was defined as the flower stage in which the sepals start opening, and the color of the anther cone start turning from green to yellow. Style length, ovary length and stamen length were measured to the nearest 0.1&#x000a0;mm. Stigma exsertion was determined by subtracting stamen length from the sum of the style length plus the ovary length, as presented by Chen and Tanksley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2004</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Characterization of parthenocarpy</title><p>In facultative parthenocarpy, the development of seedless fruits can only be observed on the flowers that are not pollinated. To minimize pollination, flowers were not vibrated. To classify the level of parthenocarpy, the first five fruit clusters of a plant were analyzed for fruit size, number of fruits, number of flowers and the presence of seeds. The diameter of the fruits was measured to the nearest 1&#x000a0;mm, using a slide caliper. Fruits were scored at mature stage. The trait parthenocarpy was calculated quantitatively, as the percentage of parthenocarpic fruits from the total number of flowers over the first five clusters. This percentage is hereafter referred to as &#x0201c;parthenocarpy level&#x0201d;. To be considered parthenocarpic, the fruits had to be fully seedless, of the same shape than a seeded fruit (round and not angular), of the same color aspect (shiny and not pale), and have jelly filled locules.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>DNA extraction</title><p>Two DNA isolation techniques were used. For most experiments total DNA was isolated from two young tomato leaves by using a CTAB DNA isolation method as described by Steward and Via (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">1993</xref>), adjusted for 96-well format using 1.2&#x000a0;ml COSTAR cluster tubes (Corning Incorporated). Leaf samples were crushed using a Retsch 300&#x000a0;mm shaker at 30&#x000a0;r/s for 45&#x000a0;s (Retsch BV).</p><p>DNA isolation, for the selection of relevant BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub> progenies, was performed by a rapid alkaline (NaOH) based extraction method (Wang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1993</xref>). This method was up-scaled to a 96-well format as described by Gorguet et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Molecular marker analysis</title><p>Genotypes were determined using PCR-based markers. Primers and enzymes of CAPS and SCAR markers TG441, CD64, CD31, TACL2, TG538, TG318 have been described by Coaker and Francis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2004</xref>) and TG358 by Brouwer and St. Clair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2004</xref>). Other CAPS and SCAR markers were generated based on RFLP and COS marker sequences previously mapped by Tanksley et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1992</xref>) or Fulton et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2002</xref>). The sequences of the RFLP and COS markers were available on the &#x0201c;SOL Genomics Network&#x0201d; (Mueller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2005</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sgn.cornell.edu">http://sgn.cornell.edu</ext-link>). The conversion of RFLP and COS markers into CAPS and SCAR markers was performed as described in Gorguet et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2006</xref>). Details on these markers are given in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Each PCR reaction (25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l) contained &#x0223c;20&#x000a0;ng of genomic DNA, 1&#x000d7; PCR-reaction buffer, 0.4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M of each forward and reverse primer, 0.2&#x000a0;mM dNTPs and 0.5&#x000a0;U Taq polymerase in miliQ water. PCR conditions were: hot start of 5&#x000a0;min at 94&#x000b0;C, followed by 39 cycles of 30&#x000a0;s at 94&#x000b0;C, 30&#x000a0;s at annealing temperature (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), 30&#x000a0;s at 72&#x000b0;C and a final extension of 7&#x000a0;min at 72&#x000b0;C. About 3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of PCR product was digested in a total volume of 15&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l for at least 3&#x000a0;h with 2&#x000a0;U of restriction enzyme. After digestion, DNA fragments were separated on a 2% agarose gel. Reverse primers for microsatellite markers were labeled with IRD700 or IRD800. PCR reactions (10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l) were prepared in the same proportion as described for CAPS markers, only with 0.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M forward and labeled reverse primer. PCR conditions were: hot start of 3&#x000a0;min at 94&#x000b0;C, followed by 30 cycles of 45&#x000a0;s at 94&#x000b0;C, 45&#x000a0;s at 53&#x000b0;C, 1&#x000a0;min at 72&#x000b0;C and a final extension of 3&#x000a0;min at 72&#x000b0;C. After the PCR, 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l LI-COR loading dye was added and the IRD700 labeled fragments were analyzed on a LI-COR 4200 DNA sequencer, essentially following the method published by Myburg and Remington (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2000</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Primer sequences and PCR reaction parameters for CAPS and SCAR markers</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Name</th><th align="left">Primer (5&#x02032;&#x02013;3&#x02032;) forward, reverse</th><th align="left">Size<sup>a </sup>(bp)</th><th align="left">TA<sup>b </sup>(&#x000b0;C)</th><th align="left">Chr<sup>c</sup></th><th align="left">Restriction enzyme</th><th align="left"><italic>SL</italic> size<sup>e</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>SH</italic> size<sup>e</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">TG609</td><td align="left">ATATGACTAGGAGGCAATGACTGA<break/>TTGCCTACTTATAACCCTGTGGA</td><td align="left">400</td><td char="." align="char">52</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Alu</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">400</td><td char="." align="char">280</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CT258</td><td align="left">CAATGAATCATCTGTGGTGATT<break/>TGCATTCCTCTGTGGATGCT</td><td char="." align="left">200</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Hin</italic>fI</td><td char="." align="char">80</td><td char="." align="char">150</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C2_At3g24010</td><td align="left">ATGCAATCAGGATTGCTGATG<break/>CTGATCGAGCTGCTGAATATG</td><td char="." align="left">1,000</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td align="left"><italic>Taq</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">1,000</td><td char="." align="char">600</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T0156</td><td align="left">GCGGTTGATTCACATCGTAA<break/>CCTGTAGCACCCAAAGGATG</td><td char="." align="left">1,100</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td align="left"><italic>Hpy</italic>CH4IV</td><td char="." align="char">1,100</td><td char="." align="char">550</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CT220</td><td align="left">AAGCGAATTATCTGTCAAC<break/>GTTCCTGACCATTACAAAAGTAC</td><td char="." align="left">200</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td align="left"><italic>Mse</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">100</td><td char="." align="char">130</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T1065</td><td align="left">GACGGTGAAGGGTACCAAG<break/>CAGGAGTGCATGGGTAGGT</td><td char="." align="left">550</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td align="left"><italic>Ssp</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">550</td><td char="." align="char">400</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C2_At5g06360</td><td align="left">GGCTATGCATGAAGAGTCATC<break/>GGCACCTCCCATTTTCCAGC</td><td char="." align="left">250</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td align="left"><italic>Apo</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">200</td><td char="." align="char">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CT229</td><td align="left">ATGGGCTGGGATCGTAGTAAA<break/>AAGCTTGCGATTCCCATAACAT</td><td char="." align="left">336</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Mwo</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">300</td><td char="." align="char">336</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T0208</td><td align="left">AACGCCCCAGCCTGACTACA<break/>CTGGGGAGGTTTCGATTTCTG</td><td char="." align="left">514</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Hin</italic>dIII</td><td char="." align="char">514</td><td char="." align="char">480</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TG483</td><td align="left">CACTCCCATGGCAGATAAAA<break/>AGTGAAGTAAAACAAAGCCAAAAT</td><td char="." align="left">334</td><td char="." align="char">59</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Hph</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">334</td><td char="." align="char">200</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T0703</td><td align="left">ATTTTTACGGGCAAGCGACTG<break/>CGTTGATCCCTCTATAATGGTG</td><td char="." align="left">456</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Hpy</italic>CH4IV</td><td char="." align="char">350</td><td char="." align="char">250</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T1068</td><td align="left">CAAAGCAATGGGCAATGGT<break/>ACACAGCAGTTTCAGTAGGAC</td><td char="." align="left">500</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Hin</italic>cII</td><td char="." align="char">400</td><td char="." align="char">500</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CT175</td><td align="left">CAGCTAAGCGTTGACAGTTGAGAA<break/>ATGGCCGCGGTTTGAGC</td><td char="." align="left">750</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Mse</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">200</td><td char="." align="char">280</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TG182</td><td align="left">GCTCGGGCAACAGTGAAC<break/>GCTAAGCAAATGAAAAACCAGA</td><td char="." align="left">335</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Taq</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">335</td><td char="." align="char">280</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TG370</td><td align="left">ATGCTGCTGCCGGTTCCACT<break/>ATCGGGTCTCTAATTTCAGCAC</td><td char="." align="left">352</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Hpy</italic>CH4IV</td><td char="." align="char">352</td><td char="." align="char">200</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T0958</td><td align="left">GTGTCGAACCCTTGGCAACAAT<break/>AGTTCTTTCAGCTTTTGGGTTAA</td><td char="." align="left">650</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Rsa</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">400</td><td char="." align="char">300</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T0891</td><td align="left">GACCGCTACCTCAACTTCT<break/>CACTCTAATACTCCACTCAACATA</td><td char="." align="left">1,200</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Dra</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">1,200</td><td char="." align="char">700</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TG339</td><td align="left">GAAACCTTACCCCTCTA<break/>CGCTGTTTCTTGCCATTT</td><td char="." align="left">436<break/>500<sup>d</sup></td><td char="." align="char">46</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">T0529</td><td align="left">TGGAGAGGAACAGGCTAAATC<break/>CACTCCGGCAACTGAAATGT</td><td char="." align="left">1,650<break/>1,600<sup>d</sup></td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">T0635</td><td align="left">CCAGAACCTCGACTCATCA<break/>TAGCCTCACAGTCTCAGTCAA</td><td char="." align="left">300</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left"><italic>Hin</italic>cII</td><td char="." align="char">80</td><td char="." align="char">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TG60</td><td align="left">TTGGCTGAAGTGAAGAAAAGTA<break/>AAGGGCATTGTAATATCTGTCC</td><td char="." align="left">1500</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td align="left"><italic>Hpy</italic>CH4IV</td><td char="." align="char">350</td><td char="." align="char">520</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CT138</td><td align="left">ACCAGCCCCGGAAGATTTTA<break/>GCGGTCAACTTCAGCAACTAT</td><td char="." align="left">900</td><td char="." align="char">55</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td align="left"><italic>Rsa</italic>I</td><td char="." align="char">700</td><td char="." align="char">600</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Size of undigested PCR product</p><p><sup>b</sup>PCR annealing temperature</p><p><sup>c</sup>Chromosome number</p><p><sup>d</sup>PCR product size on <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> and <italic>S. habrochaites</italic>, respectively</p><p><sup>e</sup>Band size estimation after digestion, on <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> (<italic>SL</italic>) and <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> (<italic>SH</italic>)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>AFLP markers were determined as described by Gorguet et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2006</xref>), using the same primer combinations as presented in Finkers et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2007a</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Data analysis and mapping</title><p>To normalize the distribution of the recorded trait, the parthenocarpy level (percentage of seedless fruits) was transformed to a logit scale: logit&#x000a0;(<italic>p</italic>)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;log&#x000a0;(<italic>p</italic>/(100&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;<italic>p</italic>)), (with <italic>p</italic> the percentage of seedless fruits on the first five clusters per plant).</p><p>Genetic linkage maps were constructed with JoinMap 3.0 (Van Ooijen and Voorrips <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2001</xref>), applying the Kosambi mapping function. QTL mapping was performed using the interval mapping and multiple-QTL mapping procedures of MapQTL 5 (Van Ooijen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2004</xref>). A logarithm of odds (LOD) threshold value of 3.0 was set (Van Ooijen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">1999</xref>). A two-LOD support interval was taken as a confidence interval for a putative QTL. Models for QTL analysis are presented hereafter.</p><p>In the BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub> population, the linear model used for the phenotype <italic>Y</italic> of an individual was: <disp-formula id="Equa"><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$$ Y_{{i(j)}} = \mu + X_{{i(j)}} \alpha _{j} + e_{i} \quad [{\text{model}}\;1] $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>where <italic>&#x003bc;</italic> is the population mean, <italic>X</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>(<italic>j</italic>)</sub> is the number of <italic>SH</italic> alleles at the major locus for individual <italic>i</italic>(<italic>j</italic>) and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub> is the effect of one allele of the major QTL. This effect differs according to <italic>j</italic>, the genotypic status of the minor QTL. <italic>j</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1 (<italic>i</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1, &#x02026;, 61) when the minor QTL is homozygous <italic>SL</italic>; <italic>j</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2 (<italic>i</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1, &#x02026;, 21) when the minor QTL is heterozygous and <italic>j</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3 (<italic>i</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1, &#x02026;, 24) when the minor QTL is homozygous <italic>SH</italic>. <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> is the residual.</p><p>In the F<sub>2</sub> population used for the mapping of two parthenocarpy QTLs, the model used for the phenotype <italic>Y</italic> of an individual was the factorial combination of the two loci: <disp-formula id="Equb"><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$$ Y = \mu + X_{1} X_{2} + e\quad [{\text{model}}\;2] $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>where <italic>&#x003bc;</italic> is the population mean, <italic>X</italic><sub>1</sub><italic>X</italic><sub>2</sub> is the effect of the combinations of the two parthenocarpy QTLs and <italic>e</italic> is the residual.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Parthenocarpic fruit development was observed in the introgression line IL5-1 developed by Finkers et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2007b</xref>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), but not characterized into details. In addition, flowers of IL5-1 presented an exserted stigma from pre-anthesis stage on. In such a phenotype, self-pollination is altered because the stigma is out of the anther cone when the pollen is released inside the anther cone (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). We hypothesized that the observed seedless fruits setting in IL5-1 was due to a combination of parthenocarpy and functional sterility. Functional sterility is characterized by a normal development of viable pollen, but natural pollination is strongly restricted due to some deviation from the normal morphology and function of the flower. Because ILs were initially vibrated to promote pollination, parthenocarpic fruit development was only obvious with the presence of a certain form of sterility. IL5-2, carrying only the long arm of chromosome 5 of <italic>SH</italic>, was not parthenocarpic but showed stigma exsertion. We concluded that the stigma exsertion locus was located on chromosome 5.</p><p>To map and characterize the parthenocarpy and functional sterility traits observed in this material, we generated a genetic linkage map of the introgressed regions of the two ILs by making use of two BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>1</sub> populations: population 5-1 and population 5-2 segregating for the <italic>SH</italic> introgressions of IL5-1 and IL5-2, respectively. The recurrent parent used for the development of IL5-1 and IL5-1, cv. Moneymaker (<italic>SL</italic>), does not produce any parthenocarpic fruit, under the criteria presented in the &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>&#x0201d;. Therefore the parthenocarpy loci of IL5-1 are located in the <italic>SH</italic> introgressions.</p><p>Because the expression of parthenocarpy requires that the plants are not pollinated, we selected them for functional sterility. For this, both populations were screened at juvenile stage with SCAR marker TG318, to select for plants that are homozygous or heterozygous <italic>SH</italic> at that locus. The final population 5-1 and population 5-2 consisted of 74 and 66 plants, respectively. Hereafter, &#x0201c;populations 5-1 and 5-2&#x0201d; refer to these selected plants. TG318 was chosen to screen the populations because it is located in the middle of the chromosome 5, near the centromere, and it carries the alleles of <italic>SH</italic> in both IL5-1 and IL5-2. Therefore TG318 was likely to be near the stigma exsertion locus. By skipping the plants homozygous <italic>SL</italic> at TG318 locus in the segregating populations, we enriched them for plants with functional sterility, to promote visible parthenocarpic fruit development. Subsequently, parthenocarpy was evaluated in population 5-1 and functional sterility in populations 5-1 and 5-2.</p><sec id="Sec10"><title>Genetic linkage map construction</title><p>The initial step in the development of linkage maps in the regions of the <italic>SH</italic> introgressions was to identify markers on the borders of the introgression. We developed a set of RFLP- and COS-derived PCR primer combinations in the expected regions of the introgressions and determined whether the loci were in or out. The border of the introgression on chromosome 4 in IL5-1 was determined between markers T0635 and TG609, respectively, at 55 and 56&#x000a0;cM on the EXPEN2000 linkage map (Fulton et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2002</xref>). On chromosome 5, the border of the introgression in IL5-2 was identified between markers CD64 and CD31, respectively, at 27 and 39&#x000a0;cM on the EXPEN1992 linkage map (Tanksley et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1992</xref>). <italic>SH</italic> introgression of IL5-1 is likely to cover the entire chromosome 5 (Finkers et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2007b</xref>).</p><p>The genetic linkage map of the <italic>SH</italic> chromosome 4 introgression of IL5-1 was generated using the population 5-1 (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;74). Thirteen RFLP or COS markers located on the short arm of chromosome 4 in the EXPEN2000 map were converted into CAPS or SCAR markers and mapped in population 5-1. Two microsatellite markers, SSR43 and SSR72 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sgn.cornell.edu">http://sgn.cornell.edu</ext-link>; Mueller et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2005</xref>), were added. The introgression on chromosome 4 spanned 22.4&#x000a0;cM, which is almost the complete short arm of chromosome 4, from the telomere to CAPS marker T0635 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a).</p><p>The genetic linkage map of the <italic>SH</italic> chromosome 5 was constructed using populations 5-1 and 5-2 separately. A total of nine CAPS or SCAR markers were developed either based on available information (Brouwer and St. Clair <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2004</xref>; Coaker and Francis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2004</xref>) or based on RFLP sequences (Tanksley et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1992</xref>). The <italic>SH</italic> introgression of IL5-2 spanned 21.1&#x000a0;cM on the long arm of chromosome 5, from the telomeric end to CAPS marker CD31. The limit of the <italic>SH</italic> introgression of IL5-1 on the short arm of chromosome 5 (distal to TG441), was not determined, therefore the introgression spanned at least 77.2&#x000a0;cM (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). Because populations 5-1 and 5-2 were selected for homozygous and heterozygous <italic>SH</italic> alleles at TG318 locus, the recombination ratio was underestimated around the TG318 locus, which reduced the distances in the chromosome 5 introgressions of IL5-1 and IL5-2. However, this did not affect the order of the markers and therefore did not affect the relative positions of the subsequent mapped loci.</p><p>The order of the markers on chromosomes 4 and 5 were in accordance with the Tomato-EXPEN2000 map and EXPEN1992 map of the &#x0201c;SOL Genomics Network&#x0201d; (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sgn.cornell.edu">http://sgn.cornell.edu</ext-link>). Overall the map distance in the chromosome 4 introgression was reduced to 41% of the distance found in the same interval in the EXPEN2000 reference map. Regarding the chromosome 5, the map distance was quasi equal (92%) between IL5-1 and the EXPEN1992 reference map (Tanksley et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1992</xref>). In contrast, the map distance in the chromosome 5 introgression of IL5-2 was reduced to 38% of the distance observed in the EXPEN1992 reference map.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Screening and mapping of parthenocarpy</title><p>The distribution of the parthenocarpy level in population 5-1 ranged from 0 to 90.5% (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) and the average size of the parthenocarpic fruits (4.73&#x000a0;cm) did not significantly differ (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;0.05) from the size of the seeded fruits (4.75&#x000a0;cm).
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Frequency distribution of the parthenocarpy levels (percentages) over the first five clusters in the BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>1</sub> population 5-1 (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;74). i.e. &#x0201c;<italic>0</italic>&#x0201d; refers to plants without seedless fruit; &#x0201c;<italic>0&#x02013;10</italic>&#x0201d; refers to plants with at least one seedless fruit and less than 10% of the flowers setting seedless fruits</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2007_708_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p>By applying interval mapping, one QTL for parthenocarpy (designated <italic>pat4.1</italic>) was identified on chromosome 4 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a), close to the centromere, with the highest LOD value at CAPS markers T0958/T0891/T0635 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). This QTL explained 48.9% of the total variation. By using one of the three peak markers as cofactor, in an Multiple-QTL Mapping (MQM) procedure, no extra QTL was detected in the introgressions.
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Genetic linkage groups of<italic> SH</italic> introgressions of IL5-1 and IL5-2 developed on population 5-1 and population 5-2. The position of the parthenocarpy QTLs (<italic>pat4.1</italic> and<italic> pat5.1</italic>) and the stigma exsertion locus (<italic>se5.1</italic>) is indicated on the<italic> left</italic> of the linkage groups. The<italic> se5-1</italic> locus was mapped on population 5-1 and population 5-2. The<italic> QTL bars</italic> indicate an interval in which the<italic> inner</italic>,<italic> thicker bar</italic>, shows a one LOD support confidence interval and the<italic> outer bars</italic>,<italic> thinner</italic>, shows a two LOD support confidence interval.<bold> b</bold> SGN reference map for the short arm and centromeric region of chromosome 4, the complete chromosome 5 and the telomeric region of the long arm of chromosome 9 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sgn.cornell.edu">http://sgn.cornell.edu</ext-link>). The putative positions of the identified QTLs are represented in it. Because the one LOD confidence interval of<italic> pat4.1</italic> and<italic> pat4.2</italic> are overlapping, this overlap is indicated with<italic> dashed lines</italic>.<bold> c</bold> Genetic linkage groups of chromosome 4 and chromosome 9<italic> SH</italic> introgressions of IVT-line 1 developed on the F<sub>2</sub> population. The position of the parthenocarpy QTLs (<italic>pat4.2</italic> and <italic>pat9.1</italic>) is indicated on the<italic> right</italic> of the linkage groups. Map positions are given in cM. Maps and QTL alignments were performed with MapChart</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2007_708_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Phenotypic analysis of<italic> pat4.1</italic> and the<italic> stigma exsertion</italic> locus, detected by interval mapping in population 5-1 for <italic>pat4.1</italic> and populations 5-1 and 5-2 for the<italic> stigma exsertion</italic> locus</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Trait</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Genotype</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">LOD<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Explained variation (%)</th></tr><tr><th align="left"><italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SL</italic> (<italic>n</italic><sup>c</sup>)</th><th align="left"><italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SH</italic> (<italic>n</italic>)</th><th align="left"><italic>SH</italic>/<italic>SH</italic> (<italic>n</italic>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Logit</italic> (parthenocarpy level)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;1.73 (16)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.40 (45)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.18 (13)</td><td char="." align="char">10.8</td><td char="." align="char">48.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Parthenocarpy level (%)<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.8</td><td char="." align="char">28.3</td><td char="." align="char">39.8</td><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Stigma exsertion (mm)<sup>d</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;0.53 (3)</td><td char="." align="char">0.45 (73)</td><td char="." align="char">2.04 (64)</td><td char="." align="char">19.23</td><td char="." align="char">47.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SL</italic>, <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>; <italic>SH</italic>, <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic></p><p><sup>a</sup>The logit numbers are transformed back into parthenocarpy level (percentages)</p><p><sup>b</sup>The highest LOD score was displayed on markers T0958, T0891 and T0635</p><p><sup>c</sup><italic>n</italic> number of individuals per genotype category</p><p><sup>d</sup>Mapping data calculated by combining populations 5-1 and 5-2</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Confirmation of parthenocarpy QTLs in BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub></title><p>In order to confirm and narrow down the confidence interval of <italic>pat4.1</italic> on chromosome 4 and to study the potential interaction of <italic>pat4.1</italic> with genes on chromosome 5, we developed a set of recombinant progenies with small homozygous <italic>SH</italic> introgressions on the short arm of chromosome 4. To develop this set of progenies, BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub> plants, recombinant for the chromosome 4 introgression, were screened at seedling stage using molecular markers. Homozygous recombinant plants were selected and divided into nine classes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Dominant parthenocarpy QTLs on chromosome 5 could not have been identified in the previous population (BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>1</sub>) because most plants were homozygous <italic>SH</italic> or heterozygous for chromosome 5 due to the enrichment for plants with functional sterility. The evaluation of the recombinant progenies segregating for chromosome 5 allowed us to look for potential dominant parthenocarpy QTLs on chromosome 5. Selected plants were genotyped and their parthenocarpy level was assessed from April to July 2006 (hereafter referred to as Spring/Summer). After making cuttings, the recombinant progenies were grown and re-evaluated in Winter 2006/2007 (hereafter referred to as Winter). The parthenocarpy level of each recombinant progeny is presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. Only chromosome 4 recombinant progenies carrying the <italic>SH</italic> chromosome segment TG182&#x02013;T0635 produced parthenocarpic fruits. This narrows down the position of the parthenocarpy QTL <italic>pat4.1</italic> confidence interval to 3.7&#x000a0;cM in population 5-1. The parthenocarpy level was significantly higher in Spring/Summer than in Winter (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). More strikingly however, was the great variation of parthenocarpy level, from one progeny to another. This did not depend on the size of the <italic>SH</italic> fragment on chromosome 4, eliminating the possibility of having a second parthenocarpy QTL on that chromosome. Therefore we investigated the potential interaction of <italic>pat4.1</italic> with chromosome 5 in progenies 1&#x02013;5. To study this interaction we applied the Multiple-QTL mapping (MQM) function and used marker T0635 (one of the peak markers for <italic>pat4.1</italic>) as co-factor. A QTL linked to marker CD64 on chromosome 5 showed a significant effect on the expression of the parthenocarpy trait (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). This QTL is hereafter referred to as <italic>pat5.1</italic> and was detected in Spring/Summer and Winter.
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p><italic>Left</italic> graphical genotypes of BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub> progenies for the short arm of chromosome 4. &#x0201c;<italic>Black</italic>&#x0201d; stands for homozygous <italic>SH</italic>, &#x0201c;<italic>white</italic>&#x0201d; for homozygous <italic>SL</italic> and &#x0201c;<italic>grey</italic>&#x0201d; for unknown because the exact position of the recombination between the two closest flanking markers is unknown. <italic>Numbers</italic> under the bars indicate the position of the above-mentioned markers, in cM. The reference number of each progeny is indicated at the <italic>far left</italic> of the graphical genotypes and the number of plants per progeny at the <italic>far right</italic>. <italic>Right</italic> average parthenocarpy level (percentages) over the first five clusters per specific progeny, in Spring/Summer (<italic>white</italic>) and Winter (<italic>black</italic>), indicated with SE bars</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2007_708_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p><p>In order to study the effects and interaction of <italic>pat4.1</italic> and <italic>pat5.1</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), we searched for the best linear model to explain the observed variation. <italic>pat4.1</italic> is clearly the main QTL in this interaction, but the size of its effect depends on the alleles of <italic>pat5.1</italic>. A higher level of parthenocarpy is observed when the two <italic>SH</italic> alleles of <italic>pat4.1</italic> are present in combination with at least one <italic>SH</italic> allele of <italic>pat5.1</italic>. In Spring/Summer, the parthenocarpy level observed on these plants is on average 41% with one <italic>SH</italic> allele of <italic>pat5.1</italic> and 46% with two <italic>SH</italic> alleles (no significant difference). It is not clear whether <italic>pat4.1</italic> in heterozygous, in combination with <italic>pat5.1</italic> homozygous <italic>SH</italic> gives also a high level of parthenocarpy, because only one plant had this specific genotype. When <italic>pat4.1</italic> is homozygous <italic>SL</italic>, the <italic>pat5.1</italic> QTL alone never shows parthenocarpy. Regarding these two observations <italic>pat4.1</italic> can be considered as the major QTL because it accounts for most of the effect on the parthenocarpy level, and <italic>pat5.1</italic> can be considered as a minor QTL that affects the parthenocarpy level of the <italic>pat4.1</italic> alleles. Model 1 was chosen among the simple linear models, because in this model the variable is explained by one major QTL, which effect is depending on one minor QTL. The coefficient of correlations for Spring/Summer and Winter were 64.8 and 57.9%, respectively, which confirms that model 1 was appropriate to this case. The details of this model are given in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Observed parthenocarpy level (percentages) for each combination of <italic>pat4.1</italic> and <italic>pat5.1</italic> alleles, in the BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>2</sub>, in Spring/Summer and Winter</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3"><italic>pat4.1</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="5"><italic>pat5.1</italic> (<italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SL</italic>)</th><th align="left" colspan="5"><italic>pat5.1</italic> (<italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SH</italic>)</th><th align="left" colspan="5"><italic>pat5.1</italic> (<italic>SH</italic>/<italic>SH</italic>)</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="2">Spring/Summer</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Winter</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="2">Spring/Summer</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Winter</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="2">Spring/Summer</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Winter</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>n</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left">Mean</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">Mean</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">Mean</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">Mean</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">Mean</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">Mean</th><th align="left">SE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SL</italic></td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td align="left">(13)</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td align="left">(6)</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td align="left">(14)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SH</italic></td><td char="." align="char">4.1</td><td char="." align="char">2.3</td><td char="." align="char">2.4</td><td char="." align="char">1.2</td><td align="left">(7)</td><td char="." align="char">4.8</td><td char="." align="char">4.8</td><td char="." align="char">16.1</td><td char="." align="char">13</td><td align="left">(2)</td><td char="." align="char">45.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td char="." align="char">37.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.0</td><td align="left">(1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>SH</italic>/<italic>SH</italic></td><td char="." align="char">11.6</td><td char="." align="char">1.9</td><td char="." align="char">4.6</td><td char="." align="char">0.9</td><td align="left">(41)</td><td char="." align="char">41.0</td><td char="." align="char">6.4</td><td char="." align="char">14.8</td><td char="." align="char">3.0</td><td align="left">(13)</td><td char="." align="char">46.0</td><td char="." align="char">6.7</td><td char="." align="char">27.2</td><td char="." align="char">6.6</td><td align="left">(9)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SE</italic> standard error; <italic>n</italic> number of individuals per genotype; <italic>SL</italic>, <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>; <italic>SH</italic>, <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Significance of model 1 and estimates of the parameters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Spring/Summer</th><th align="left">Winter</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Probability of F</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td char="." align="char">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Coefficient correlation (%)</td><td char="." align="char">64.8</td><td char="." align="char">57.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Constant (<italic>&#x003bc;</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;6.801</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02212;6.658</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3">Effect of <italic>SH</italic> allele of <italic>pat4.1</italic> (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic><sub><italic>j</italic></sub>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;When <italic>pat5.1</italic> is <italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SL</italic> (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic><sub>1</sub>)</td><td char="." align="char">1.782</td><td char="." align="char">1.235</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;When <italic>pat5.1</italic> is <italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SH</italic> (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic><sub>2</sub>)</td><td char="." align="char">3.101</td><td char="." align="char">2.439</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;When <italic>pat5.1</italic> is <italic>SH</italic>/<italic>SH</italic> (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic><sub>3</sub>)</td><td char="." align="char">3.408</td><td char="." align="char">2.787</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Characterization and mapping of functional sterility</title><p>Functional sterility, procured by stigma exsertion (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), was evaluated in populations 5-1 and 5-2 at pre-anthesis on the third cluster. <italic>SH</italic> flowers have exserted stigmas, whereas the stigma of cv. Moneymaker (<italic>SL</italic>) flowers is inside the anther cone at pre-anthesis. Interval mapping showed one QTL for stigma exsertion, on chromosome 5 introgressions of IL5-1 and IL5-2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a) linked to marker TG318. We named this locus <italic>se5.1</italic> due to its position on chromosome 5. Plants homozygous for the <italic>SH</italic> introgression at marker TG318 produced flowers with stigmas significantly more exserted than heterozygous or homozygous <italic>SL</italic> plants at that marker (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p>In order to study whether the stigma exsertion, observed in IL5-1 and IL5-2, could fully prevent self-pollination, we characterized qualitatively the population 5-2 for the presence or absence of seeded fruits: plants without seeded fruits over the five characterized clusters were differentiated from plants producing at least one fruit with seeds. Population 5-1 was not used for this purpose, because this population was also segregating for parthenocarpy which influences the setting of fruits with seeds. The characterized trait, &#x0201c;presence or absence of seeded fruits&#x0201d;, co-segregated with CAPS marker TG318 on chromosome 5 and thus with the QTL for stigma exsertion. This demonstrated that stigma exsertion could fully prevent self-pollination, thus seeded fruits setting.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>IVT-line 1</title><p>In a first step towards the mapping of the parthenocarpy trait present in IVT-line 1, we wanted to identify the positions of the <italic>SH</italic> introgressions. We screened a large number of known <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> AFLP markers on IVT-line 1. Seven <italic>SH</italic> introgressions could clearly be identified, on chromosomes 4, 5, 6, 9 and 11. Only introgressions where known <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> AFLP markers were present can potentially be retrieved, therefore we cannot exclude the possible presence of other, small <italic>SH</italic> introgressions.</p><p>An F<sub>2</sub> population composed of 160 plants, coming from the cross between IVT-line 1 and <italic>SL</italic> cv. Moneymaker, was grown, and the parthenocarpy level of the plants was evaluated in Spring 2006 in Wageningen, The Netherlands, following the same procedure as previously described. The parthenocarpy level in the F<sub>2</sub> population ranged from 0 to 97%. About 44% of the plants did not produce any parthenocarpic fruit (data not shown). Fruits with and without seeds, within a same cluster were significantly different in size (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05), with averages of 4.36 and 4.11&#x000a0;cm, respectively.</p><p>Because of the presence of an <italic>SH</italic> introgression around the centromere of chromosome 4, where <italic>pat4.1</italic> was previously mapped, we hypothesized that parthenocarpy in IVT-line 1 might also be under the control of <italic>pat4.1</italic> or an allelic variant of it. After confirming that marker T0635 was in the <italic>SH</italic> introgression of IVT-line 1, we tested the association between marker T0635 (peak marker for <italic>pat4.1</italic>) and the segregation of parthenocarpy observed in the F<sub>2</sub> population. This association was highly significant. However, not all plants homozygous <italic>SH</italic> for T0635 produced parthenocarpic fruits, which may be due to the mode of action of another locus. To localize this other locus, we screened AFLP primer combinations on the set of F<sub>2</sub> plants homozygous <italic>SH</italic> at the T0635 locus. One AFLP marker, P18M51-219 was clearly associated with the parthenocarpy level of the selected plants and was known to be located in a chromosome 9 introgression. Parthenocarpy in IVT-line 1 is therefore under the control of at least two QTLs, one located near the centromere of chromosome 4 and one near the telomere of the long arm of chromosome 9.</p><p>To map these two parthenocarpy loci more accurately, we developed a linkage map for the introgressions on chromosomes 4 and 9 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c). The borders of the introgression on chromosome 4 were between markers T0635 and T0958 and between CT258 and TG287. On chromosome 9, the border of the introgression was located between markers T1519 and C2_At3g24010 and likely spanned the rest of the telomeric region of the long arm of chromosome 9. The two linkage groups were generated using eight CAPS markers, converted from RFLP or COS sequences and three SSR markers (SOL Genomics Network database). The order of the markers on chromosome 4 was identical as in the SGN reference map. In the introgression of chromosome 9, few inversions of marker orders were observed. The introgression of chromosome 4 spanned 1.7&#x000a0;cM (7&#x000a0;cM on the SGN reference map) and the introgression on chromosome 9 was 3.8&#x000a0;cM (17&#x000a0;cM in the reference map). This means that the map distances observed in the introgressions of IVT-line 1 were reduced to 25% of the distances of the same intervals, presented on the SGN reference map.</p><p>Parthenocarpy was mapped using MapQTL. We used a <italic>logit</italic> scale of the parthenocarpy level to improve the normality of the distribution. Because of the small genetic sizes of the two introgressions on chromosomes 4 and 9, both complete introgressions were highly significant and it was not possible to narrow down the position of the two parthenocarpy QTLs. These two parthenocarpy QTLs are hereafter denoted as <italic>pat4.2</italic> (on chromosome 4) and <italic>pat9.1</italic> (on chromosome 9). Because it was not possible to narrow down the confidence intervals of <italic>pat4.2</italic> and <italic>pat9.1</italic>, we excluded the plants recombinant for one or both introgressions in the following analysis, and plants with an ambiguous scoring, in order to improve the accuracy of the calculations. In total, out of 160 F<sub>2</sub> plants, 137 plants were selected. An ANOVA showed that both QTLs had a highly significant effect on parthenocarpy and also the interaction between both QTLs was highly significant. Therefore among simple linear models we selected one in which the observed variation is explained by the interaction between two QTLs (model 2). The coefficient of correlation (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) was 73.7%, which confirms that the model chosen fitted well the observed variation. The observed and predicted effect, based on model 2, of the different allele&#x02019;s combinations between <italic>pat4.2</italic> and <italic>pat9.1</italic> is presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>. The absence of <italic>SH</italic> allele in either of the <italic>pat4.2</italic> or <italic>pat9.1</italic> loci results in the absence of parthenocarpic fruit. The highest level of parthenocarpy is obtained when both QTLs are homozygous <italic>SH</italic> (76% of parthenocarpy level).
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Observed and predicted parthenocarpy levels (percentage) for each combination of <italic>pat4.2</italic> and <italic>pat9.1</italic> alleles, in the F<sub>2</sub> population (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;137)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>pat4.2</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="3"><italic>pat9.1</italic> (<italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SL</italic>)</th><th align="left" colspan="3"><italic>pat9.1</italic> (<italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SH</italic>)</th><th align="left" colspan="3"><italic>pat9.1</italic> (<italic>SH</italic>/<italic>SH</italic>)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Pred.<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left">Obs.<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left">SE (<italic>n</italic>)</th><th align="left">Pred.</th><th align="left">Obs.</th><th align="left">SE (<italic>n</italic>)</th><th align="left">Pred.</th><th align="left">Obs.</th><th align="left">SE (<italic>n</italic>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SL</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>0.0</italic></bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.3</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.2 (14)</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>0.0</italic></bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.8</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.4 (24)</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>0.0</italic></bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.4</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.4 (4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>SL</italic>/<italic>SH</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>0.0</italic></bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.2</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.2 (14)</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>0.1</italic></bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>12.3</bold></td><td char="." align="char">2.7 (40)</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>87.5</italic></bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>65.2</bold></td><td char="." align="char">6.0 (12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>SH</italic>/<italic>SH</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>0.0</italic></bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>0.0</bold></td><td char="." align="char">0.0 (8)</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>7.1</italic></bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>29.2</bold></td><td char="." align="char">4.4 (17)</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>97.1</italic></bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold>76.6</bold></td><td char="." align="char">12.8 (4)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>SL</italic>, <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>; <italic>SH</italic>, <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic></p><p><sup>a</sup>Predicted effect from model 2 (presented in &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>&#x0201d;), initially calculated in logit scale, transformed back into percentages</p><p><sup>b</sup>Observed mean for each combination of alleles (percentages)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Candidate gene analysis</title><p>One main parthenocarpy gene, known as <italic>fwf</italic> or <italic>ARF8</italic>, was recently isolated in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (Goetz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>). The use of COS markers in the present mapping work and the increasing availability of BAC sequence information linked to tomato markers, allowed us to study the potential microsynteny between the <italic>ARF8</italic><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> region and the tomato parthenocarpy QTLs identified in this study. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> orthologs of markers T0953 and C2_AT5G37360, both located in the <italic>pat4.1</italic>-<italic>pat4.2</italic> region, were found to be closely linked to <italic>ARF8</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>). In addition we found one extra <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> ortholog in the sequence of BAC clone HBa311A10, linked to marker C2_AT3G54770 in the <italic>pat</italic>4.1-<italic>pat4.2</italic> region, also located near <italic>ARF8</italic>. Eventually we could draw a microsynteny map that highlights the hypothesis that <italic>ARF8</italic> may well be a homolog to <italic>pat4.1</italic>-<italic>pat4.2</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> orthologs of tomato markers in the <italic>pat4.1</italic>-<italic>pat4.2</italic> region compared to <italic>ARF8</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2">Tomato</th><th align="left" colspan="4"><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Marker Chr.4</th><th align="left">Position (cM)</th><th align="left">Accession no.<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left">Gene name</th><th align="left">Chr.</th><th align="left">AGI coordinates (bases)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">T0953</td><td char="." align="char">49.0</td><td align="left">AT5G37370</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">14829915&#x02013;14833750</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HBa311A10<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">55.3</td><td align="left">AT5G36905</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">14575028&#x02013;14577414</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C2_AT5G37360</td><td char="." align="char">56.0</td><td align="left">AT5G37360</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">14822459&#x02013;14825466</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">AT5G37020</td><td align="left"><italic>ARF8</italic></td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">14647258&#x02013;14651617</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>BAC clone HBa311A10 is linked to marker C2_AT3G54770 which has been mapped at 55.3&#x000a0;cM on Chr. 4 on the EXPEN2000 reference map</p><p><sup>b</sup><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> orthologs were found in the SOL genomics network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sgn.cornell.edu">http://www.sgn.cornell.edu</ext-link>)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Microsynteny between the <italic>pat4.1</italic>-<italic>pat4.2</italic> tomato region and <italic>ARF8 Arabidopsis</italic> region. A zoom in the two regions of interest, with the microsyntenic relations, is highlighted in <italic>grey</italic></p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="122_2007_708_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>We studied parthenocarpy in an IL, named IL5-1, of <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> in a <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> genetic background. At least two QTLs were responsible for parthenocarpy in this line: one major QTL, referred to as <italic>pat4.1</italic>, located close to the centromere of chromosome 4, and one minor QTL, referred to as <italic>pat5.1</italic>, on the short arm of chromosome 5. The <italic>pat4.1</italic> gene was initially mapped in a BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>1</sub> population, enriched for plants with functional sterility. The <italic>pat5.1</italic> locus was later on mapped in another set of specific progenies. The model used to explain the phenotypic variation in the selected progenies improves the understanding of the genetic control of parthenocarpy in this IL. In this model the variation is explained by a major QTL, <italic>pat4.1</italic> and a minor QTL, <italic>pat5.1</italic>. The effect of <italic>pat4.1</italic> depends on the number of <italic>SH</italic> alleles at the <italic>pat5.1</italic> locus. When at least one <italic>SH</italic> allele is present at the <italic>pat5.1</italic> locus, the effect of <italic>pat4.1</italic> is higher. There is hardly difference in the effect of <italic>pat4.1</italic> between plants carrying one or two <italic>SH</italic> alleles at the <italic>pat5.1</italic> locus, which means that <italic>pat5.1</italic> is a dominant QTL (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). This explains why <italic>pat5.1</italic> was not detected in the BC<sub>5</sub>S<sub>1</sub> population, because the enrichment for functional sterility also resulted in an enrichment of <italic>SH</italic> alleles at the <italic>pat5.1</italic> locus.</p><p>We mapped the stigma exsertion locus close to marker TG318, on chromosome 5. When the presence of seeded fruits was considered as a qualitative trait, it co-segregated with marker TG318. This supports the hypothesis that the exserted stigma prevents self-pollination and therefore prevents seeded fruits setting. Bernacchi and Tanksley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1997</xref>) characterized stigma exsertion in an IL of <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> acc. LA1777 in a <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> genetic background. They mapped the main stigma exsertion locus on chromosome 2 and did not report a functional sterility locus on chromosome 5. However, the ILs of Monforte and Tanksley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2000</xref>) do not cover the complete genome and amongst others the central part of chromosome 5 is missing. It is therefore impossible at this stage to speculate whether the stigma exsertion locus identified in our study is specific to accession LYC4, or inherent to the <italic>S. habrochaites</italic> species.</p><p>The position of <italic>pat4.1</italic> led to the identification of <italic>pat4.2</italic>, one of the two parthenocarpy QTLs identified in IVT-line 1. Eventually, we identified two QTLs, one close to the centromere of chromosome 4, referred to as <italic>pat4.2</italic>, and one close to the telomere of the long arm of chromosome 9, referred to as <italic>pat9.1</italic>. Both QTLs are of equal importance in the parthenocarpic expression. It is not clear at this stage whether <italic>pat4.1</italic> and <italic>pat4.2</italic> refer to the same gene. Some minor differences can be observed between both genetic controls of parthenocarpy, but the allelic possibility between <italic>pat4.1</italic> and <italic>pat4.2</italic> cannot be discarded: The presence of <italic>pat4.1</italic> alone is enough to obtain a certain level of parthenocarpy, but <italic>pat4.2</italic> alone does not give any parthenocarpic fruit development. In addition we observed that the size of seedless fruits produced in <italic>pat4.1</italic>/<italic>pat5.1</italic> plants was similar to the size of the fruits with seeds on the same material, but a significant smaller size was observed in the <italic>pat4.2</italic>/<italic>pat9.1</italic> material. To give a definitive answer to the question whether <italic>pat4.1</italic> and <italic>pat4.2</italic> are allelic, we need to fine-map both QTLs. However, fine mapping will be hampered by the strong suppression of recombination, especially in the small introgressed fragment of IVT-line 1, giving rise to the reductions of map distances observed in this study, and by the centromeric position of these parthenocarpy QTLs. Reduction in recombination has been observed previously in introgressed intervals from wild tomato species (Chetelat and Meglic <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2000</xref>; Monforte and Tanksley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2000</xref>; Rick <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1969</xref>). Sequence divergence between wild and cultivated <italic>Solanum</italic> species has been suggested as cause for this phenomenon (Paterson et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1990</xref>).</p><p>The increasing availability of sequence information provided by the sequencing of BAC clones anchored to molecular markers, and the recent development and mapping of COS markers helped us to study the syntenic relationship between tomato and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> at parthenocarpy QTLs regions. We focused on the potential synteny of the parthenocarpy QTLs regions with the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> parthenocarpy locus, <italic>ARF8</italic>, region. Two COS markers and one putative gene of the <italic>pat4.1</italic>-<italic>pat4.2</italic> region were orthologous to <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> genes closely linked to <italic>ARF8</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). This finding provides evidence that <italic>pat4.1</italic>-<italic>pat4.2</italic> may be homologs of <italic>ARF8</italic>. However, T0953 and C2_AT5G37360 (both extreme borders of the syntenic map presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) are distant of 7 cM in the EXPEN2000 reference map, which is, to our knowledge, much larger than in any reported synteny between tomato and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. <italic>ARF8</italic> has been found to act as an inhibitor for further carpel development, in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, in the absence of fertilization (Goetz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>). A lesion in <italic>ARF8</italic>, found in the <italic>fruit without fertilization</italic> mutant (<italic>fwf</italic>) has resulted in the uncoupling of fruit development from pollination and fertilization and therefore has given rise to seedless fruit. Further fine mapping and isolation of the parthenocarpy QTLs, identified in this study, are necessary to confirm the potential homology with <italic>ARF8</italic>. Recently the tomato <italic>ARF8</italic> gene has been isolated (Goetz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>). Expression of an aberrant form of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>ARF8</italic>, in tomato conferred parthenocarpy, which proves that ARF8 is also involved in the control of fruit set in tomato. Sequencing of the <italic>ARF8</italic> gene on IL5-1 and IVT-line 1 may already give information on the functionality of this candidate gene in both parthenocarpic lines. In addition, the mapping of the tomato <italic>ARF8</italic> homolog would also be sufficient to discard the possibility of homology between the <italic>pat4.1</italic>&#x02013;<italic>pat4.2</italic> and <italic>ARF8</italic>, in case the tomato <italic>ARF8</italic> homolog would not co-segregate with the parthenocarpy QTLs.</p><p>In the present experiment, the parthenocarpy level was higher with <italic>pat4.2</italic>/<italic>pat9.1</italic> than with <italic>pat4.1/pat5.1</italic>. With <italic>pat4.2</italic>/<italic>pat9.1</italic>, we observed an average of 76.6% parthenocarpic fruit set in Spring compared to 46% for <italic>pat4.1/pat5.1</italic>, in Summer. In both cases, the higher the number of parthenocarpy alleles is, the higher the level of parthenocarpy. We can only speculate about the level of parthenocarpy in one single line with all four parthenocarpy QTLs. However, the development of such a line is now possible by molecular assisted selection, using the above-mentioned markers. A too strong parthenocarpic expression often results in a fruit set that precedes anthesis as observed in the <italic>pat</italic> mutant <italic>Soressi</italic> (Mazzucato et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>). Therefore in such material the production of seeds, when needed, is hampered even when pollination is promoted. This limits the interest for breeders who ultimately want to commercialize seeds. It would be valuable to study the level of parthenocarpy in a hybrid that combines several parthenocarpy QTLs, most or all of them in heterozygous state. If such a hybrid displays a high parthenocarpy level, it would be possible to commercialize it by developing two parental lines that carry different parthenocarpy QTLs, or one parental line, used as male parent, that combines most of the parthenocarpy QTLs in homozygous and the other parental line, used as female parent, carrying only few parthenocarpy QTLs, thus with a high level of seed production. Of course a reasonable level of seed production in the male parent is also needed. A detailed study of the parthenocarpy level of these new sources of parthenocarpy in different environments, different genetic background, as well as combining the four parthenocarpy QTLs or making new combinations will allow comparisons with the reference parthenocarpy lines such as <italic>Soressi</italic> (<italic>pat</italic>), <italic>Severianin</italic> (<italic>pat-2</italic>) and <italic>RP75/59</italic> (<italic>pat-3</italic>/<italic>pat-4</italic>). This will show the potential of these newly identified QTLs for practical breeding.</p><p>So far, only one parthenocarpy gene, <italic>pat</italic>, was mapped in tomato (Beraldi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2004</xref>). In this study we mapped four parthenocarpy QTLs in tomato, which provides valuable information for the development of parthenocarpic tomato varieties. The isolation of the main QTLs will greatly enhance our understanding of the control of fruit set in tomato and offer possibilities, considering the high level of similarities within the Solanaceae, to develop seedless fruits in other economically important species.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This project was sponsored by Western Seed BV, The Netherlands.</p><p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beraldi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Picarella</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Soressi</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzucato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine mapping of the <italic>parthenocarpic fruit</italic> (<italic>pat</italic>) mutation in tomato</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-003-1442-6</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Beraldi D, Picarella ME, Soressi GP, Mazzucato A (2004) Fine mapping of the parthenocarpic fruit (pat) mutation in tomato. Theor Appl Genet 108:209&#x02013;216 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14564391</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernacchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An interspecific backcross of <italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>L. hirsutum</italic>: linkage analysis and a QTL study of sexual compatibility factors and floral traits</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1997</year><volume>147</volume><fpage>:861</fpage><lpage>877</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bernacchi D, Tanksley SD (1997) An interspecific backcross of Lycopersicon esculentum&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;L. hirsutum: linkage analysis and a QTL study of sexual compatibility factors and floral traits. Genetics 147:861&#x02013;877 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9335620</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brouwer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>St. Clair</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine mapping of three quantitative trait loci for late blight resistance in tomato using near isogenic lines (NILs) and sub-NILs</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>628</fpage><lpage>638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-003-1469-8</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Brouwer DJ, St. Clair DA (2004) Fine mapping of three quantitative trait loci for late blight resistance in tomato using near isogenic lines (NILs) and sub-NILs. Theor Appl Genet 108:628&#x02013;638 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14586504</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-resolution mapping and functional analysis of <italic>se2.1</italic>: a major stigma exsertion quantitative trait locus associated with the evolution from allogamy to autogamy in the genus <italic>Lycopersicon</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2004</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>1563</fpage><lpage>1573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.103.022558</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Chen K-Y, Tanksley SD (2004) High-resolution mapping and functional analysis of se2.1: a major stigma exsertion quantitative trait locus associated with the evolution from allogamy to autogamy in the genus Lycopersicon. Genetics 168:1563&#x02013;1573 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15579707</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chetelat</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Meglic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mapping of chromosome segments introgressed from <italic>Solanum lycopersicoides</italic> into cultivated tomato (<italic>L. esculentum</italic>)</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220050031</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Chetelat RT, Meglic V (2000) Molecular mapping of chromosome segments introgressed from Solanum lycopersicoides into cultivated tomato (L. esculentum). Theor Appl Genet 100:232&#x02013;241 </citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coaker</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping, genetic effects, and epistatic interaction of two bacterial canker resistance QTLs from <italic>Lycopersicon hirsutum</italic></article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2004</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>1047</fpage><lpage>1055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-003-1531-6</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Coaker GL, Francis DM (2004) Mapping, genetic effects, and epistatic interaction of two bacterial canker resistance QTLs from Lycopersicon hirsutum. Theor Appl Genet 108:1047&#x02013;1055 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15067391</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finkers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Berloo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>ten Have</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heusden</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three QTLs for <italic>Botrytis cinera</italic> resistance in tomato</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>593</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-006-0458-0</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Finkers R, van den Berg P, van Berloo R, ten Have A, van Heusden AW, van Kan JA, Lindhout P (2007a) Three QTLs for Botrytis cinera resistance in tomato. Theor Appl Genet 114:585&#x02013;593 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17136515</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finkers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heusden</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer-Dekens</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maris</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The construction of a <italic>Solanum habrochaites</italic> LYC4 introgression line population and the identification of QTLs for resistance to <italic>Botrytis cinera</italic></article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>1071</fpage><lpage>1080</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-006-0500-2</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Finkers R, van Heusden AW, Meijer-Dekens F, van Kan JA, Maris P, Lindhout P (2007b) The construction of a Solanum habrochaites LYC4 introgression line population and the identification of QTLs for resistance to Botrytis cinera. Theor Appl Genet 114:1071&#x02013;1080 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17273845</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoeven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eannetta</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification, analysis, and utilization of conserved ortholog set markers for comparative genomics in higher plants</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1457</fpage><lpage>1467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.010479</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Fulton TM, van der Hoeven R, Eannetta NT, Tanksley SD (2002) Identification, analysis, and utilization of conserved ortholog set markers for comparative genomics in higher plants. Plant Cell 14:1457&#x02013;1467 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12119367</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Spilttstoesser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parthenocarpy in tomato</article-title><source>Hortic Rev</source><year>1984</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">George W, Scott J, Spilttstoesser W (1984) Parthenocarpy in tomato. Hortic Rev 6:65&#x02013;84 </citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivian-Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Koltunow</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR8</italic> is a negative regulator of fruit initiation in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1873</fpage><lpage>1886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.105.037192</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Goetz M, Vivian-Smith A, Johnson SD, Koltunow AM (2006) AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR8 is a negative regulator of fruit initiation in Arabidopsis. Plant Cell 18:1873&#x02013;1886 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16829592</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivian-Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koltunow</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of aberrant forms of <italic>AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR8</italic> stimulates parthenocarpy in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and tomato</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.107.104174</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Goetz M, Hooper LC, Johnson SD, Rodrigues JC, Vivian-Smith A, Koltunow AM (2007) Expression of aberrant forms of AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR8 stimulates parthenocarpy in Arabidopsis and tomato. Plant Physiol 145:351&#x02013;366 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17766399</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorguet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Heusden</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parthenocarpic fruit development in tomato</article-title><source>Plant Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2005-837494</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gorguet B, van Heusden AW, Lindhout P (2005) Parthenocarpic fruit development in tomato. Plant Biol 7:131&#x02013;139 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15822008</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorguet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Schipper</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Heusden</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindhout</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High resolution fine mapping of <italic>ps-2</italic>, a mutated gene conferring functional male sterility in tomato due to non-dehiscent anthers</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>1437</fpage><lpage>1448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-006-0389-9</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gorguet B, Schipper D, van Heusden AW, Lindhout P (2006) High resolution fine mapping of ps-2, a mutated gene conferring functional male sterility in tomato due to non-dehiscent anthers. Theor Appl Genet 113:1437&#x02013;1448 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16932878</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazzucato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Taddei</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Soressi</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>parthenocarpic fruit</italic> (<italic>pat</italic>) mutant of tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic> Mill.) sets seedless fruits and has aberrant anther and ovule development</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1998</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>114</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mazzucato A, Taddei AR, Soressi GP (1998) The parthenocarpic fruit (pat) mutant of tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum Mill.) sets seedless fruits and has aberrant anther and ovule development. Development 125:107&#x02013;114 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9389668</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monforte</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a set of near isogenic and backcross recombinant inbred lines containing most of the <italic>Lycopersicon hirsutum</italic> genome in a <italic>L. esculentum</italic> genetic background: a tool for gene mapping and gene discovery</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2000</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/gen-43-5-803</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Monforte AJ, Tanksley SD (2000) Development of a set of near isogenic and backcross recombinant inbred lines containing most of the Lycopersicon hirsutum genome in a L. esculentum genetic background: a tool for gene mapping and gene discovery. Genome 43:803&#x02013;813 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11081970</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Solow</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Skwarecki</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Buels</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Binns</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahrens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Keyder</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Menda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamir</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The SOL genomics network. A comparative resource for <italic>Solanaceae</italic> biology and beyond</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>1310</fpage><lpage>1317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.060707</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mueller LA, Solow TH, Taylor N, Skwarecki B, Buels R, Binns J, Lin C, Wright MH, Ahrens R, Wang Y, Herbst EV, Keyder ER, Menda N, Zamir D, Tanksley SD (2005) The SOL genomics network. A comparative resource for Solanaceae biology and beyond. Plant Physiol 138:1310&#x02013;1317 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16010005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><citation citation-type="other">Myburg AA, Remington DL (2000) Protocol for high-throughput AFLP analysis using LI-COR IR2 automated sequencer. NC State Forest Biotech AFLP protocol-Sept 2000</citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>De-Verna</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine mapping of quantitative trait loci using selected overlapping recombinant chromosomes, in an interspecific cross of tomato</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1990</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>735</fpage><lpage>742</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Paterson AH, De-Verna JW, Lanini B, Tanksley SD (1990) Fine mapping of quantitative trait loci using selected overlapping recombinant chromosomes, in an interspecific cross of tomato. Genetics 124:735&#x02013;742 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1968874</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Picken</surname><given-names>AJF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of pollination and fruit set in the tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic> Mill.)</article-title><source>J Hortic Sci</source><year>1984</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Picken AJF (1984) A review of pollination and fruit set in the tomato (Lycopersicon esculentum Mill.). J Hortic Sci 59:1&#x02013;13 </citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlled introgression of chromosomes from <italic>Solanum pennellii</italic> into <italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>: segregation and recombination</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1969</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>768</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rick CM (1969) Controlled introgression of chromosomes from Solanum pennellii into Lycopersicon esculentum: segregation and recombination. Genetics 62:753&#x02013;768 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17248457</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steward</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Via</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A rapid CTAB DNA isolation technique useful for RAPD fingerprinting and other PCR applications</article-title><source>Biotechniques</source><year>1993</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>748</fpage><lpage>750</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Steward CN, Via LE (1993) A rapid CTAB DNA isolation technique useful for RAPD fingerprinting and other PCR applications. Biotechniques 14:748&#x02013;750 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8512694</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganal</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonierbale</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Broun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandillo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Messeguer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pineda</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High density molecular linkage maps of tomato and potato genomes</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1992</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>1141</fpage><lpage>1160</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tanksley SD, Ganal MW, Prince JP, de Vicente MC, Bonierbale MW, Broun P, Fulton TM, Giovannoni JJ, Grandillo S, Martin GB, Messeguer R, Miller JC, Miller L, Paterson AH, Pineda O, Roder MS, Wing RA, Wu W, Young ND (1992) High density molecular linkage maps of tomato and potato genomes. Genetics 132:1141&#x02013;1160 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1360934</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ooijen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LOD significance thresholds for QTL analysis in experimental populations of diploid species</article-title><source>Heredity</source><year>1999</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.hdy.6886230</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Van Ooijen JW (1999) LOD significance thresholds for QTL analysis in experimental populations of diploid species. Heredity 83:613&#x02013;624 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10620035</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ooijen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><source>MapQTL&#x000ae; 5, software for the mapping of quantitative trait loci in experimental populations</source><year>2004</year><publisher-loc>Wageningen</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Kyazma B.V</publisher-name></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Van Ooijen JW (2004) MapQTL&#x000ae; 5, software for the mapping of quantitative trait loci in experimental populations. Kyazma B.V., Wageningen </citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ooijen</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Voorrips</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><source>JoinMap&#x000ae; 3.0, software for the calculation of genetic linkage maps</source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>Wageningen</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Plant Research International</publisher-name></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Van Ooijen JW, Voorrips RE (2001) JoinMap&#x000ae; 3.0, software for the calculation of genetic linkage maps. Plant Research International, Wageningen </citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cutler</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple method of preparing plant samples for PCR</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1993</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>4153</fpage><lpage>4154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/21.17.4153</pub-id></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wang H, Qi M, Cutler AJ (1993) A simple method of preparing plant samples for PCR. Nucleic Acids Res 21:4153&#x02013;4154 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8371994</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zijlstra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parthenocarpie in tomaat; twee nieuwe lijnen uit soortkruising</article-title><source>Zaadbelangen</source><year>1985</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>94</lpage></citation><citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Zijlstra S (1985) Parthenocarpie in tomaat; twee nieuwe lijnen uit soortkruising. Zaadbelangen 4:92&#x02013;94 </citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>