<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Plant Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Plant Sci.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Plant Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-462X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4999453</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.01286</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Association Mapping of Main Tomato Fruit Sugars and Organic Acids</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Jiantao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/294941/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Yao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn003"><sup>&#x02020;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Qin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Xinli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yating</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Zhirong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/189972/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Mingjun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/178095/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Lu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/254593/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>College of Horticulture, Northwest A&#x00026;F University</institution><country>Yangling, China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Key Laboratory of Protected Horticultural Engineering in Northwest, Ministry of Agriculture</institution><country>Yangling, China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>College of Forestry, Northwest A&#x00026;F University</institution><country>Yangling, China</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>College of Food Science and Engineering, Northwest A&#x00026;F University</institution><country>Yangling, China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Paul Christiaan Struik, Wageningen University and Research Centre, Netherlands</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Hiroshi Ezura, University of Tsukuba, Japan; Michael Benjamin Kantar, University of Hawai'i, USA</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Jing Zhang <email xlink:type="simple">yyzhj@nwsuaf.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Crop Science and Horticulture, a section of the journal Frontiers in Plant Science</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p>&#x02020;These authors have contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>1286</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2016 Zhao, Xu, Ding, Huang, Zhang, Zou, Li, Cui and Zhang.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Zhao, Xu, Ding, Huang, Zhang, Zou, Li, Cui and Zhang</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Association mapping has been widely used to map the significant associated loci responsible for natural variation in complex traits and are valuable for crop improvement. Sugars and organic acids are the most important metabolites in tomato fruits. We used a collection of 174 tomato accessions composed of <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> (123 accessions) and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> var <italic>cerasiforme</italic> (51 accessions) to detect significantly associated loci controlling the variation of main sugars and organic acids. The accessions were genotyped with 182 SSRs spreading over the tomato genome. Association mapping was conducted on the main sugars and organic acids detected by gas chromatography-mass spectrometer (GC-MS) over 2 years using the mixed linear model (MLM). We detected a total of 58 significantly associated loci (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) for the 17 sugars and organic acids, including fructose, glucose, sucrose, citric acid, malic acid. These results not only co-localized with several reported QTLs, including <italic>fru9.1/PV, suc9.1/PV, ca2.1/HS, ca3.1/PV, ca4.1/PV</italic>, and <italic>ca8.1/PV</italic>, but also provided a list of candidate significantly associated loci to be functionally validated. These significantly associated loci could be used for deciphering the genetic architecture of tomato fruit sugars and organic acids and for tomato quality breeding.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>tomato</kwd><kwd>association mapping</kwd><kwd>sugars</kwd><kwd>organic acids</kwd><kwd>metabolites</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Program for New Century Excellent Talents in University<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100004602</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">NCET-12-0474</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">National Natural Science Foundation of China<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001809</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn002">31301498</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="47"/><page-count count="11"/><word-count count="7047"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Sugars and organic acids are the key components impacting tomato quality and customer preferences. They account for over 60% of the dry matter, and contribute to soluble solid content (SSC) and also are essential to the flavor intensity (Davies et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">1981</xref>; Goff and Klee, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Baldwin et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Kader, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Bastias et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). However, in the long breeding processes, the sugars are usually evaluated by soluble solid content (SSC), and the organic acids are usually evaluated by titratable acid (TA; Saliba-Colombani et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Xu et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Ruggieri et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Sauvage et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). QTL mappings or genome-wide association studies (GWAS) focusing on the individual sugars and organic acids in tomato fruits were quite limited (Fulton et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Schauer et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Ruggieri et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Sauvage et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Besides, in the present available researches focusing on individual sugars and organic acids in tomato fruits, only a few of these metabolites were measured, such as fructose, glucose, sucrose, malic acid, citric acid, ascorbic acid (Osvald et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Fulton et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Schauer et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Ruggieri et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) or association mapping have been widely used in identifying candidate QTLs/genes that are related to various agronomically important traits and to uncover the genetic architecture that controls these traits (Atwell et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Li et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Shirasawa et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Chen et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Sauvage et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The development of metabolomics tools, such as gas chromatography-mass spectrometer (GC-MS) have facilitated the comprehensive phenotyping of complex metabolomic traits (Saito and Matsuda, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Recently the metabolite-based association study has validated the metabolome-GWAS in genetic improvement of complex traits (Riedelsheimer et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Chen et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Sauvage et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Wen et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Matsuda et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). However, the understanding of the genetic and molecular basis of natural variation of tomato fruit sugars and organic is still quite limited (Fulton et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Schauer et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Sauvage et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>Tomato is a major crop plant and a research model system for fruit development and is also an important source of fiber and nutrients in the human diet (Meissner et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">1997</xref>; Giovannoni, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Tomato Genome Consortium, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Many association studies have been published to date for studying the main morphological and nutritional traits in tomato (Mazzucato et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Shirasawa et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Xu et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Ruggieri et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Sauvage et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). However, GWAS or association mapping will probably remain an efficient way of investigating the missing heritability, as the significant associated signals may well define the genomic regions where rare variants, structural variants, and other forms of underlying variation are likely to cluster (Manolio et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>In this study, we aimed to investigate the genetic architecture of the main sugars and organic acids in tomato fruits. To reach this objective, fruit sugars and organic acids were evaluated by using GC-MS (Lisec et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). We then carried out an association mapping study using the mixed linear model (MLM) to detect the significant loci responsible for the natural variations of main sugars and organic acids. We present results on the genotypic diversity, heritability and significantly associated loci of the main sugars and organic acids in tomato.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Plant material</title><p>The experiments were performed on 174 tomato accessions comprised of 123 cherry tomato accessions (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> var. <italic>cerasiforme</italic>) and 51 large-fruit cultivars (<italic>S. lycopersicum</italic>; See Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">S1</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). All accessions were grown during the springs of 2013 and 2014, respectively, according to a randomized complete block design with three replicates (10 plants per replicate), as described in Zhang et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). All accessions received the same horticultural practices. All fruits were harvested at the red-ripe stage each sample consisted of ten fruits for each accession. After quickly removing the seeds, the flash was quickly cut into pieces and were immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C until analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Sugar and organic acid analysis</title><p>Extraction and derivatization of sugars, sugar alcohols and organic acids in tomato fruits were mainly according to Zhang et al. (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) with minor modifications. One hundred milligrams of flash tomato tissue was used in the extraction. Due to the wide range of the concentrations of sugars and organic acids, two vials with different volumes of extract were prepared for each sample, with 5 &#x003bc;L for highly abundant metabolites (fructose, sucrose, glucose, malic acid, etc.) and 100 &#x003bc;L for less abundant metabolites. Briefly, after fractionation of non-polar metabolites into chloroform, 5 and 100 &#x003bc;L of the polar phase of each sample were taken and transferred into separate 2.0 ml Eppendorf vials. These samples were then dried under vacuum without heating and then derivatized with methoxyamine hydrochloride and N-methyl-N-trimethylsilyl-trifluoroacetamide (MSTFA) sequentially (Lisec et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>).</p><p>After derivatization, the metabolites were analyzed via an Agilent 7890A GC/5795C MS (Agilent Technology, Palo Alto, CA, USA) with an electron ionization source. One microliter sample was injected and performed at 230&#x000b0;C in splitless mode with helium carrier gas flow at 1 ml/min. Chromatography was performed using a DB-5MS capillary column (20 m &#x000d7; 0.18 mm &#x000d7; 0.18 &#x003bc;m) with a 5 m Duraguard column in front. The temperature program started isothermal at 70&#x000b0;C for 2.471 min and then increased to 330&#x000b0;C by a 10.119&#x000b0;C/min ramp and kept for 2.471 min. Mass spectra were collected at 5.6 scans/s with an m/z 50&#x02013;600 scanning range. The transfer line temperature and the ion source temperature were set to 250 and 230&#x000b0;C, respectively.</p><p>Metabolites were identified by comparing fragmentation patterns with those in a mass spectral library generated on our GC/MS system and an annotated quadrupole GC-MS spectral library from the Golm Metabolome Database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://csbdb.mpimpgolm.mpg.de/csbdb/gmd/msri/gmd_msri.html">http://csbdb.mpimpgolm.mpg.de/csbdb/gmd/msri/gmd_msri.html</ext-link>). Ribitol was used as the international standard for quantification.</p></sec><sec><title>Association mapping</title><p>The DNA of the 174 accessions was extracted from fresh leaf tissue following the method of Fulton et al. (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>). Samples were genotyped with 182 SSR markers (see details in Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>), as described by Zhang et al. (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). The protocol for Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) and electrophoresis (6% PAGE) was described by Sun et al. (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). All SSR markers were mainly selected from the SOL Genomics Network (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sgn.cornell.edu/">http://sgn.cornell.edu/</ext-link>) and the VegMarks database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://vegmarks.nivot.affrc.go.jp/">http://vegmarks.nivot.affrc.go.jp/</ext-link>). Only markers with minor allele frequency (MAF) &#x0003e; 0.05 were genotyped with the whole accessions (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Population structure of the 174 tomato accessions was analyzed via STRUCTURE2.3.3 software (Pritchard et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>). We set the number of hypothetical subpopulations (K) at 2&#x02013;10 in order to evaluate the population structure with an admixture model and the Markov Chain Monte Carlo replicates and the burn-in length was 200,000, 100,000, respectively. We used Evanno transformation method to infer the optimal K of populations (Evanno et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The kinship matrix was calculated via SPAGeDi software (Hardy and Vekemans, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). We calculated association mapping between markers and phenotypes using the mixed linear model (Q+K model) via TASSEL 2.1 software (Bradbury et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Decay of LD and the corresponding significance level (<italic>P</italic>-value) were calculated using TASSEL 2.1 software (Bradbury et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). We analyzed the metabolic data for GWAS in 2013 and 2014 separately. The raw <italic>P</italic>-values were corrected for multiple tests in order to reduce false positive associations using the Benjamini and Hochberg FDR test (Benjamini and Hochberg, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>). After <italic>P</italic>-value-correction, we used <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.005 as the value to detect associations and <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 as the significant value to reduce false positive associations. The amount of phenotypic variation explained by each marker was estimated by <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistics</title><p>SAS 8.1 program (SAS institute, Cary, NC) or the R statistical Software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org">http://www.r-project.org</ext-link>) 3.0.2 were used for statistical analyses. We replaced the values of zero (undetectable) for all metabolites by the smallest non-zero value in the whole dataset (Mathieu et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). All the phenotypes were log<sub>2</sub>-transformed (ng g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> fresh weight h<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) before further association mapping analysis. Correlations among sugars and organic acids and other traits were analyzed in the R statistical software and the results were presented via HemI 1.0. We estimated genetic variance, genetic by environment interaction variance, technical variance, and heritability values according to the method of Xu et al. (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Phenotyping</title><p>In total, 17 sugars, sugar alcohols and organic acids were detected using the 20 &#x003bc;L and 100 &#x003bc;L reaction systems, with eight sugars and nine organic acids, respectively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The main sugars in tomato fruits are fructose, glucose, and galactose. The highest concentration was detected on glucose. The concentration of allose and threitol is relatively lower and the lowest concentration was observed on myo-inostiol. Among the eight organic acids, two of them are amino acids (L-proline and L-glutamic acid). Their concentration is relatively lower compared with the other organic acids. The highest concentration was observed on gluconic acid. The concentration of butanedioic acid was also very high. The concentration of citric acid and malic acid were relatively lower, compared with gluconic acid and butanedioic acid. Among all the sugars and organic acids, only some of them were likely to be normally distributed, such as fructose, galactose, myo-inositol, citric acid, gluconic acid, etc. (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">S1</xref>). The heritability of the 17 metabolites varied from 0.293 (hexdecanoic acid) to 0.674 (citric acid). Fructose, glucose, sucrose, citric acid, and malic acid had a higher heritability value compared with the other compounds. So, association mapping was analyzed separately for the metabolite traits in 2013 and 2014.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>Phenotypic variation of main tomato fruit sugars and organic acids among the 174 tomato accessions</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Phenotype</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>H</italic><sup>2</sup></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Max (ppm)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Min (ppm)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Average (ppm)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>SD</italic> (ppm)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.553</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.139</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.878</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.839</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.519</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.547</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.682</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.344</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.438</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.398</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.635</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.838</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.892</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.032</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galactose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.611</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.073</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.131</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.606</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.409</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myo-inositol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.382</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.683</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.079</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.268</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allose</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.468</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.418</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.013</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.806</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.737</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Threitol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.296</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.343</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.054</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.240</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.665</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Octanol</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.421</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.398</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.148</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.576</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.287</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citric acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.674</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.040</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.527</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.518</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.890</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.668</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.426</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.512</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.106</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.268</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Proline</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.487</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.621</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.834</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.523</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.531</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.744</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.579</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Glutamic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.429</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.311</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.244</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.185</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.988</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gluconic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.364</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.231</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.495</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.927</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.823</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexdecanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.293</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.890</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.196</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.534</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.228</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Octadecanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.358</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.770</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.064</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.135</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.007</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butanedioic acid</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.485</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.714</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.192</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.809</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.920</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Maximum (Max), minimum (Min), standard deviation (SD)</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Pearson correlation coefficients (<italic>r</italic>) among the 17 metabolites revealed that compounds corresponding to a functional classification of the metabolites tended to be positively correlated (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). For example, fructose, glucose, and galactose had a significant positive correlation value and were clustered together with each other. The main organic acids, such as citric acid, malic acid, butanoic acid, were also positively clustered together. We observed that main sugars and organic acids were negatively corrected.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>The Pearson correlation analysis of the main sugars, organic acids, morphological, nutritional, and sensory traits</bold>. Panel <bold>(A)</bold> is the correlation between the main sugars and organics; Panel <bold>(B)</bold> is the correlation between the main sugars, organic acids, and morphological, nutritional and sensory traits. Positive correlations are indicated in red, while negative correlations are indicated in blue.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-01286-g0001"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Association mapping</title><p>We assessed population structure of the 174 tomato accession using STRUCTURE 2.3.3 software with 182 SSRs. According to Evanno method (Evanno et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), the 174 tomato accessions could be divided into two sub-populations (Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">S2</xref>). The division could be seen as the separation between cherry tomato types and large-fruit types (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). The tomato genome decayed at about 8 cM (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; see Figure <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM7">S3</xref>). Using the mixed linear model in TASSEL under MAF&#x0003e;5%, after Bonferroni correction, 139 marker-trait associations (MTAs) were detected in 2013 (97 MTAs) or 2014 (83 MTAs) and 40 MTAs of them were detected in both years (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, see more details in Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>). Among these, 58 MTAs had a significant value (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), with 40, 35 significant associations in 2013, 2014, respectively. We observed at least one MTA on all sugars and organic acids except for threitol. These MTAs were spread unevenly over tomato genome, with all chromosomes carried at least one MTA (chromosome 1, Chr1) and up to 30 MTAs were detected on Chr9. The number of MTAs ranged from zero (no MTAs were observed for threitol) to 38 (citric acid).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>Association mapping for 17 sugars, sugar alcohols and organic acids in tomato fruit estimated with K+Q (MLM) model on 174 tomato accessions (only those where <italic><bold>P</bold></italic> &#x0003c; 0.001 are listed)</bold>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Phenotype</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Locus</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Chromosome</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Position<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1a"><sup>a</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>2013</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>2014</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Corrected <italic>P</italic><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1b"><sup>b</sup></xref></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Corrected <italic>P</italic></bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fructose</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES291</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0925</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0227</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES671</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0501</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS2911</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0643</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.12E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0255</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR122</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.73E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES520</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.57E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0242</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS801</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0801</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glucose</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES671</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0893</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0725</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS2911</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93.92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.15E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0249</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR122</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0053</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.75E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0404</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS801</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0716</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.15E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0649</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sucrose</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES291</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.76E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0677</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES835</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.49E-06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1694</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.06E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1212</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES945</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.80E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0904</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR122</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0662</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.15E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0985</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0841</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.28E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0749</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS2132</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.28E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0689</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS801</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.94E-05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1290</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66E-05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1517</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR142</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1274</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR110</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.15E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1014</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES618</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0750</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0526</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Galactose</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES671</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.84E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0669</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.12E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0475</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS801</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.89E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0529</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Allose</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS821</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.99E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0551</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0293</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Octanol</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES291</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.61E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0284</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0269</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR133</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.69E-12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1121</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Citric acid</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR92</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0726</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0315</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0315</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS1548</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.30E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0388</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0498</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES1276</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.99</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.07E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0317</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0451</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS292</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0210</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.98E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0288</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0801</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS364</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.73E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0377</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0445</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS862</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0338</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0393</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES945</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.82</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0354</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.65E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0608</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.27E-07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0946</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.12E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0577</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS821</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.55E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0469</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.15E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0595</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS354</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.81E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0427</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS607</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.89</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.63E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0362</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.06E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0581</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS947</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0433</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.58E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0339</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0436</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS560</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.87</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0578</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES562</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.64E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0414</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0375</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS2885</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40E-05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0007</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Malic acid</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOM166</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.62E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0362</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L-Glutamic acid</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS827</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.11E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0458</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.70E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0323</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gluconic acid</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR266</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1013</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Octadecanoic acid</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES786</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.42E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0773</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Butanedioic acid</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS207</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.23E-07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0904</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04E-05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0564</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.24E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0124</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS821</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.76E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0254</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.15E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0169</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR344</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.36E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0437</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOM166</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.57E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0244</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR142</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.61E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0376</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSR110</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.04E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0344</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.08E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0028</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES623</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.25E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0223</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0143</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TES6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.83E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0346</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TGS3266</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.33</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.67E-04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0358</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TN1a"><label>a</label><p><italic>Genetic distance of the marker was mainly found in EXPEN2000 reference map (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.solgenomics.net">http://www.solgenomics.net</ext-link>)</italic>.</p></fn><fn id="TN1b"><label>b</label><p><italic>P-values are corrected following the Benjamini and Hochberg (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>) procedure (see section Materials and Methods)</italic>.</p></fn><p><italic>ns, no significant; &#x02013;, not given</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>For the eight sugars and sugar alcohols, 56 MTAs were observed with 31, 43 MTAs in 2013 and 2014, respectively. Among these, 18 MTAs were detected in both years. The largest MTA number was detected for sucrose (16 MTAs, either in 2013 or 2014) and no MTA was detected for threitol. For fructose, nine MTAs were observed in total and two of them were observed both in 2013 and 2014. For sucrose, 16 MTAs were observed and the most significant association was detected on TES835 (Chr3) both in 2013 and 2014, explaining 16.94, 12.12% of the phenotypic variation. The other significantly associated marker was TGS801 (Chr9) and was also detected both in 2013 and 2014, explaining 12.9, 15.17% of the phenotypic variation, respectively. For octonol, it was significantly associated with marker SSR133 (Chr 4) in 2014. This association had a very high significance value (<italic>P</italic> = 3.69E-12), accounting for 11.21% of the phenotypic variation. However, no significant association was detected between this marker and octonol variation in 2013.</p><p>For the nine organic acids, 83 MTAs were detected, with 66, 50 MTAs in 2013, 2014, respectively. Among these, 33 MTAs were detected in both years. For citric acid, 38 MTAs were detected in 2013 or 2014, representing the largest MTAs for all measured metabolites, with at least one MTA for each chromosome. The most significant association was observed on SSR45 (Chr7) in 2013 (<italic>P</italic> = 8.27E-07), accounting for 9.46% of the phenotypic variation. Besides, this association was also observed in 2014, representing 5.77% of the phenotypic variation. For malic acid, five MTAs were observed either in 2013 or 2014 (Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">S3</xref>). The most significant association was observed on TOM166 (Chr9) in 2013, accounting for 3.62% of the phenotypic variation. For butanedioic acid, 20 MTAs were detected either in 2013 or 2014, and 10 of them had a significance value (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). For proline and glutamic acid, the two main amino acids with a high concentration in tomato fruits, four and six MTAs were observed, either in 2013 or 2014, respectively. The two MTAs with a significance value for glutamic acid were TGS827 (Chr3) and TES56 (Chr3) both in 2013, explaining 4.58, 3.23% of the phenotypic variation, respectively. Less MTAs were observed for butanoic acid, gluconic acid, and hexdecanoic acid, with two, one and one MTA, either in 2013 or 2014, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Phenotype diversity</title><p>In this study, we observed up to 17 sugars, sugar alcohols and organic acids (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), which greatly diversified the reported sugar and organic acid types in tomato fruits. In tomato fruits, there are many different sugars, sugar alcohols, and organic acids and strong Pearson correlation coefficients were observed among these metabolites. This is particularly true for fructose, glucose, and galactose and the main organic acids, such as citric acid, malic acid, and butanoic acid (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). Besides, we also observed that the concentration of sugars and organic acids were significantly correlated with some important tomato fruit volatiles, in positive correlations or negative correlations (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). Compounds corresponding to the same functional classification of the metabolites tended to be positively correlated, as revealed in our previous studies (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). These results demonstrate the diverse biological functions of the sugars and organic acids in shaping of tomato fruit quality. The concentrations of fructose, glucose, sucrose, and galactose were negatively correlated with fruit morphological traits, including fruit weight (FW), fruit equatorial diameter (ED), and fruit polar diameter (PD) and were positively correlated with soluble solid content (SSC). Malic acid, citric acid and proline were negatively correlated with ascorbic acid (AsA) and SSC. We also observed some positive or negative correlations between the main sugars and organic acids with the main volatiles. For the complete correlation data, see Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">S4</xref>. Similar results were also found in other previous studies (Fulton et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Ruggieri et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), demonstrating the complexity of the nutritional characterization and genetic makeup of tomato fruit quality.</p></sec><sec><title>Population structure and LD</title><p>Population structure is a strong confounding factor in GWAS and could lead to false positive associations (Pritchard et al., <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; McCarthy et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Nordborg and Weigel, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Shirasawa et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Based on 182 SSR markers, the 174 tomato accessions could be divided into two sub-populations and the division could be seen as the separation between cherry tomato types and large-fruit types (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). However, the concentrations of the sugars and organic acids detected in this study varied greatly among the 174 tomato accessions (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). This could be mainly due to the narrow genetic diversity in the tomato breeding history of intensive human selection (Miller and Tanksley, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">1990</xref>; Lin et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In cultivated tomato, LD decays over large genomic regions and could up to several Mb, which is advantageous for GWAS, as fewer markers being able to cover the whole tomato genome (Xu et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Sauvage et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In this study, the LD decays at about 8 cM and the average marker genome coverage is about 5.2 cM (960/182), demonstrating that using the 182 SSRs is enough to cover the tomato genome. Our previous GWAS confirmed that using these SSRs could detect positive marker-trait associations (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Cherry tomato accessions could be seen as a mosaic of wild and cultivated tomato genomes, and could be useful to overcome the high LD for GWAS (Ranc et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Xu et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Our previous GWAS focused on the main fruit quality traits, such FW, SSC, AsA, LYC, and 28 volatiles in this 174 tomato accessions also confirmed this, demonstrating the feasibility of this study. However, the overall SSRs used in our study is still relatively limited, comparing with the dense SNPs available in tomato genomes. With a higher genome marker density, such as SNPs, GWAS could be used to detect candidate genes directly linked to the metabolic composition of sugars and organic acids in tomato fruits, despite a high LD level and population structure in tomato (Ruggieri et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Sauvage et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Association mapping</title><p>A total of 56 MTAs were associated with the seven sugars in 2013 (31 MTAs) or 2014 (43 MTAs) with at least two MTAs (myo-inositol) and up to 16 MTAs (sucrose). For the nine organic acids, 83 MTAs were detected in 2013 (66 MTAs) or 2014 (50 MTAs). Fulton et al. (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) detected 23, 18, and 10 QTLs for fructose, glucose, and sucrose, respectively, using four tomato advanced backcross populations. Beside, they also observed 17 QTLs for citric acid, 20 QTLs for glutamic acid and 21 QTLs for malic acid. Schauer et al. (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) detected up to 332 QTLs for the main tomato primary metabolites in a tomato IL population, including 104 QTLs for 22 amino acids, 102 QTLs for 22 organic acids, and 39 QTLs for 12 sugars. Among these, fourwere detected for fructose, three for glucose, in all 3 years' field trails, even though only two and one QTLs were detected for citric acid and malic acid, respectively. Our results obtained via a GWAS approach contrasted with these results in terms of the number of QTLs and their chromosome positions. Similar results were also found using a GWAS approach for the 36 metabolite traits in a collection of tomato accessions by Sauvage et al. (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Among the 44 significant associations detected within the 36 traits by Sauvage et al. (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), only two, three significant associations were observed for fructose and sucrose, respectively. For citric acid, malic acid, and proline, only one, two and two significant associations were detected, respectively. This difference could be due to the methodological principles underlying QTL mapping and GWAS and be explained by the more stringent threshold used in GWAS and the confounding effect of population structure (Sauvage et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Similar results were also found in Arabidopsis (Chan et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), maize (Riedelsheimer et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), and rice (Chen et al., <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), indicating that GWAS has a larger variability and the linkage mapping relies on a much narrower genetic pool, comparing with association mapping (Riedelsheimer et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>However, our results still confirmed several reported QTLs on main tomato fruit sugars and organic acids (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Fructose were associated with two SSRs (TES291 and TGS127) on chromosome one (Chr1). Schauer et al. (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) detected 39 QTLs for 12 sugars. Among these, one major QTL was detected for fructose on Chr1 in IL1-1-3, across all 3 years' field trails. Fulton et al. (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) also detected one QTL for fructose on Chr1 at about 131 cM. These results demonstrate that there should be one major QTL for the variation of fructose on Chr1. Besides, there are another three QTLs in Fulton et al. (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) that are likely to co-localized with the associated loci in this study. For instance, <italic>fru9.1/PV</italic> on Chr9 was located in less than 0.3 cM away from TGS801, and we observed that this loci was significantly associated with the variation of fructose in 2014 and could explain 8.01% of the variation. <italic>fructose6.1/PV</italic> was located about 10 cM away from the significantly associated loci TGS2911. This significantly associated loci only explained 3.7% of the phenotypic variation. This could be mainly due to the large genomic distance between the associated loci and QTL (&#x0003e;8 cM). However, it is still possible that this association might be caused be <italic>fructose6.1/PV</italic>, based on previous GWAS results that tomato genome decays at about 10&#x02013;20 cM (Mazzucato et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; van Berloo et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Xu et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Besides, fructose and glucose were both associated with TGS2911, and Fulton et al. (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) reported there was also a QTL (<italic>glu6.1/PV</italic>) for glucose near TGS2911. This observation suggests that in the near region of TGS2911, there are either two dependent QTLs/genes or one gene involved in the sugar metabolic pathways. Sucrose was significantly associated with four loci on chr9 (TGS801, SSR142, SSR110, and TES1028). Fulton et al. (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) reported two QTLs (<italic>suc9.1/PV</italic> and <italic>suc9.2/PV</italic>) for sucrose on Chr9. <italic>suc9.1/PV</italic> was located about 5 cM away from the significantly associated loci SSR142. <italic>suc9.2/PV</italic> was located about 7 cM away from the significantly associated loci SSR110. These two significant associations accounted for 12.74, 10.14% of the variation of sucrose in 2014 and could be mainly due to <italic>suc9.1/PV</italic> and <italic>suc9.2/PV</italic>, respectively.</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Comparison of significant associations and co-localized QTLs identified by linkage mapping</bold>. The names and Positions of SSRs are showed on the right and left of the chromosomes, respectively. Co-localized QTLs are mainly reported in Fulton et al. (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Fru, fructose; glu, glucose; suc, sucrose; ca, citric acid.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpls-07-01286-g0002"/></fig><p>Citric acid was associated with up to 38 loci with at least one MTA on each chromosome, representing the largest number of MTAs for all traits. Among these, 18 MTAs had a significance value (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Fulton et al. (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) detected up to 17 QTLs for citric acid. Among these, we confirmed at least four of them, including <italic>ca2.1/HS, ca3.1/PV, ca4.1/HS</italic>, and <italic>ca8.1/PM</italic>. The significantly associated loci SSR32 was about 3 cM away from <italic>ca2.1/HS</italic>, accounting for 3.15% of the phenotypic variation. The significantly associated loci SSR601 was about 1 cM away from <italic>ca3.1/PV</italic> and TES734 was less than 1 cM away from <italic>ca4.1/HS</italic>. TGS947 was about 6 cM away from <italic>ca8.1/PM</italic>. Since the LD of the tomato population decayed at about 8 cM based on 182 SSRs (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), these three significant associations could be mainly caused by <italic>ca2.1/HS, ca3.1/PV</italic>, and <italic>ca8.1/PM</italic>. Besides, we also detected three MTAs on chr1 (SSR92, TGS1156, and TGS127). <italic>ca1.1/PR</italic> and <italic>ca1.2/PR</italic> are two QTLs on Chr1 detected in Fulton et al. (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) in the near region of SSR92 and TGS127 (&#x0003c;8 cM). This suggested that the two significantly associated loci SSR92 and TGS127 could also be caused by <italic>ca1.1/PR</italic> and <italic>ca1.2/PR</italic>.</p><p>Many primary and secondary metabolites including sugars and organic acids in tomato fruits have a relatively low heritability (Schauer et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Sauvage et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Zhang et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). However, even those traits exhibiting a low heritability could still be valuable targets for fruit quality breeding purposes (Schauer et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Apart from fructose, glucose, sucrose, malic acid, citric acid, attentions should also be paid to the other sugars and organic acids, such as galactose, butanoic acid, and butanedioic acid, etc. GWAS will probably remain an efficient way of investigating the remaining heritability. Because the available associations may well define the genomic regions of rare variants, structural variants and other forms of underlying variation (Manolio et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The association mapping approach undertaken allowed the detection of 58 significant associations for the main tomato fruit sugars and organic acids. These metabolites are essential for deciphering the genetic architecture of tomato fruit nutritional composition. Our findings suggested that using SSRs and the mixed linear model (MLM) were suitable for detecting significant associations with tomato fruit sugars and organic acids. Several formerly identified QTLs, such as <italic>fru9.1/PV, suc9.1/PV, ca2.1/HS, ca3.1/PV, ca4.1/HS</italic>, and <italic>ca8.1/PM</italic> were co-localized with a group of significant associated loci, which validated this study. Most of the sugars and organic had a relatively low heritability. Further GWAS will probably remain an efficient way in investigating the remaining heritability and detecting more significantly associated loci for tomato fruit sugars and organic acids.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JTZ, JZ, and ZZ designed the study. JTZ and YX carried out the main GC-MS analysis and molecular mapping, analyzed the data, and drafted the manuscript. XH, QD, ML, LC participate in the data analysis of sugars and organic acids. YZ participated in genotyping. All authors corrected and approved the final version.</p></sec><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the Program for New Century Excellent Talents in University (No. NCET-12-0474), National Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No. 31301498), Agricultural Science and Technology Innovation and Research in Shaanxi province (Grant No. 2016NY-165) and the National Agricultural Science Foundation (No. 201203002).</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank Dr. Fengwang Ma for his encouragement and helpful advice; as well as Dr. Zheng Li, Xiaohui Hu, and Yanxu Yin for their technical support. We also thank Priscilla Licht for her help in revising our English composition. We thank Dr. Yanhong Hu for the helping in R analyses. We gratefully acknowledge the assistance of Xiaoting Zhou and Lipan Hu in harvesting the fruits for this study.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s7"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpls.2016.01286">http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fpls.2016.01286</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><bold>The number and origin of the whole accessions</bold>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table1.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><bold>Detailed information for 182 SSR markers used for association mapping in this research</bold>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table2.XLS"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><bold>Genome-wide associations for 17 sugars, sugar alcohols and organic acids in tomato fruit estimated with K+Q (MLM) model on 174 tomato accessions (only those where <italic><bold>P</bold></italic> &#x0003c; 0.005 are listed)</bold>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table3.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p><bold>The Pearson correlation coefficients (<italic><bold>r</bold></italic>) among sugars, organic acids, nutritional traits, and volatiles</bold>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table4.XLS"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM5"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><bold>Frequency distribution of the content of the detected 17 sugars and organic acids</bold>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image1.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM6"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><bold>Optimal K of the population structure of all accessions based on 182 SSR markers, according to Evanno method (2005)</bold>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image2.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM7"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><bold>Estimates of LD (<italic><bold>r</bold></italic><sup><bold>2</bold></sup>) over genetic distance on all chromosomes for all 174 tomato accessions</bold>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image3.jpg"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atwell</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilhj&#x000e1;lmsson</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide association study of 107 phenotypes in <italic>Arabidopsis thalia</italic> Maher na inbred lines</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>465</volume>, <fpage>627</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>631</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08800</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20336072?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20336072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodner</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Plotto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Interaction of volatiles, sugars, and acids on perception of tomato aroma and flavor descriptors</article-title>. <source>J. Food Sci.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>S294</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S307</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1750-3841.2008.00825.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19241574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19241574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bastias</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Climent</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valcarcel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosello</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Cadenas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casaretto</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Modulation of organic acids and sugar content in tomato fruits by an abscisic acid-regulated transcription factor</article-title>. <source>Physiol. Plant.</source>
<volume>141</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.2010.01435.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21128945?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21128945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>. <source>J. R. Stat. Soc. Series B (Methodological)</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>300</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroon</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Casstevens</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramdoss</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckler</surname><given-names>E. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>TASSEL: software for association mapping of complex traits in diverse samples</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>2633</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2635</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btm308</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17586829?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>E. K. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kliebenstein</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Understanding the evolution of defense metabolites in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> using genome-wide association mapping</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>185</volume>, <fpage>991</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1007</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.109.108522</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19737743?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19737743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide association analyses provide genetic and biochemical insights into natural variation in rice metabolism</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>714</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>721</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24908251?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24908251</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A novel integrated method for large-scale detection, identification, and quantification of widely targeted metabolites: application in the study of rice metabolomics</article-title>. <source>Mol. Plant</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1780</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/sst080</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23702596?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23702596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobson</surname><given-names>G. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGlasson</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>The constituents of tomato fruit&#x02013;the influence of environment, nutrition, and genotype</article-title>. <source>Crit. Rev. Food Sci.</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>280</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10408398109527317</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7030623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7030623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evanno</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Regnaut</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Detecting the number of clusters of individuals using the software STRUCTURE: a simulation study</article-title>. <source>Mol. Ecol.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>2611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2620</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2005.02553.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15969739?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15969739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bucheli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Voirol</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;tiard</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Quantitative trait loci (QTL) affecting sugars, organic acids and other biochemical properties possibly contributing to flavor, identified in four advanced backcross populations of tomato</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>
<volume>127</volume>, <fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>177</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1020209930031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chunzoongse</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Microprep protocol for extraction of DNA from tomato and other herbaceous plants</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol. Biol. Rep.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>209</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02670897</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giovannoni</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Molecular biology of fruit maturation and ripening</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>725</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>749</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.52.1.725</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11337414?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11337414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goff</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klee</surname><given-names>H. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Plant volatile compounds: sensory cues for health and nutritional value?</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>311</volume>, <fpage>815</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>819</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1112614</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16469919?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16469919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>O. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vekemans</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>SPAGeDi: a versatile computer program to analyse spatial genetic structure at the individual or population levels</article-title>. <source>Mol. Ecol. Notes</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>618</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>620</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-8286.2002.00305.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27544487?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27544487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kader</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Flavor quality of fruits and vegetables</article-title>. <source>J. Sci. Food Agr.</source>
<volume>88</volume>, <fpage>1863</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1868</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jsfa.3293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide association study dissects the genetic architecture of oil biosynthesis in maize kernels</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2484</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23242369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23242369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Genomic analyses provide insights into the history of tomato breeding</article-title>. <source>Nat. Genet.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>1220</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1226</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3117</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25305757?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25305757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lisec</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willmitzer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Gas chromatography mass spectrometry&#x02013;based metabolite profiling in plants</article-title>. <source>Nat. Protoc.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>396</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2006.59</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17406261?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17406261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manolio</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>F. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hindorff</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Finding the missing heritability of complex diseases</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>461</volume>, <fpage>747</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>753</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08494</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19812666?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19812666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cin</surname><given-names>V. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bliss</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Flavour compounds in tomato fruits: identification of loci and potential pathways affecting volatile composition</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>337</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ern294</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19088332?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19088332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakabayashi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonemaru</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebana</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Metabolome-genome-wide association study dissects genetic architecture for generating natural variation in rice secondary metabolism</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tpj.12681</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25267402?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25267402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazzucato</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitocchi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosconi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanni</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Negri</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Genetic diversity, structure and marker-trait associations in a collection of Italian tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> L.) landraces</article-title>. <source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source>
<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>669</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-007-0699-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18193185?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18193185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abecasis</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardon</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>J. P. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide association studies for complex traits: consensus, uncertainty and challenges</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>356</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>369</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2344</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18398418?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18398418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meissner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melamed</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Levyatuv</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalev</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>A new model system for tomato genetics</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>1465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1472</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313x.1997.12061465.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20154339?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20154339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>RFLP analysis of phylogenetic relationships and genetic variation in the genes <italic>Lycopersicon</italic></article-title>. <source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source>
<volume>80</volume>, <fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>448</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00226743</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24221000?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24221000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nordborg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Next-generation genetics in plants</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>456</volume>, <fpage>720</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>723</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07629</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19079047?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19079047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osvald</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrovic</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Demsar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Sugar and organic acid content of tomato fruits (<italic>Lycopersicon lycopersicum</italic> Mill.) grown on aeroponics at different plant density</article-title>. <source>Acta Aliment. Hung.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/AAlim.30.2001.1.6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>). <article-title>Inference of population structure using multilocus genotype data</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>155</volume>, <fpage>945</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>959</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10835412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10835412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranc</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Munos</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Paslier</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauveau</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bounon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide association mapping in tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) is possible using genome admixture of <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> var. <italic>cerasiforme</italic></article-title>. <source>G3 (Bethesda)</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>853</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>864</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.112.002667</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22908034?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22908034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riedelsheimer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lisec</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Czedik-Eysenberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulpice</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grieder</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide association mapping of leaf metabolic profiles for dissecting complex traits in maize</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>8872</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8877</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1120813109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22615396?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22615396</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruggieri</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Francese</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Alessandro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigano</surname><given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>An association mapping approach to identify favourable alleles for tomato fruit quality breeding</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>337</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-014-0337-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25465385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25465385</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Metabolomics for functional genomics, systems biology, and biotechnology</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Plant Biol.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>489</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.043008.092035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19152489?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19152489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saliba-Colombani</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Causse</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Langlois</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Philouze</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buret</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Genetic analysis of organoleptic quality in fresh market tomato. 1. Mapping QTLs for physical and chemical traits</article-title>. <source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>272</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001220051643</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauvage</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauchet</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>P. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikoloski</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide association in tomato reveals 44 candidate loci for fruit metabolic traits</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>165</volume>, <fpage>1120</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1132</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.241521</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24894148?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24894148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Semel</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balbo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinfath</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Repsilber</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Selbig</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Mode of inheritance of primary metabolic traits in tomato</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Online</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>523</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.107.056523</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18364465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18364465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Semel</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roessner</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balbo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrari</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Comprehensive metabolic profiling and phenotyping of interspecific introgression lines for tomato improvement</article-title>. <source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>454</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt1192</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16531992?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16531992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinhauser</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strelkov</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schomburg</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>GC-MS libraries for the rapid identification of metabolites in complex biological samples</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett.</source>
<volume>579</volume>, <fpage>1332</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1337</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2005.01.029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15733837?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15733837</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirasawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuoka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsunaga</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide association studies using single nucleotide polymorphism markers developed by re-sequencing of the genomes of cultivated tomato</article-title>. <source>DNA Res.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>603</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dst033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23903436?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23903436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Dynamic QTL analysis for fruit lycopene content and total soluble solid content in a <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> &#x000d7; <italic>S. pimpinellifolium</italic> cross</article-title>. <source>Genet. Mol. Res.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>3696</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3710</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4238/2012.August.17.8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22930431?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Tomato Genome Consortium</collab></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The tomato genome sequence provides insights into fleshy fruit evolution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>485</volume>, <fpage>635</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>641</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11119</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22660326?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22660326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Berloo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ursem</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbakel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gort</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Eeuwijk</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Diversity and linkage disequilibrium analysis within a selected set of cultivated tomatoes</article-title>. <source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source>
<volume>117</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-008-0755-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18389208?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18389208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Metabolome-based genome-wide association study of maize kernel leads to novel biochemical insights</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>3438</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms4438</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24633423?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24633423</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranc</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;os</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolland</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouchet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Desplat</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Phenotypic diversity and association mapping for fruit quality traits in cultivated tomato and related species</article-title>. <source>Theor. Appl. Genet.</source>
<volume>126</volume>, <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>581</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-012-2002-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23124430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23124430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide association-mapping for fruit quality traits in tomato</article-title>. <source>Euphytica</source>
<volume>207</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>451</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-015-1567-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Genome-wide association mapping for tomato volatiles positively contributing to tomato flavor</article-title>. <source>Front. Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<issue>1042</issue>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.01042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26640472?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26640472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Developmental changes of carbohydrates, organic acids, amino acids, and phenolic compounds in &#x02018;Honeycrisp&#x02019; apple flesh</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source>
<volume>123</volume>, <fpage>1013</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1018</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2010.05.053</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>