<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Breed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol. Breed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Breeding</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1380-3743</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1572-9788</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5395597</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">664</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11032-017-0664-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mapping quantitative trait loci for heat tolerance of reproductive traits in tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Jiemeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Driedonks</surname><given-names>Nicky</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rutten</surname><given-names>Marc J. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vriezen</surname><given-names>Wim H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>Gert-Jan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8575-0959</contrib-id><name><surname>Rieu</surname><given-names>Ivo</given-names></name><address><phone>+31 24 3652761</phone><email>i.rieu@science.ru.nl</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000122931605</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5590.9</institution-id><institution>Department of Molecular Plant Physiology, </institution><institution>Radboud University, </institution></institution-wrap>6525 AJ Nijmegen, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Bayer Vegetable Seeds, 6083 AB Nunhem, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>ENZA Zaden Research and Development B.V, 1602 DB Enkhuizen, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>37</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>58</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p>Global warming has become a worldwide concern due to its adverse effects on agricultural output. In particular, long-term mildly high temperatures interfere with sexual reproduction and thus fruit and seed set. To uncover the genetic basis of observed variation in tolerance against heat, a bi-parental F<sub>2</sub> mapping population from two contrasting cultivars, i.e. Nagcarlang and NCHS-1, was generated and phenotyped under continuous mild heat conditions for a number of traits underlying reproductive success, i.e. pollen viability, pollen number, style length, anther length, style protrusion, female fertility and flowering characteristics, i.e. inflorescence number and flowers per inflorescence. Quantitative trait loci (QTLs) were identified for most of these traits, including a single, highly significant one for pollen viability, which accounted for 36% of phenotypic variation in the population and modified pollen viability under high temperature with around 20%. QTLs for some traits colocalised, indicating trait dependency or pleiotropic-effect loci. We conclude that a limited set of major genes determines differences in performance of reproductive traits under continuous mild heat in tomato. The results contribute to our fundamental understanding of pollen thermotolerance and may support development of more heat-tolerant tomato varieties.</p><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s11032-017-0664-2) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>QTL mapping</kwd><kwd>Reproductive heat tolerance</kwd><kwd>Pollen viability</kwd><kwd>Tomato</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004543</institution-id><institution>China Scholarship Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>201207565002</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Jiemeng</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000780</institution-id><institution>European Commission</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>289220 (Marie Curie Initial Training Network: Solanaceae Pollen Thermotolarance/SPOT-ITN)</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Rieu</surname><given-names>Ivo</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Dutch Topsector Horticulture and Starting Materials</institution></funding-source><award-id>2013-H320</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Rieu</surname><given-names>Ivo</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Science+Business Media Dordrecht 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>High temperature is one of the major abiotic stress factors affecting plants, having adverse effects on both growth and reproduction. In an agricultural context, this leads to negative effects on yields (Jha et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2014</xref>; Driedonks et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2016</xref>). Temperature projections for the coming century show a continuing increase in global surface temperature and suggest more frequent and more severe heat waves, meaning that crops are even more likely to be exposed to high temperature during their growth period (Pachauri et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2014</xref>). For instance, the maize cultivation area that suffers from stress-inducing levels of heat has been predicted to increase from 15% in 2000 to 44% in 2050 (Gourdji et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2013</xref>). Therefore, a better understanding of plant heat tolerance mechanisms and description of existing heat tolerance traits is urgently needed.</p><p>A number of basic processes, such as protein folding, maintenance of membrane stability, photosynthesis and assimilate metabolism, are shown to be affected by heat (Bokszczanin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2013</xref>). When considering long-term mildly high temperatures, representative of heat waves, life cycle stages clearly differ from each other regarding their sensitivity, with reproductive processes found to be more vulnerable than vegetative ones (Hall <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1992</xref>). This vulnerability applies especially to the meiotic to early microspore stages during pollen development, and early embryo development at 1&#x02013;3&#x000a0;days after fertilisation (Hedhly et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2009</xref>; Giorno et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2013</xref>; Bac-Molenaar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2015</xref>; M&#x000fc;ller and Rieu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2016</xref>). There seems to be considerable natural variation for heat tolerance in reproduction within plant species (Shpiler and Blum <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">1986</xref>; Patel and Hall <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1990</xref>; Redona et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2009</xref>; Bac-Molenaar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2015</xref>) and QTLs for a number of underlying traits have been identified (Esten Mason et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2011</xref>; Ye et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2012</xref>; Bac-Molenaar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2015</xref>). The underlying causal genes and their physiological effects have not yet been reported.</p><p>As an important horticultural crop grown for fruit production in subtropical climates, tomato has been extensively studied for heat tolerance at reproductive phase. Similar to other plant species, the reproduction is particularly sensitive to continuous mild heat (CMH; Kinet and Peet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1997</xref>). Under these conditions, male fertility and the position of the stigma relative to the anther cone seem to be major factors limiting fruit and seed set (Dane et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1991</xref>; Levy et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1978</xref>). A number of studies have assessed tomato cultivars for fruit set under CMH condition and identified relatively well-performing genotypes (Levy et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1978</xref>; Dane et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1991</xref>; Sato et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2000</xref>; Sato et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2004</xref>; Bhattarai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2016</xref>). The largest, multi-year characterisations by the Asian Vegetable Research and Development Center (AVRDC) identified 39 tolerant lines, some of which have already been utilised in tomato breeding programs (Ope&#x000f1;a et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1992</xref>; Scott et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">1995</xref>; Gardner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2000</xref>). However, to be able to efficiently use variation in heat tolerance for fundamental and applied aims, it is necessary to have knowledge on the genetic basis of the trait. Tomato QTLs associated with reproduction under heat were reported in two studies (Grilli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2007</xref>; Lin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2010</xref>), but identified markers and linkage groups were not associated with chromosomes, hampering wider use of the findings.</p><p>The objective of this study was to dissect the genetic architecture underlying tolerance of key reproductive traits to CMH. Tolerance regarding pollen viability was identified in tomato cultivar Nagcarlang, while tolerance with respect to total pollen number and stigma protusion was identified in cultivar NCHS-1. Here, in a forward genetic approach, an intraspecific F<sub>2</sub> population derived from these two phenotypically contrasting parents was used for QTL mapping.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Plant material</title><p>Tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) cultivars Nagcarlang (LA2661) and NCHS-1 (LA3847) were obtained from TGRC and crossed by using Nagcarlang as the mother plant. F<sub>2</sub> seeds were collected from a single F<sub>1</sub> individual, and 180 F<sub>2</sub> individuals were phenotyped for QTL analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Plant husbandry and heat stress phenotyping</title><p>Seeds of the two parental cultivars and the F<sub>2</sub> population were sown in standard commercial potting soil (Lentse Potgrond number 4, Horticoop, Katwijk, The Netherlands) with vermiculite scattered on top to cover the seeds. Ten days after sowing, seedlings were transplanted into separate pots with commercial potting soil and at 20&#x000a0;days after sowing, seedling were transferred further to 12-l pots filled with the same soil supplemented with slow-release fertiliser (4&#x000a0;g&#x000a0;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> Osmocote Exact Standard 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;M, Everris International B.V., Geldermalsen, The Netherlands). Plants were grown under standard greenhouse conditions with a 16-h light period (supplemented with artificial light from 600&#x000a0;W sodium lamps if natural light intensity fell below 250&#x000a0;&#x003bc;mol&#x000a0;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x000a0;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and a temperature of around 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in the day (minimum set to 20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) and 19&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in the night (minimum set to 17&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C).</p><p>When the first inflorescences were detectable by eye, all inflorescences were removed and plants were transferred to climate chambers with CMH condition (31&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C&#x000a0;day, 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C night; 14&#x000a0;h light, [&#x0223c;250&#x000a0;&#x003bc;mol&#x000a0;m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>&#x000a0;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> at plant height, Philips fluorescent lamps], 10&#x000a0;h dark; 70&#x02013;80% RH). The following phenotypical data were collected: inflorescence number (IN; i.e. number of inflorescences on top 5 branches present 3&#x000a0;weeks after start of CMH), flowers per inflorescence (FPI; i.e. average number of flowers on 3 randomly chosen inflorescences), anther length (AL; i.e. of 6 to 10 newly opened flowers), style length (SL; i.e. of 6 to 10 newly opened flowers), style protrusion (SP&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;SL&#x02013;AL; i.e. of 6 to 10 newly opened flowers), pollen viability (PV; i.e. in-vitro pollen germination percentage of 6 to 10 newly opened flowers), pollen number (PN; i.e. of 6 to 10 newly opened flowers) and female fertility (FF). To assess PV, anthers from newly opened flowers were cut into four pieces and pollen was incubated under wet condition for 30&#x000a0;min. Hydrated pollen were released by vortexing in 0.5&#x000a0;mL artificial germination medium (25% (<italic>w</italic>/<italic>v</italic>) PEG 4000, 5% (<italic>w</italic>/<italic>v</italic>) sucrose, 1&#x000a0;mM KNO<sub>3</sub>, 1&#x000a0;mM Ca(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>&#x000b7;4H<sub>2</sub>O, 1.6&#x000a0;mM H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>, 0.8&#x000a0;mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>&#x000b7;7H<sub>2</sub>O) and further incubated at room temperature for 1.5&#x000a0;h under constant rotation. Subsequently, the pollen suspension was loaded on a haemocytometer and pollen with tubes longer than the diameter was rated as germinated; about 100 pollens were evaluated for calculating germination rate. The number of pollens in 25 squares (0.1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L) of the haemocytometer were counted, and values were expressed as PN. After phenotype evaluation under CMH, plants were moved back to normal greenhouse conditions and four open flowers were immediately pollinated with NCHS-1 pollen from control condition. Seed number of fruits from hand pollination were counted to evaluate FF.</p><p>To confirm QTL qPV11, 31 F<sub>3</sub> progenitor plants from single F<sub>2</sub> plant were genotyped at the closest marker and phenotyped for PV under CMH using impedance flow cytometry with AMPHA Z30 (Amphasys AG, Lucerne, Switzerland). Per plant, pollen was analysed at four different days with three fresh flowers pooled as one sample per day.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>SNP genotyping</title><p>Single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) between Nagcarlang and NCHS-1 were identified using the SolCAP SNP array, according to Sim et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2012</xref>). Ninety-six SNPs (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">1</xref>), relatively evenly distributed over the tomato genome, were used for genotyping by KASP assays (LGC, Teddington, UK; Supplemental Table <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">1</xref>) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical and QTL analysis</title><p>Without explicit mention, all statistical analyses were done with R (version 3.2.0, R Core Team <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2015</xref>). Phenotypic differences between the two parental cultivars were compared by Welch (unequal variance assumption) two-sample <italic>t</italic>-test with <italic>t.test</italic> function. In addition, the descriptive statistics of F<sub>2</sub> population were calculated and trait frequency distributions were plotted. Pearson correlations between mother plants (F<sub>2</sub> plants) and cuttings, and among phenotypic traits in the F<sub>2</sub> population were calculated and visualised by using the Hmisc package (Frank and Harrell <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2015</xref>). PV data from the F<sub>3</sub> progenitor plants were analysed by ANOVA and Tukey post hoc test.</p><p>Phenotypic and genotypic data were integrated for QTL mapping with the R/qtl package (Broman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2003</xref>). Marker diagnostics was performed, and 12 low-quality markers were discarded. Furthermore, one marker assay showing strong segregation distortion (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001) and two marker assays showing high correlation with segments of different chromosomes were excluded. A genetic map was constructed by using the <italic>est.map</italic> function based on 81 informative markers. Standard interval mapping (SIM) and composite interval mapping (CIM) were applied for QTL detection. For SIM, the whole genome was scanned at steps of 1&#x000a0;cM by by using the <italic>scanone</italic> function with batch and climate chamber added as covariates. CIM was performed by using the <italic>cim</italic> function at 1&#x000a0;cM step, and three markers were selected as cofactors by forward selection. Expectation-maximisation was chosen as the solution-generating algorithm; other settings were left at their default values. Significance thresholds were generated for each trait by using the permutation test (&#x003b1;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.05, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1000; Churchill and Doerge, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1994</xref>). Both for mapping construction and QTL analysis, the Kosambi map function was used for the conversion of recombination frequency to genetic distance (Kosambi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1944</xref>). Since highly similar results were obtained from SIM and CIM, only CIM results were further analysed by using the <italic>fitqtl</italic> function to obtain the effects and interactions of QTLs.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Phenotypic variation under CMH condition</title><p>As tomato seed and fruit set under high temperature are complex traits, which reduces the power of QTL mapping, we analysed various subtraits known to contribute to reproductive success under high temperature, i.e. PV, PN, AL, SL, SP from the anther cone and FF. The tomato cultivars Nagcarlang and NCHS-1 were found to contrast for a number of these traits when grown under CMH (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). A bigger portion of the pollen from Nagcarlang was viable, whereas NCHS-1 produced a larger number of pollen, had a shorter style and less style protrusion. Moreover, Nagcarlang flowered significantly earlier, produced more inflorescences and formed more flowers per inflorescence than NCHS-1 under CMH.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Phenotype of the two parental lines and F<sub>2</sub> population under continuous mild heat condition</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="2">Nagcarlang</th><th colspan="2">NCHS-1</th><th colspan="7">F<sub>2</sub> population</th></tr><tr><th>Trait</th><th>
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th>Mean</th><th>
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th>Mean<sup>a</sup>
</th><th>
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th>Mean</th><th>SD</th><th>Minimum</th><th>Maximum</th><th>Kurtosis</th><th>Skewness</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>PV (%)</td><td>20</td><td>35.6</td><td>21</td><td>21.1**</td><td>180</td><td>25.7</td><td>11.4</td><td>2.7</td><td>61.8</td><td>0.71</td><td>0.51</td></tr><tr><td>PN (&#x000d7; 5000)</td><td>20</td><td>11.9</td><td>21</td><td>17.4**</td><td>180</td><td>13.1</td><td>4.3</td><td>4.2</td><td>28.1</td><td>0.73</td><td>0.87</td></tr><tr><td>FF</td><td>14</td><td>113.5</td><td>9</td><td>81.8*</td><td>122</td><td>119.7</td><td>28.3</td><td>22.0</td><td>185.5</td><td>0.51</td><td>&#x02212;0.23</td></tr><tr><td>SP(mm)</td><td>20</td><td>1.2</td><td>21</td><td>0.2**</td><td>180</td><td>1.0</td><td>0.7</td><td>&#x02212;0.7</td><td>3.3</td><td>&#x02212;0.08</td><td>0.32</td></tr><tr><td>SL (mm)</td><td>20</td><td>7.9</td><td>21</td><td>6.7**</td><td>180</td><td>7.9</td><td>0.8</td><td>5.6</td><td>10.1</td><td>0.06</td><td>&#x02212;0.02</td></tr><tr><td>AL (mm)</td><td>20</td><td>6.7</td><td>21</td><td>6.5</td><td>180</td><td>6.9</td><td>0.5</td><td>5.4</td><td>8.1</td><td>&#x02212;0.12</td><td>0.05</td></tr><tr><td>IN</td><td>20</td><td>24.8</td><td>18</td><td>12.2**</td><td>180</td><td>16.0</td><td>3.5</td><td>7.0</td><td>24.0</td><td>&#x02212;0.64</td><td>0.03</td></tr><tr><td>FPI</td><td>20</td><td>5.8</td><td>19</td><td>4.1**</td><td>180</td><td>5.2</td><td>0.9</td><td>2.7</td><td>7.7</td><td>&#x02212;0.14</td><td>0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>PV</italic> pollen viability, <italic>PN</italic> pollen number, <italic>FF</italic> female fertility, <italic>SP</italic> style protrusion, <italic>SL</italic> style length, <italic>AL</italic> anther length, <italic>IN</italic> inflorescence number, <italic>FPI</italic> flowers per inflorescence</p><p>*Significantly different from Nagcarlang, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.01; **<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.001</p><p>
<sup>a</sup>Differences between the means of Nagcarlang and NCHS-1 were compared by Welch&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p>In the F<sub>2</sub> population, phenotypic data for all traits scattered over wide continuous ranges, indicating quantitative inheritance (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). FPI, AL and SL followed normal distributions as their kurtosis and skewness values were close to 0. Distributions of the other traits skewed somewhat to the right except for FF (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Transgressive segregation was observed for AL and FF since the F<sub>2</sub> population mean for these two tratis was outside the ranges defined by the two parental population means (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p>Reliability of the phenotyping assay was verified by correlating phenotypic data on PV, PN, SL, AL and SP between 35 F<sub>2</sub> individuals and clones thereof. For all traits, strong and positive correlations were found, in particular for PV and SP (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). This indicates that in the used setup, these traits showed moderate to high heritability.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Trait correlations in the F<sub>2</sub> population</title><p>To assess associations among traits, Pearson correlation analysis was applied (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). For the size of floral organs, positive correlations were found between SP and SL, and between SL and AL. AL was also positively correlated with PN (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Also, a number of relatively weak associations were observed, such as the negative correlations between PV and SL, SP. Female fertility was not correlated to any other trait and therefore might be considered as an independent trait. In addition, positive correlation was found between IN and FPI.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Pearson correlations among phenotypic traits in the Nagcarlang &#x000d7; NCHS-1 F<sub>2</sub> population. Significance level: *<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.05; **<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.01; ***<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.001. Trait abbreviations: IN, inflorescence number; FPI, flowers per inflorescence; SL, style length; AL, anther length; SP, style protrusion; PV, pollen viability; PN, pollen number; FF, female fertility</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11032_2017_664_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>QTL analysis and their interaction</title><p>A single, highly significant QTL associated with pollen viability (qPV11) was detected on chromosome 11 and explained 36.3% of phenotypic variation (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). The additive and dominance effects of qPV11 were 9.1 and &#x02212;3.3, respectively. The allele contributing positively to pollen viability originated from Nagcarlang. PV of the three qPV11 genotypes, according to the closest marker, differed significantly from each other (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>). Likewise, a QTL for PN was identified on chromosome 7 (qPN7) and explained 18.6% of the phenotypic variation of the trait (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). The positive effect was contributed by the NCHS-1 allele. The additive and dominance effects were &#x02212;2.4 and 0.3, respectively.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Overview of mapped QTLs</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Trait</th><th rowspan="2">QTL</th><th colspan="6">Composite interval mapping (CIM)</th></tr><tr><th>Position<sup>a</sup>
</th><th>Closest SNP</th><th>LOD</th><th>a</th><th>d</th><th>
<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup> (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>PV</td><td>qPV11</td><td>11@19.4</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_36066</td><td>17.6</td><td>9.1</td><td>&#x02212;3.3</td><td>36.3</td></tr><tr><td>PN</td><td>qPN7</td><td>7@134.7</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_12139</td><td>8.0</td><td>&#x02212;2.4</td><td>0.3</td><td>18.6</td></tr><tr><td>SP</td><td>qSP1</td><td>1@16</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_8704</td><td>8.5</td><td>0.3</td><td>0.1</td><td>19.5</td></tr><tr><td/><td>qSP3</td><td>3@80.4</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_7942</td><td>12.9</td><td>0.4</td><td>0.2</td><td>28.0</td></tr><tr><td>AL</td><td>qAL1</td><td>1@70</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_42213</td><td>6.6</td><td>0.3</td><td>0.0</td><td>15.5</td></tr><tr><td/><td>qAL2</td><td>2@80.8</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_36287</td><td>4.8</td><td>&#x02212;0.2</td><td>0.0</td><td>11.6</td></tr><tr><td/><td>qAL7</td><td>7@134.7</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_12139</td><td>11.3</td><td>&#x02212;0.3</td><td>0.1</td><td>25.2</td></tr><tr><td>SL</td><td>qSL1</td><td>1@16</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_8704</td><td>10.1</td><td>0.4</td><td>0.0</td><td>22.7</td></tr><tr><td/><td>qSL2</td><td>2@80.8</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_36287</td><td>4.3</td><td>&#x02212;0.3</td><td>0.0</td><td>10.5</td></tr><tr><td/><td>qSL3</td><td>3@75.8</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_7942</td><td>6.7</td><td>0.3</td><td>0.3</td><td>15.8</td></tr><tr><td>FPI</td><td>qFPI1</td><td>1@40</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_13762</td><td>19.1</td><td>0.7</td><td>0.0</td><td>38.7</td></tr><tr><td>IN</td><td>qIN1</td><td>1@39</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_13762</td><td>9.7</td><td>2.1</td><td>0.2</td><td>21.9</td></tr><tr><td/><td>qIN8</td><td>8@95.3</td><td>solcap_snp_sl_15446</td><td>5.6</td><td>1.7</td><td>0.8</td><td>13.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>PV</italic> pollen viability, <italic>PN</italic> pollen number, <italic>SP</italic> style protrusion, <italic>AL</italic> anther length, <italic>SL</italic> style length, <italic>FPI</italic> flowers per inflorescence, <italic>IN</italic> inflorescence number, <italic>a</italic> additive effect (positive value indicates a positive effect from Nagcarlang, negative value indicates a positive effect from NCHS-1), <italic>d</italic> dominance effect</p><p>
<sup>a</sup>Postition is presented as chromosome@genetic position</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Genotype effects on pollen viability and inflorescence number QTL interaction effect. <bold>a</bold> Comparing PV by genotypes at the closet marker to qPV11. The A allele originates from NCHS-1 and the B from Nagcarlang. <bold>b</bold> Interaction of two QTLs for inflorescence number (IN). If one of the QTLs is homozygous to NCHS-1, the effect of the other one is small</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="11032_2017_664_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p><p>QTLs for SL, AL, SP, IN and FPI were also identified (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>). The two QTLs for SP, on chromosomes 1 (qSP1) and 3 (qSP3), colocalised with two QTLs for SL (qSL1, qSL3), while a third QTL for SL (qSL2) colocalised with a QTL for AL (qAL2). Of the two additional QTLs for AL, the stronger one (qAL7) colocalised with qPN7 for PN. Two QTLs were found for IN on chromosomes 1 and 8. Among the traits with multiple QTLs, only those for IN interacted: if qIN1 was homozygous for the NCHS-1 allele, the effect of qIN8 was relatively small, whereas it became larger with qIN1 having one or two Nagcarlang alleles (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Validation of the QTL for pollen viability heat tolerance</title><p>Thirty-one F<sub>3</sub> plants were generated from a single F<sub>2</sub> plant that was heterozygous for qPV11. Plants homozygous for the Nagcarlang allele of qPV11 produced pollen with significant higher viability than those homozygous for the NCHS-1 allele and heterozygous plants (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). No difference was found between the latter two genotypes.<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>QTL validation for pollen viabiliy under CMH</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Genotype<sup>a</sup>
</th><th>Number</th><th>Pollen viability<sup>b</sup>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>AA</td><td>16</td><td>47.7&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.6a</td></tr><tr><td>AB</td><td>9</td><td>40.9&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2a</td></tr><tr><td>BB</td><td>6</td><td>71&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.6b</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>a</sup>F<sub>3</sub> plants were grouped into three genotypes according to the closet marker to qPV11. &#x0201c;A,&#x0201d; allele from NCHS-1; &#x0201c;B,&#x0201d; allele from Nagcarlang</p><p>
<sup>b</sup>Pollen viability of the three genotypes was shown as &#x0201c;mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SE&#x0201d; and labelled with letters for significant difference (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x02264;&#x000a0;0.001)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Pollen viability and number</title><p>Pollination with a sufficient number of viable pollen is required for effective fertilisation in flowering plants. The number of viable pollen depends on the total number of pollen that are available at flower anthesis and the portion of them that are able to germinate and form a pollen tube. Both these factors were significantly decreased when tomato plants were grown under a long-term mild heat conditions. This is in accordance with previous reports, a number of which also showed a positive correlation between pollen performance and fruit set under a similar type of high-temperature regime (Akhtar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2012</xref>; Dane et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1991</xref>; Firon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2006</xref>; Levy et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1978</xref>; Pressman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2002</xref>; Sato et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2000</xref>; Sato et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2006</xref>). In the present study, the tomato accession Nagcarlang was found to have relatively high pollen thermotolerance, in agreement with findings of Dane et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1991</xref>). In a cross with cultivar NCHS-1, a single QTL for PV, qPV11, was detected on chromosome 11, accounting for a considerable proportion (36%) of phenotypic variation in the population. In homozygous state, the allele from Nagcarlang increased pollen viability under CHM with around 20% (Tables <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The continuous distribution of phenotypic values in the F<sub>2</sub> population and the portion of unexplained variance indicates that undetected small-effect genetic factors are likely to be involved. The position of qPV11 was unique with respect to those identified for other traits here. Interestingly, in the F<sub>3</sub> population, the NCHS-1 allele behaved dominant, suggesting that the qPV11 affects the sporophytic, rather than the gametophytic tissues. This agrees with the widely shared view that high temperature, as well as other stress factors, impair pollen development indirectly by affecting tapetal function (Parish et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2012</xref>; De Storme and Geelen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2014</xref>; M&#x000fc;ller and Rieu <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2016</xref>). Previouis QTLs for fruit setting under high temperature were not positioned on the tomato genome, and the subtraits affected were not studied (Grilli et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2007</xref>; Lin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2010</xref>). The only two QTLs for pollen fertility under long-term mild heat described so far come from a study in rice. In combination, these two QTLs explained a portion of phenotypic variance comparable to that of tomato qPV11 described here (Xiao et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2011</xref>). Dominance characteristics were not reported for the rice QTLs. Taken together, the results indicate that pollen thermotolerance in tomato and possibly other species may be determined to a large extend by relatively few major genes.</p><p>A negative effect of heat on PN was reported before (Firon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2006</xref>; Levy et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1978</xref>; Pressman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2002</xref>; Sato et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2000</xref>; Sato and Peet <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2005</xref>). Cultivar NCHS-1 was found to be relatively heat tolerant regarding this trait. Our QTL mapping identified one QTL for PN on chromosome 7, the positive effect coming from the NCHS-1 allele, which was also associated with AL, in line with the strong positive correlation between the two traits. The same association was recently found in wheat, where introduction of a chromosome from rye enhanced both anther size and pollen production (Nguyen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2015</xref>). It seems likely that a larger anther contains more pollen mother cells and is able to support more developing pollen. Interestingly, there was no evidence for a trade-off between PV and PN, indicating that the total number of viable pollen can be increased by genetic means. Whether the number of pollen produced and the number of pollen released from the anther at anthesis are independent traits, and which of the two most strongly limits reproduction under heat, is still unclear (Sato et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2000</xref>; Firon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">2006</xref>). Future analysis of the effect of qPN7 on fruit setting ability under high temperature should shed light on this.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Style and anther length and style protrusion</title><p>An inserted stigma is an important trait to ensure self-pollination in cultivated tomato (Rick and Dempsey <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">1969</xref>; Chen and Tanksley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2004</xref>). Growth at high temperature may lead to protrusion of the style out of the anther cone (Levy et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1978</xref>; Sato et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2006</xref>). SP depends on the interaction between AL and SL (Chen and Tanksley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2004</xref>). In our mapping population, SP was positively correlated with SL and negatively with AL, indicating both anther and style have effects on the extent of SP. However, the much stronger correlation between SP and SL indicates that an elongated style is the main reason for SP under heat stress. Association among these floral structure traits is also reflected by the underlying genetic architecture: both QTLs for SP colocalised with QTLs for SL. By contrast, a QTL on chromosome 2 affected both style and anther length, in the same direction, explaining why it did not contribute to variation in SP. The relatively simple genetic architecture of SP at high temperature is in line with high heritability found in previous genetic studies (Levy et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1978</xref>; El Ahmadi and Stevens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1979</xref>). An protruded stigma phenotype is observed often in self-incompatible wild tomato relatives to facilitate outcrossing (Chen and Tanksley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2004</xref>). To reveal how an inserted stigma evolved from the wild ancestors, Chen and Tanksley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2004</xref>) identified several QTLs for anther and style morphology. One of them (<italic>se2.1</italic>) was further mapped to a short region on chromosome 2. Within that region, loci for style length and stamen length were confirmed. S<italic>tyle2.1</italic> was cloned and turned out to encode a transcription factor regulating cell elongation; a mutation in the promoter region of <italic>Style2.1</italic> was responsible for low activity of the gene during flower development (Chen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2007</xref>). Our QTLs on chromosome 2 affecting SL and AL under heat were mapped to the same region as <italic>se2.1</italic>, suggesting that the mechanisms responsible for anther and style development under normal and high temperature conditions are at least partially conserved. The two other QTLs related to SP and SL on chromosome 1 and 3 did not colocalise with any previously identified QTL under normal temperature, indicating additional, distinct mechanisms for style development upon heat stress that lead to SP.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Formation of inflorescences and flowers</title><p>The total number of flowers produced by a tomato plant correlates with yield per plant under CMH condition (Bhattarai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2016</xref>). We examined flower production by assessing the number of inflorescences and number of flowers per inflorescence. The positive correlation between these two traits suggests a common physiological basis and is in line with colocalisation of the main QTLs, qIN1 and qFPI1, on chromosome 1. A number of studies have been done on reproductive traits under normal conditions and several QTLs responsible for flowering time and FPI were published (Grandillo and Tanksley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1996</xref>; Georgiady et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2002</xref>; Doganlar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2002</xref>). Among these, Grandillo and Tanksley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1996</xref>) reported that one of the QTLs for days to first flower was close to RFLP marker TG125 on chromosome 1. Later, a QTL for FPI was also found to be close to TG125 (Doganlar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2002</xref>). This marker is very close to the QTLs identified here, suggesting that inflorescence and flower production under normal and heat condition are controlled by the same genes. Indeed, we have noticed that IN was not significantly influenced by the CMH regime (data not shown). FPI was reduced by CMH, but both parents reacted similarly (i.e. no genotype-temperature interaction), making it unlikely for heat-specific QTLs to be identified. In line with the above, El Ahmadi and Stevens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1979</xref>) found that in a germplas set, FPI under normal and mildly elevated growth temperatures correlated strongly and the traits were highly heritable.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Implications for tomato heat tolerance breeding</title><p>The QTLs identified here are good candidates for cloning to generate knowledge on the genes involved in determining reproductive heat tolerance levels. This kind of approach is of great importance for understanding the fundamental molecular physiological mechanisms of the tolerance. However, even without this information, the identified QTLs can directly be tested in breeding programs. As an advantage, most of the QTLs mapped in this study showed additive behaviour. Nearly no epistatic interactions were found, except for the two QTLs for IN, in which case pyramiding of favourable alleles from different loci may give rise to superior offspring.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec17"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="11032_2017_664_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>Supplementary Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Phenotype distributions for the F<sub>2</sub> population. a Inflorescence number (IN); b Flowers per inflorescence (FPI); c Style length (SL); d Anther length (AL); e Style protrusion (SP); f Pollen viability (PV); g Pollen number (PN); h Female fertility (FF). Mean values of two parents were indicated by arrows. P1, Nagcarlang; P2, NCHS-1. (DOCX 91&#x000a0;kb).</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="11032_2017_664_MOESM2_ESM.docx"><label>Supplementary Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Scatterplots of phenotypic data from mother plants and their cuttings. Correlations (r) and number of observations (n), as well as linear regression were shown for earch trait. Correlations were significant in all cases (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001). <bold>a</bold> Pollen viability (PV); <bold>b</bold> Pollen number (PN); <bold>c</bold> Style length (SL); <bold>d</bold> Anther length (AL); <bold>e</bold> Style protrusion (SP). (DOCX 138&#x000a0;kb).</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="11032_2017_664_MOESM3_ESM.docx"><label>Supplementary Fig. 3</label><caption><p>LOD profiles of QTL mapping for all traits. For each trait, LOD scores are indicated along all 12 chromosomes. The horizontal line indicates the significance threshold. PV, pollen viability; PN, pollen number; SP, style protrusion; AL, anther length; SL, style length; FPI, flowers per inflorescence; IN, Inflorescence number. (DOCX 150&#x000a0;kb).</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="11032_2017_664_MOESM4_ESM.docx"><label>Supplementary Table 1</label><caption><p>Primer sequences for KASP SNP genotyping assays. (DOCX 22&#x000a0;kb).</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s11032-017-0664-2) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors wish to thank Gerard van der Weerden (Experimental Garden and Genebank, Radboud University, Nijmegen, The Netherlands) and the greenhouse staff for taking excellent care of the plants. We appreciate receiving technical assistance from Mieke Wolters-Arts and Marieke Ykema. This work was supported by the China Scholarship Council (grant number 201207565002, to JX), the Dutch Topsector Horticulture and Starting Materials (grant number 2013-H320, to IR) and the European Commission (Marie Curie Initial Training Network: Solanaceae Pollen Thermotolarance/SPOT-ITN, grant number 289220, to IR).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>JX, WV, GB and IR conceived and designed the study. JX acquired the data. JX, ND, MR and IR analysed and interpreted the data. JX and IR wrote the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Ethical standards</title><p>This article does not contain any studies with human participants or animals performed by any of the authors.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ansary</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crucial reproductive characters as screening indices for tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) under high temperature stress</article-title><source>J Crop Weed</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>117</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bac-Molenaar</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fradin</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>FFM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide association mapping of fertility reduction upon heat stress reveals developmental stage-specific QTLs in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1857</fpage><lpage>1874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.15.00248</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26163573?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26163573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhattarai</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Talukdar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of yield and yield-attributing traits for high temperature resistance in tomato</article-title><source>Int J Veg Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>5260</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bokszczanin</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><collab>Solanaceae Pollen Thermotolerance Initial Training Network (SPOT-ITN) Consortium</collab><name><surname>Fragkostefanakis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspectives on deciphering mechanisms underlying plant heat stress response and thermotolerance</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>315</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2013.00315</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23986766?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23986766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broman</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Churchill</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>R/qtl: QTL mapping in experimental crosses</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2003</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg112</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12724300?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-resolution mapping and functional analysis of se2.1: a major stigma exsertion quantitative trait locus associated with the evolution from allogamy to autogamy in the genus <italic>lycopersicon</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2004</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>1563</fpage><lpage>1573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.103.022558</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15579707?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15579707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Changes in regulation of a transcription factor lead to autogamy in cultivated tomatoes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2007</year><volume>318</volume><fpage>643</fpage><lpage>645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1148428</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17962563?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17962563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Churchill GA, Doerge RW (1994) Empirical threshold values for quantitative trait mapping. Genetics 138:963&#x02013;971</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dane</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambliss</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fruit set, pollen fertility, and combining ability of selected tomato genotypes under high-temperature field conditions</article-title><source>J Am Soc Hortic Sci</source><year>1991</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>906</fpage><lpage>910</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Storme</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Geelen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of environmental stress on male reproductive development in plants: biological processes and molecular mechanisms</article-title><source>Plant Cell Environ</source><year>2014</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pce.12142</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23731015?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23731015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doganlar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Frary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ku</surname><given-names>H-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping quantitative trait loci in inbred backcross lines of <italic>Lycopersicon pimpinellifolium</italic> (LA1589)</article-title><source>Genome</source><year>2002</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1189</fpage><lpage>1202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/g02-091</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12502266?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12502266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Driedonks</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Vriezen</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Breeding for plant heat tolerance at vegetative and reproductive stages</article-title><source>Plant Reprod</source><year>2016</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00497-016-0275-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26874710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26874710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Ahmadi</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of high temperature fruit set in tomato</article-title><source>J Am Soc Hortic Sci</source><year>1979</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>696</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esten Mason</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beecher</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic loci linking improved heat tolerance in wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) to lower leaf and spike temperatures under controlled conditions</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2011</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-011-0349-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Firon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaked</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Peet</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pollen grains of heat tolerant tomato cultivars retain higher carbohydrate concentration under heat stress conditions</article-title><source>Sci Hortic (Amsterdam)</source><year>2006</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>212</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2006.03.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Frank E, Harrell J (2015) Hmisc: Harrell Miscellaneous</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Sun Leaper&#x0201d;, a hybrid tomato, and its parent, NC HS-1</article-title><source>Hortscience</source><year>2000</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>960</fpage><lpage>961</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georgiady</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitkus</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of traits distinguishing outcrossing and self-pollinating forms of currant tomato, <italic>Lycopersicon pimpinellifolium</italic> (Jusl.) Mill</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2002</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12019247?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12019247</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giorno</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolters-Arts</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieu</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ensuring reproduction at high temperatures: the heat stress response during anther and pollen development</article-title><source>Plants</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/plants2030489</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27137389?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27137389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gourdji</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sibley</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobell</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global crop exposure to critical high temperatures in the reproductive period: historical trends and future projections</article-title><source>Environ Res Lett</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>024041</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1748-9326/8/2/024041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grandillo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanksley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QTL analysis of horticultural traits differentiating the cultivated tomato from the closely related species <italic>Lycopersicon pimpinellifolium</italic></article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00224033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24166620?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24166620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grilli</surname><given-names>GVG</given-names></name><name><surname>Braz</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemos</surname><given-names>EGM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QTL identification for tolerance to fruit set in tomato by fAFLP markers</article-title><source>Crop Breed Appl Biotechnol</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12702/1984-7033.v07n03a02</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hall AE (1992) Breeding for heat tolerance. In: Plant breeding reviews. Wiley, p 129</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedhly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hormaza</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global warming and sexual plant reproduction</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2008.11.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19062328?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19062328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>UC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heat stress in crop plants: its nature, impacts and integrated breeding strategies to improve heat tolerance</article-title><source>Plant Breed</source><year>2014</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pbr.12217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kinet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Peet</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wien</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tomato</article-title><source>The physiology of vegetable crops</source><year>1997</year><publisher-loc>Wallingford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cab International</publisher-name><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>258</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosambi</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The estimation of map distances from recombination values</article-title><source>Ann Eugenics</source><year>1944</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-1809.1943.tb02321.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabinowitch</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kedar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological and physiological characters affecting flower drop and fruit set of tomatoes at high temperatures</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>1978</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00039137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative trait loci influencing fruit-related characteristics of tomato grown in high-temperature conditions</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2010</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10681-010-0147-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">M&#x000fc;ller F, Rieu I (2016) Acclimation to high temperature during pollen development. Plant Reprod:1&#x02013;12. doi:10.1007/s00497-016-0282-x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleury</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Addition of rye chromosome 4R to wheat increases anther length and pollen grain number</article-title><source>Theor Appl Genet</source><year>2015</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>953</fpage><lpage>964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00122-015-2482-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25716820?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25716820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ope&#x000f1;a RT, Chen JT, Kuo CG, Chen HM (1992) Genetic and physiological aspects of tropical adaptation in tomato. In: Adaptation of food crops to temperature and water stress: proceedings of an international symposium. Pp 13&#x02013;18</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pachauri RK, Allen MR, Barros VR, et al. (2014) Climate Change 2014: Synthesis Report. Contribution of Working Groups I, II and III to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parish</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Phan</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Iacuone</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tapetal development and abiotic stress: a centre of vulnerability</article-title><source>Funct Plant Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/FP12090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genotypic variation and classification of cowpea for reproductive responses to high temperature under long photoperiods</article-title><source>Crop Sci</source><year>1990</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>614</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2135/cropsci1990.0011183X003000030029x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pressman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Peet</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pharr</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of heat stress on tomato pollen characteristics is associated with changes in carbohydrate concentration in the developing anthers</article-title><source>Ann Bot</source><year>2002</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>631</fpage><lpage>636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcf240</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12466104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12466104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Core Team (2015) R: a language and environment for statistical computing</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Redona</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Manigbas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Laza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identifying heat tolerant rice genotypes under different environments</article-title><source>SABRAO Journal of Breeding and Genetics</source><year>2009</year><volume>2009</volume><fpage>41</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rick</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dempsey</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Position of the stigma in relation to fruit setting of the tomato</article-title><source>Bot Gaz</source><year>1969</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/336488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peet</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of moderately elevated temperature stress on the timing of pollen release and its germination in tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic> Mill.)</article-title><source>J Hortic Sci Biotechnol</source><year>2005</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14620316.2005.11511885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peet</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological factors limit fruit set of tomato (<italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic> Mill.) under chronic, mild heat stress. Plant</article-title><source>Cell Environ</source><year>2000</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3040.2000.00589.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peet</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altered flower retention and developmental patterns in nine tomato cultivars under elevated temperature</article-title><source>Sci Hortic (Amsterdam)</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scienta.2003.10.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Moderate increase of mean daily temperature adversely affects fruit set of <italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic> by disrupting specific physiological processes in male reproductive development</article-title><source>Ann Bot</source><year>2006</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>731</fpage><lpage>738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcl037</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16497700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16497700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Equinox&#x0201d; heat-tolerant hybrid tomato</article-title><source>Hortscience</source><year>1995</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>648</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shpiler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential reaction of wheat cultivars to hot environments</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>1986</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00021856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Durstewitz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Plieske</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of a large snp genotyping array and generation of high-density genetic maps in tomato</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e40563</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0040563</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22802968?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22802968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantitative trait loci associated with pollen fertility under high temperature stress at flowering stage in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic>)</article-title><source>Rice Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1672-6308(11)60028-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Argayoso</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Redo&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping QTL for heat tolerance at flowering stage in rice using SNP markers</article-title><source>Plant Breed</source><year>2012</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0523.2011.01924.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>